<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/183"><dc:title>Blick auf Murnau mit Kirche</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>183</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:date>1910</dc:date><dcterms:created>1910</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">The painting 'View of Murnau with Church' by the Russian artist Wassily Kandinsky shows a landscape with the village of Murnau situated in the middle of the Bavarian hills. A church and some houses, as well as trees and hills, can be distinguished in this landscape. Kandinsky did not depict the theme in a way that is true to nature. He left out the details, particularly in the buildings, painting the larger shapes in a free style which is unrelated to the actual architecture. For example, the church tower is at a great angle and the use of colour is also very free: the colours are much brighter than in a real landscape. Furthermore, Kandinsky did not relate the colour to a specific form or to an object. He placed the various colours next to each other within a single design, sometimes with a great deal of contrast, at other times, merging together. 'Kandinsky was much more influenced by his feelings when he chose colours and form than by what his eye perceived. His brushstroke style is clearly recognizable with the theme placed onto the canvas directly, not in several layers. These are the characteristics of Expressionism and Kandinsky was one of the founders of the group of Expressionist artists known as “Der blaue Reiter”. In 1912, he published the eponymous almanac together with Franz Marc. This contained articles about new movements in the arts and music, reproductions of contemporary modern paintings, as well as examples of folk art, medieval art and ethnic art. These art forms were not concerned with realistic representations of the real world, but with a personal, ritual or spiritual experience. Kandinsky considered the artist’s “inner need” to be his only true guideline. 'For him, music was the highest form of art, because music was completely abstract and totally separate from any references to reality. He wanted to paint in the way that music is composed: with sounds, tones and rhythms. In 1913 his work became completely abstract. The visual means such as lines, planes, colours, rhythm and structure were used independently, referring to nothing other than themselves.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>110,6 x 120 x 4,9 cm (incl.lijst / frame) 96 x 105,5 x 2,4 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Wassily Kandinsky</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het schilderij 'Blick auf Murnau mit Kirche' van de Russische kunstenaar Wassily Kandinsky toont een landschap met een dorpje. Het is het dorp Murnau gelegen te midden van de Beierse heuvels. In dit landschap zijn een kerk en wat huizen evenals bomen en heuvels te herkennen. Kandinsky geeft zijn motief niet natuurgetrouw weer. Details laat hij achterwege, met name in de gebouwen; de grotere vormen zet hij op een vrije, niet aan de werkelijke architectuur gebonden manier neer. De kerktoren bijvoorbeeld staat erg scheef. Ook zijn kleurgebruik is heel vrij. De kleuren zijn veel feller dan in een werkelijk landschap. Bovendien bindt Kandinsky de kleur niet aan een specifieke vorm of aan een object. Hij zet verschillende kleuren tegen elkaar aan binnen één grote vorm, soms sterk contrasterend, dan weer meer overvloeiend. 'Kandinsky wordt bij zijn keuzen voor kleur en vorm veel meer geleid door zijn gevoel, dan door wat zijn oog waarneemt. Zijn penseelstreek is duidelijk herkenbaar. Het motief wordt direct, en niet laag over laag, op het doek gezet. Dit zijn kenmerken van het expressionisme. Kandinsky is één van de oprichters van de expressionistische kunstenaarsgroep 'der blaue Reiter'. In 1912 geeft hij samen met Franz Marc de gelijknamige almanak uit. Deze bevat artikelen over nieuwe richtingen in de beeldende kunst en muziek, reproducties van eigentijdse, moderne schilderijen maar ook voorbeelden van volkskunst, middeleeuwse en uitheemse kunst. Bij deze vormen van kunst gaat het niet om een natuurgetrouwe afbeelding van iets uit de werkelijkheid, maar om een persoonlijke, rituele of spirituele beleving. Kandinsky vindt een 'innerlijke noodzaak' de enige ware leidraad voor een kunstenaar. 'Muziek is voor Kandinsky de hoogste vorm van kunst, omdat muziek volkomen abstract is, helemaal los staat van verwijzingen naar de werkelijkheid. Hij wil schilderen zoals muziek gecomponeerd wordt: met klanken, tonen, ritmen. Rond 1913 wordt zijn werk geheel abstract. Beeldende middelen als lijn, vlak, kleur, ritme en structuur worden dan zelfstandig gebruikt: ze verwijzen naar niets anders dan naar zichzelf.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/183"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/183"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C524"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0183-01.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0183-01.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>