<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2577"><dc:identifier>2577</dc:identifier><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1971</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (PAL, zwart-wit, geluid)</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (PAL, black-and-white, sound), duration 2:20 min.</dc:type><dc:creator>John Baldessari</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">These two anecdotes are paradigmatic of Baldessari's investigations of language systems and meaning through disjunction and juxtaposition. In a strategy that recurs throughout his work, Baldessari presents the pieces as lessons, appearing first as teacher and then as student. Some Words I Mispronounce is an absurdist exercise in which he writes a series of words on a blackboard — poor, cask, bade, Beelzebub, bough, sword. The words are never pronounced. The second lesson juxtaposes two sign systems, language and music. As instructed by a foreign language lesson book (a found object), Baldessari repeats a sentence — "You tell me what I do" — according to notes on a musical scale. His intonations are exaggerated, his delivery is deadpan, and the phrase is rendered absurd. Ironically, the literalness of the phrase as articulated, and the reduction of English to basic units of sound and pronunciation, nullifies the point of the lesson — to speak the language fluently.</dc:description><dc:title>Some Words I Mispronounce</dc:title><dcterms:created>1971</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Deze twee anekdotes zijn exemplarisch voor Baldessari's onderzoek naar taalsystemen en betekenis met behulp van ontleding en combinatie. Volgens een strategie die in zijn hele werk opduikt, presenteert Baldessari de delen in de vorm van lessen, waarin hij eerst als docent en vervolgens als student verschijnt. Some Words I Mispronounce is een absurdistisch werk waarin hij een reeks woorden op een schoolbord schrijft: ‘poor, cask, bade, Beelzebub, bough, sword’. De woorden worden nooit uitgesproken. In de tweede les worden twee tekensystemen, taal en muziek, gecombineerd. Volgens de instructies van een lesboek Engels als vreemde taal (een gevonden voorwerp) herhaalt Baldessari een zin – "You tell me what I do" (jij vertelt me wat ik doe) – aan de hand van noten op een toonladder. Zijn intonatie is overdreven, zijn voordracht is sec en de zin wordt absurd. Ironisch genoeg ondermijnt de letterlijke herhaling van de zin en de reductie van het Engels tot basiseenheden van geluid en uitspraak het doel van de les: het vloeiend spreken van de taal.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:02:20</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2577"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2577"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2878"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2577-02.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2577-02.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>