<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2351"><dc:date>1997</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>2351</dc:identifier><dcterms:created>1997</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Vexation Island' is a short film that is screened in a loop. From above you see a small island of white sand and palm trees in a blue sea near the mainland. You can hear the sound of wind and waves. Close-ups alternate with panoramic views. There is a man lying on the beach near to a coconut palm. He has a large wound on his forehead. A wooden post with a parrot stands at an angle in the sand. The man opens his eyes, the parrot screeches and points with his wing. The man stands up, looks out over the sea, turns round, walks up to the coconut palm and starts to shake it. A coconut is shaken loose and falls on the man’s forehead. The man falls, the coconut rolls towards the sea. The falling and rolling are slowed down and are shown several times from different camera positions. Then you see the island again from above and the film begins again. 'It was recorded with a very professional camera team. It is somewhere in between an advertisement for a tropical product or a distant holiday destination and the start of a feature film with a shipwrecked protagonist like Robinson Crusoe. Crusoe, who cultivates the island where he is washed up as well as possible, is saved in the end. However, for Graham who acts in this film himself, there is no redemption. He endlessly comes to and is then knocked out again. 'Rodney Graham’s work is very varied. Usually he bases his work on existing art, such as a book, a piece of music or a sculpture, intervening in these in a way which corresponds to the original work in terms of form, but which changes the meaning or even undermines it. For example, he will insert a piece of text in a book or add notes to a composition. He often works with the principle of the loop: the end joins onto the beginning. In Vexation Island this happens both in terms of content, and as regards the form.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">35mm film transferred to video (NTSC, colour, sound, loop), duration 13:40 min.</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Vexation Island' is een korte film die in loop wordt getoond. Je ziet van bovenaf een klein eiland met wit zand en palmbomen, in een blauwe zee, nabij het vaste land. Je hoort het geluid van wind en golven. Close-ups en overzichtshots wisselen elkaar af. Er ligt een man op het strand, vlakbij een kokospalm. Hij heeft een grote wond op zijn voorhoofd. Een houten vaatje met een papegaai erop staat schuin in het zand. De man opent zijn ogen. De papegaai roept en wijst met zijn vleugel. De man staat op, kijkt over zee, draait zich om, loopt naar de kokospalm en begint hieraan te schudden. Er laat een kokosnoot los. Deze valt op het voorhoofd van de man. De man valt. De kokosnoot rolt naar zee. Het vallen en rollen worden vertraagd en verschillende malen, vanuit diverse camerastandpunten weergegeven. Dan zie je weer het eiland van bovenaf. Het filmpje begint opnieuw. 'Het filmpje is opgenomen met een zeer professionele cameraploeg. Het houdt het midden tussen een reclamespot voor een tropisch product of verre reis en het begin van een speelfilm met als hoofdpersoon een schipbreukeling a la Robinson Crusoë. Crusoë, die het eiland waarop hij aanspoelt zo goed mogelijk cultiveert, wordt uiteindelijk gered. Voor Graham echter, die in dit filmpje zelf acteert, is er geen verlossing. Hij blijft eindeloos bijkomen en weer knock-out gaan. 'Rodney Graham maakt zeer divers werk. Meestal baseert hij zijn werken op bestaande kunst, bijv. een boek, een muziekstuk of een sculptuur. Hierin doet hij een ingreep die qua vorm aansluit bij het oorspronkelijke werk, maar de betekenis ervan verandert of zelfs ondermijnt. Hij last bijvoorbeeld in een boek een stuk tekst in, of voegt noten toe aan een compositie. Hij werkt vaak met het principe van de lus of loop: het einde sluit weer aan bij het begin. Dit gebeurt bij 'Vexation Island' zowel inhoudelijk als formeel.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">35mm film overgezet op video (NTSC, kleur, geluid, loop)</dc:type><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:09:12</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Vexation Island</dc:title><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Rodney Graham</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2351"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2351.JPG"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2351.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2351"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2501"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>