<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3003"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3003-03.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3003-03.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C8850"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3003"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3003"><dc:description xml:lang="en">'‘Museum Songspiel: The Netherlands 20XX’ tells the story of a group of immigrants fleeing deportation. The film follows the immigrants struggle as they seek refuge in the museum, under the assumption that it is the last bastion of free speech and support for the politically oppressed. When the refugees are discovered a cogent, stimulating conversation develops between the director of the museum, the curator, the artist, a TV reporter and the museum attendants. 'Chto Delat? draw on the mode of ‘songspiel’ employed in musical theatre developed by playwright Bertolt Brecht and composer Kurt Weill in the early twentieth century. A ‘songspiel’ presents political and social concerns through the accessible and often humorous form of song.The elegiac music score composed by Mikhail Krutik is sung by the museum attendants. 'The film is an eerie reminder that any system can become monstrous if its masters seal it off from challenge and change and if popular belief in it is blind and fanatical. 'Chto Delat? draw on the mode of ‘songspiel’ employed in musical theatre developed by playwright Bertolt Brecht and composer Kurt Weill in the early twentieth century, which presents political and social concerns through the accessible and often tragicomic form of song. In this manner Museum Songspiel: The Netherlands 20XX reframes the discrepancy between art and politics. Unity and cohesion are achieved through an elegiac music score composed by Mikhail Krutik. '- Exhibition text 2011 -</dc:description><dcterms:created>2011</dcterms:created><dc:identifier>3003</dc:identifier><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Museum Songspiel: The Netherlands 20XX</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (PAL, colour, sound), duration 25:36 min.</dc:type><dc:date>2011</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'‘Museum Songspiel: The Netherlands 20XX’ vertelt het verhaal van een groep immigranten die aan deportatie probeert te ontkomen. De film volgt de immigranten die hun toevlucht zoeken in een museum, in de veronderstelling dat deze een laatste bolwerk is van vrije meningsuiting en hulp biedt aan de politiek onderdrukten. Als de vluchtelingen worden ontdekt ontspint zich een pakkend en stimulerend gesprek tussen de directeur van het museum, de conservator, de kunstenaar, een televisieverslaggever en de suppoosten. 'Chto Delat? hanteert het genre van het ‘songspiel’, zoals dat begin twintigste eeuw door toneelschrijver Bertolt Brecht en componist Kurt Weil voor het muziektheater werd ontwikkeld. In een ‘songspiel’ worden politieke en maatschappelijke kwesties gepresenteerd in de vorm van toegankelijke en vaak humoristische liederen. De weemoedige begeleidende muziek gecomponeerd door Mikhail Krutik wordt gezongen door de suppoosten. 'De film herinnert ons er op griezelige wijze aan dat elk systeem monsterlijke vormen kan aannemen als de mensen er blindelings en fanatiek achteraan lopen en degenen die het voor het zeggen hebben geen enkele ruimte meer bieden voor twijfel of verandering. 'Chto Delat? hanteert het genre van het ‘songspiel’, zoals dat begin twintigste eeuw door toneelschrijver Bertolt Brecht en componist Kurt Weill voor het muziektheater werd ontwikkeld en waarbij politieke en maatschappelijke kwesties door een koor worden voorzien van tragikomisch commentaar. Op deze manier werpt Museum Songspiel: The Netherlands 20XX nieuw licht op de kloof tussen de kunst en het politieke. De weemoedige begeleidende muziek, gecomponeerd door Mikhail Krutik geeft het geheel eenheid en samenhang. '- Tenstoonstellingstekst 2011 -</dc:description><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:25:36</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (PAL, kleur, geluid)</dc:type><dc:creator>Chto Delat</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>