<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2328"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">lakvernis op foto op hout</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">varnish on photograph on wood</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Five maxime: Bar' by Niek Kemps is a wooden object with photographs printed on it. The whole thing has been varnished with a shiny varnish. It consists of a narrow central section which is attached to the wall and two side sections folding into the space in the same direction. The top and bottom of the parts are at an angle and look as if they have been twisted. The outer sections can be seen from both sides. 'Five maxims: Bar' is part of the 'Five maxims'. Kemps made this installation consisting of five wall objects in 1986 for the stairwell and nursery of a house in Ghent, in the context of the exhibition 'Chambres d’Amis'. After this, the wall objects were sent to different places. The Van Abbemuseum has two: 'Five maxims: Bar' and 'Five maxims: Refreshments on the ground floor'. 'Kemps’ works can never be seen from a single perspective. He usually works with transparent and reflecting materials, often in several layers one over the other. Sometimes they are covered with photographic images, resulting in complex pictures. It is not only the object and possibly the illustrations on these that are the subject of perception, but the space where the work is located and the visitors who are present there are also included in the work by means of reflections or peep-through views. The photographs which Kemps printed on the 'Five maxims' were taken in the place where the objects were to be attached, so that for the viewer there could be interaction between the actual space, its reflection in the shiny surface of the object and the photographic record of the same space on the object. 'The complexity of Kemps’ work has a disorienting effect. The viewer is constantly forced to revise his position, both literally and metaphorically. Kemps saw this as a characteristic of our current world. In the past, there was a general world view, formulated on the basis of the prevailing religion or philosophy, but nowadays there is a whole range of knowledge and information, as well as possible points of view based on these. The individual can choose a position in this but cannot avoid the possible alternatives. Niek Kemps translates these ideas into an image.</dc:description><dc:creator>Niek Kemps</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1986</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Vijf maximes: Bar' van Niek Kemps is een houten object waarop foto's afgedrukt zijn. Het geheel is glanzend gelakt. Het bestaat uit een smal middendeel dat aan de wand bevestigd wordt, en twee zijdelen die in dezelfde richting de ruimte inbuigen. De boven- en onderkant van de delen zijn schuin en vertonen een verloop alsof ze getordeerd zijn. De zijdelen kunnen van beide kanten bekeken worden. 'Vijf maximes: Bar' is een onderdeel van de 'Vijf Maximes'. Deze installatie van vijf wandobjecten maakte Kemps in 1986 voor het trappenhuis en de kinderkamer van een woning in Gent, in het kader van de tentoonstelling 'Chambres d'Amis'. Daarna hebben de wandobjecten verschillende bestemmingen gekregen. Het Van Abbemuseum bezit er twee: 'Vijf maximes: Bar' en 'Vijf maximes: Refreshments on the ground floor'. 'Werken van Kemps zijn nooit vanuit één standpunt te overzien. Hij werkt meestal met transparante en reflecterende materialen, vaak in lagen achter elkaar. Soms zijn deze voorzien van fotografische afbeeldingen. Hierdoor ontstaan er complexe beelden. Niet alleen het object en eventueel de afbeeldingen daarop zijn het voorwerp van waarneming. Ook de ruimte waarin het werk zich bevindt en de daarin aanwezige bezoekers worden via spiegelingen of doorzichten in het werk opgenomen. De foto's die Kemps op de 'Vijf Maximes' afdrukte, zijn genomen op de plaats waar de objecten bevestigd zouden worden. Zo kon er voor de beschouwer een interactie ontstaan tussen de werkelijke ruimte, de weerspiegeling daarvan in het glanzende oppervlak van het object, en de fotografische afbeelding van diezelfde ruimte op het object. 'De complexiteit van Kemps' werk leidt tot desoriëntatie. De kijker wordt telkens gedwongen zijn standpunt te herzien, letterlijk en figuurlijk. Kemps ziet dit als een kenmerk van onze huidige leefwereld. Vroeger was er sprake van een algemeen wereldbeeld, geformuleerd vanuit de heersende religie of filosofie. Tegenwoordig is er een veelheid aan kennis en informatie en van daaruit aan mogelijke standpunten. Het individu kan daarin positie kiezen, maar kan niet om mogelijke alternatieven heen. Niek Kemps vertaalt deze gedachten naar een beeld.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>86 x 120 x 58 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:date>1986</dc:date><dc:identifier>2328</dc:identifier><dc:title>Vijf maximes: Bar</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2328"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2480"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2328.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2328"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2328.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>