<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3225"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C10523"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3225"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3225-02.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3225-02.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3225"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">urinoir, kunsthistorische referenties, porcelein brandschilderverf</dc:type><dcterms:created>(2009) productie / production 2016</dcterms:created><dc:date>(2009) productie / production 2016</dc:date><dc:title>Arte Útil</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 1917 Marcel Duchamp placed a urinal on its back in an exhibition hall. By depriving the object of its practical use, signing it and presenting it as a sculptural object, he declared it to be art. Tania Bruguera installs such an autographed urinal in the museum’s public toilet. By restoring the urinal to its original purpose, she invites us to consider the usefulness of art and its function within society. 'The authorship of the original work has recently been called into question. Most likely it is not by Duchamp, but by Baroness Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven. '[2018]</dc:description><dc:creator>Tania Bruguera</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">urinal, art historical references, porcelain enamel</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Marcel Duchamp presenteerde in 1917 een niet aangesloten urinoir, ruggelings op een sokkel in een tentoonstellingsruimte. Door het sanitaire voorwerp zijn praktisch waarde te ontnemen, het te signeren en het als sculpturaal object te introduceren, verklaarde hij het tot kunst. Tania Bruguera laat zo’n gesigneerd urinoir aansluiten in het openbare toilet van dit museum. Ze geeft het urinoir zijn oorspronkelijke functie terug. Met Arte Útil moedigt ze het publiek aan om over de gebruikswaarde van kunst – en haar functie in de samenleving – na te denken. 'Het auteurschap van het oorspronkelijke werk is recentelijk in twijfel gebracht. Hoogstwaarschijnlijk is het niet van Duchamp maar van Baroness Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven. '[2018]</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>3225</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>