<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2977"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C8604"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2977-01.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2977-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2977"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2977"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">digitale print op doek</dc:type><dcterms:created>2008</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In dit werk confronteert Heiman een bekende kunsthistorische compositie, 'Maria en kind' van Raphaël, met een hedendaags mediabeeld dat een vergelijkbare opbouw heeft. Is objectieve verslaglegging en waarneming mogelijk? Wat roepen mediabeelden op die verwant zijn aan bekende composities en beeldelementen uit de beeldende kunst? Heiman refereert aan de theorie 'Attacks on Linking' (1959) van de psychiater Wilfred Bion. Bion onderzocht de relatie tussen zintuigelijke registratie en subjectieve interpretatie. Heiman test dit verband door twee uit afzonderlijke contexten afkomstige beelden naast elkaar te tonen. '[tentoonstellingstekst 2013]</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">digital print on canvas</dc:type><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dc:identifier>2977</dc:identifier><dc:title>Attacks on Linking: Scrolls – What’s on Your Mind? (Photographer Unknown / Zahoul Family, Hussan Village, 23 Feb. 2004) Attacks On Linking: Scrolls – What’s on Your Mind? (Raphael / Madonna del Granduca, ca. 1505)</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work Heiman adopts a well-known composition in art history, the Madonna and child by Raphael, with a contemporary media image that uses a comparable structure. Is it possible to report and observe this objectively? What do media images evoke when they are related to well-known compositions and visual elements in the arts? Heiman refers to the theory 'Attacks on Linking' (1959) by the psychiatrist Wilfred Bion. Bion examined the relationship between sensory registration and subjective interpretation. By displaying two images taken from separate contexts side by side Heiman tests these links. '[exhibition text 2013]</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Michal Heiman</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>(2x) 470 x 255 cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>