<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2675"><dc:type xml:lang="en">book, offset on paper</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het project 'No Ghost Just a Shell' (2002) is een schenking van de Stichting Promotors Van Abbemuseum ter gelegenheid van de opening van het nieuwe museum. De publicatie bundelt voor de eerste keer alle kunstwerken die tussen 1999 en 2003 met en rond de virtuele figuur AnnLee zijn ontwikkelt. Het is bovendien het afsluitende object in de totale serie van 26 kunstwerken. Naast een interview van Hans Ulrich Obrist met de initiatiefnemers Pierre Huyghe en Philippe Parreno, hebben negen schrijvers een bijdrage aan de publicatie geleverd. Pierre Huyghe zegt hierover in een inleidend interview: "The authors of the book add on the list of artists who have already taken the character into their hands. They share equally in the project (…) The book No Ghost just A Shell is an anthology of the sign AnnLee. It's a technical book, a book exploring the different facets of the project, ideas that had been observed in the course of the project's constitution." Verder bevat de publicatie het nu al legendarische contract waardoor AnnLee zelf eigenaar wordt van de auteursrechten. Zo zal het in de toekomst onmogelijk zijn om AnnLee nog artistiek of economisch te exploiteren, en is deze publicatie onmiddellijk ook het laatste AnnLee boek. Een exemplaar van deze publicatie is voor onderzoek beschikbaar in onze bibliotheek.</dc:description><dc:identifier>2675</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">The project 'No Ghost Just a Shell' (2002) is a gift from the Stichting Promotors Van Abbemuseum on the occasion of the opening of the new museum. For the first time, the publication bundles all works of art that were developed between 1999 and 2003 with and around the virtual figure AnnLee. It is also the concluding object in the total series of 26 works of art. In addition to an interview by Hans Ulrich Obrist with the initiators Pierre Huyghe and Philippe Parreno, nine writers contributed to the publication. Pierre Huyghe says about this in an introductory interview: "The authors of the book add on the list of artists who have already taken the character into their hands. They share equally in the project (…) The book No Ghost just A Shell is an anthology of the sign AnnLee. It's a technical book, a book exploring the different facets of the project, ideas that had been observed in the course of the project's constitution." Furthermore, the publication contains the already legendary contract whereby AnnLee herself becomes the owner of the copyrights. For example, in the future it will be impossible to exploit AnnLee artistically or economically, and this publication will immediately be the last AnnLee book. A copy of this publication is available for research in our library.</dc:description><dc:title>No Ghost Just a Shell</dc:title><dcterms:created>2003</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>2003</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="nl">boek, offset op papier</dc:type><dcterms:extent>36,8 x 23,2 x 2,1 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Pierre Huyghe &amp; Philippe Parreno</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2675"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2675"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2675-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2675-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C3104"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>