<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2997"><dc:title>Naked Machine (Volkswagen Modern)</dc:title><dc:creator>Surasi Kusolwong</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="nl">VW Kever 1973, futons, video, iPads, collectieve voorwerpen, meubels, planten, tapijt</dc:type><dcterms:created>2000-2011</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">The light blue Volkswagen hanging in this space immediately attracts attention. It is a work of art by the Thai artist Surasi Kusolwong and is called 'Naked Machine, (Volkswagen Modern)'. The wheels, engine, steering wheel and interior – everything has been removed from this car, leaving only the bodywork. It hangs upside down, sturdily attached to the ceiling with steel wire. The two doors have been removed so that you can easily sit down in it. In order to make this more pleasant, some comfortable cushions have been placed inside it. The windows have been covered with coloured foil. You can have a lazy rest in this car or watch a video. In fact, you can do everything there which you cannot do when you are driving a car. 'The Volkswagen Beetle is one of the most successful cars ever to have been produced. Altogether more than 21 million were manufactured. This car was once the symbol of the post-war German economic recovery, the so-called Wirtschaftswunder. Many people wanted a Volkswagen, and previous owners still remember the characteristic space in the boot at the back which served as an extra back seat for many small children. For a long time the Beetle was the prototype of a no-nonsense car, a means of transport that became affordable for many. 'Although a car is often chosen for its image and prestige, it is in the first place simply a means of transport. It is just another consumer object that serves to take people from one place to another. The Beetle was a perfect example of this. As an artist Surasi Kusolwong often removed such consumer articles from their context, giving them new and unexpected functions. In this way, he contrasts usefulness with art and raises questions about the need for the objects surrounding us. The reason for doing this is: “to practise and demonstrate the way of happiness.” He involves the viewer in his work and in this way provides an alternative for the passive consumption of images in a museum. In this work he also replaces one function of the object with another, but ensures that the whole thing can still be used as a work of art. The car becomes a special place to spend time and in this way changes from a method of transport to a place where you can be transported. We become the engine ourselves in a feeling machine with unknown possibilities. '- Exhibition text 2011 -</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">1973 VW Beetle, futons, video, IPads, collective objects, furniture, plants, carpet</dc:type><dc:identifier>2997</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De lichtblauwe Volkswagen die in deze ruimte opgehangen is, trekt meteen de aandacht. Het is een kunstwerk van de Thaise kunstenaar Surasi Kusolwong en het heet Naked Machine (Volkswagen Modern). De wielen, de motor, het stuur en het interieur, alles is van deze auto afgehaald. Alleen de carrosserie is over. En deze hangt op zijn kop, stevig bevestigd aan het plafond met staaldraad. De twee deuren zijn er uitgehaald zodat je er gemakkelijk in kunt plaatsnemen. Om het verblijf in de auto wat aangenamer te maken zijn er comfortabele kussens in gelegd. De ramen zijn met gekleurde folie beplakt. In deze auto kun je liggen luieren of een video bekijken. Eigenlijk kun je er alles doen wat je niet kunt als je in een rijdende auto aan het stuur zit. 'De Volkswagen Kever is een van de meest succesvolle auto's die ooit geproduceerd is. In totaal werden er meer dan 21 miljoen van gemaakt. Deze auto was ooit het symbool van de na-oorlogse Duitse economische wederopbouw, het zogenaamde Wirtschaftswunder. Veel mensen wilden een Volkswagen en voormalige eigenaren herinneren zich nog goed de typische 'kattenbak' achterin, die voor veel kleine kinderen heeft gefunctioneerd als een extra achterbank. De Kever was een tijdlang hèt prototype van een no nonsense auto: een vervoermiddel dat voor velen binnen bereik kwam. 'Hoewel een personenauto vaak gekozen wordt om het imago en het prestige is het in de eerste plaats gewoon een vervoermiddel. Het is simpelweg een gebruiksobject dat dient om mensen van de ene plek naar de andere te vervoeren. De Kever was dat bij uitstek. Surasi Kusolwong haalt als kunstenaar zulke gebruiksvoorwerpen vaak uit hun context en geeft er nieuwe, onverwachte functies aan. Zo plaatst hij nut tegenover kunst en zet hij vraagtekens bij de noodzaak van de ons omringende objecten. De reden dat hij dit doet is: "To practise and demonstrate the way of happiness". Hij betrekt de toeschouwer bij zijn werk en biedt zo een alternatief voor de passieve consumptie van beelden in een museum. Ook in dit werk vervangt hij de ene functie van het object door een andere, maar hij zorgt ervoor dat het geheel als kunstwerk nog steeds te gebruiken blijft. Deze auto wordt tot een bijzondere verblijfplaats en verandert zo van een vervoermiddel in een middel van vervoering. Wij zijn zelf de motor geworden in een gevoelsmachine met ongekende mogelijkheden. '- Tentoonstellingstekst 2011 -</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>2000-2011</dc:date><dcterms:extent>installatie afmeting variabel / installation dimensions variable</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2997"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2997.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2997"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2997.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C8661"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>