<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3137"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3137-02.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3137-02.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C10117"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3137"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3137"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Van Abbe Donation Drawings (b)</dc:title><dcterms:created>1981</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1981</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">Solakov donated this drawing in 2013 and wrote the following notes to accompany the work: "This drawing was done in October 1981 when I had just entered the army for two years after graduating the Art Academy in Sofia. I had two weeks of heavy training and afterwards the commanders started using my muralist skills. So over two years, I did many sgraffitos I was also able to paint in my army studio and to take part in most national exhibitions organized by the Creative Union of Artists. While in the army, I became the youngest member of the Union of Artists (our Art World at that time)."</dc:description><dc:identifier>3137</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>7,3 x 9.9 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">black ink, pen on paper</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">zwarte inkt, pen op papier</dc:type><dc:creator>Nedko Solakov</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Solakov schonk deze tekening in 2013 en schreef de volgende toelichting bij het werk: “Deze tekening heb ik gemaakt in oktober 1981, in de periode dat ik, na afgestudeerd te zijn aan de Kunstacademie in Sofia, twee jaar in het leger heb gezeten. Ik heb twee weken zware trainingen gevolgd, daarna mocht ik me van de bevelhebbers toeleggen op het maken van muurschilderingen. Ik heb dus twee jaar lang veel in sgraffito techniek gewerkt. Daarnaast kon ik schilderen in mijn legerwerkplaats en deelnemen aan de meeste nationale tentoonstellingen van de Creative Union of Artists. Terwijl ik in het leger zat, werd ik tegelijkertijd het jongste lid van de Union of Artists (in die tijdzone Art World van nu).”</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>