<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3163"><dc:title>Let’s Meet at the Orient</dc:title><dc:identifier>3163</dc:identifier><dc:date>1995</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Let’s Meet at the Orient' consists of a large blue balloon and a copper container filled with water. In the container, the name of every country in the world is inscribed in brass. They seem to have fallen off the blue balloon, together with a white silk cloth cut in the shape of the continents. The installation represents planet Earth, the blue planet, stripped of boundaries, conflicts, power relationships, or traces of exploitation, in a time far in the past or perhaps the future. 'Füsun Onur says about her work: ‘The world map is pure white, without borders. As if the world has united against evil. Like Atatürk said: “Peace in the country, peace in the world.” Years have passed and nothing has changed. Rich countries are ever greedier. They want to devour, invade, exploit the situation. So, this work remains a fairy tale.’</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">rubber balloon, silk, beads, rope, wood, copper washtub, brassed letters</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Let’s Meet at the Orient' bestaat uit een grote blauwe ballon en een met water gevulde koperen bak. In de bak bevinden zich, uitgevoerd in messing, de namen van alle landen op de wereld. Ze lijken van de blauwe ballon te zijn gevallen, samen met een witte zijden lap in de vorm van de continenten. De installatie stelt de aarde voor, de blauwe planeet, ontdaan van landgrenzen, conflicten, machtsverhoudingen en sporen van uitbuiting. In een tijd ver in het verleden of ver in de toekomst? 'Füsun Onur zelf zegt over haar werk: “De wereldkaart is zuiver wit, zonder grenzen. Alsof de wereld zich tegen het kwaad verenigd heeft. Zoals Atatürk zei: ‘Vrede in het land, vrede in de wereld.’ Jaren zijn voorbijgegaan en er is niets veranderd. De rijke landen worden steeds hebzuchtiger. Ze willen verzwelgen, binnenvallen, gebruik maken van de situatie. Dus blijft dit werk een sprookje.”</dc:description><dcterms:created>1995</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">rubberen ballon, zijde, kralen, touw, hout, koperen wastobbe, messing letters</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Füsun Onur</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3163"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C10179"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3163-01.Jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3163"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3163-01.Jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>