<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3008"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3008-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C8851"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3008"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3008-01.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3008"><dc:title>Guppy 13 vs Ocean Wave; a Bas Jan Ader Experience</dc:title><dc:date>2010</dc:date><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">'The Guppy 13 is one of the smallest sailing boats in the world, and only 300 were made between 1974 and 1975. The Dutch artist Bas Jan Ader wanted to cross the Atlantic on one of these boats, called the Ocean Wave. He left from Cape Cod on 9 July 1975, but after three weeks radio contact with him broke down. Nine months later his boat was found unmanned by a Spanish fishing boat, about 240 kilometres from the Irish coast. Ader’s body was never found. The boat was taken to La Coruña in Spain for further investigation. A few weeks later the boat was stolen and it has never been found. 'Never arriving in a place inspired the Kurdish-Turkish artist Ahmet Ögüt, who works in Amsterdam, to create the work ‘Guppy 13 vs Ocean Wave; a Bas Jan Ader Experience’. In 2010 Ögüt invited the public to sit on a Guppy 13 sailing boat for a few minutes on the IJ, to experience what Bas Jan Ader must have felt like at sea. The only rule was that the members of the public had to get on the boat by themselves. The video is a fictitious documentary in which the Guppy 13 sails backwards with a different person on the boat every time. The music ‘A life on the ocean wave’ (published 1838) was composed by Henry Russel, and is played backwards. It was part of Bas Jan Ader’s last project. The video is actually a trip backwards in time. 'The disappearance of Ögüt’s boat was very curious. In fact the Guppy 13 was stolen in Amsterdam after six weeks, but it was found again four months later. '- Exhibition text 2013 -</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (PAL, kleur, geluid); zeilboot, politierapport, kleurenfoto</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (PAL, colour, sound) duration 6:47 min., sailing boat, police report, colour photograph</dc:type><dc:creator>Ahmet Öğüt</dc:creator><dcterms:created>2010</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>3008</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'De Guppy 13 is een van de kleinste zeilboten ter wereld, waarvan er tussen 1974 en 1975 maar 300 zijn gemaakt. De Nederlandse kunstenaar Bas Jan Ader wilde met dit bootje, genaamd Ocean Wave, de Atlantische Oceaan oversteken. Op 9 juli 1975 vertrok hij vanaf Cape Cod, maar na drie weken werd het radiocontact met hem verbroken. Negen maanden later werd zijn boot onbemand gevonden door een Spaanse vissersboot op ongeveer 240 kilometer van de kust van Ierland. Aders lichaam is nooit gevonden. Het bootje werd meegenomen naar La Coruña in Spanje voor nader onderzoek. Een paar weken later werd de boot gestolen en is nooit meer teruggevonden. 'Het nooit arriveren op een plek inspireerde de in Amsterdam werkzame Koerdisch-Turkse kunstenaar Ahmet Ögüt voor zijn werk ‘Guppy 13 vs Ocean Wave; a Bas Jan Ader Experience’. In 2010 nodigde Ögüt het publiek uit om op het IJ voor een paar minuten alleen op een Guppy 13 zeilboot te zitten om te ervaren hoe Bas Jan Ader zich moet hebben gevoeld op zee. De enige regel was dat het publiek zelf op het bootje moest zien te komen. De video is een fictieve documentaire waarbij Guppy 13 achteruit vaart met steeds een andere persoon op de boot. De muziek ‘A life on the ocean wave’ (gepubliceerd in 1938) is een compositie van Henry Russel, achterstevoren afgespeeld en was onderdeel van het laatste project van Bas Jan Ader. De video is eigenlijk een reis van achter naar voren in de tijd. 'Opmerkelijk is de verdwijning van het bootje van Ögüt. Na anderhalve maand werd zijn Guppy 13 namelijk in Amsterdam gestolen en na vier maanden weer teruggevonden. '- Tentoonstellingstekst 2013 -</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>