<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2353"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work by Fortuyn/O’Brien six rectangular shapes the size of a door are placed side by side, leaning against a wall. They consist of two layers of perspex with a wooden frame and pieces of thin silk between the perspex. The frame and part of the glass are painted one colour. A curved piece in the middle remains transparent and there is a matt elliptical shape visible in this in some of the “doors”. Two of the “doors” are painted bright pink, two pale yellow and two dark brown. 'The artists, Irene Drooglever Fortuyn and Robert O’Brien, have been working together under the name Fortuyn/O’Brien since 1983 and Fortuyn has continued to use this name as an artist since O’Brien’s death in 1988. The sculptures of Fortuyn/O’Brien inspire associations with interiors, homes and architecture. They refer to mirrors, doors, balustrades and bowers, but do not usually function as such. They are like accessories and say: ”We want to make objects which compete with the chairs and tables that surround everyone.” Because of the form of their work and the use of reflecting and transparent materials, there is a strong interaction with the surrounding area: the work influences the experiences of the space, and the space influences that of the work. The sculptures mark points in a space, but at the same time contribute to the denial of the limitations and material quality of that space and of themselves. 'In 'Venetian Blinds' the “doors” stand against the wall. They are not real passageways. The title reveals that they are actually not doors but shutters, but their position is not logical for shutters. They are not hanging on the wall and they are not next to a window; rather they are windows, but the size of a door. However, they do not function as windows either: the transparent material is largely cancelled out by being painted, by placing fabric between it or by making it matt. Therefore they work more as blinds. The sculpture evokes associations with recognizable objects, but is not clear. The theme of a door or gateway regularly occurs in Fortuyn/O’Brien’s work. It is the point where two spaces, two worlds are interconnected and where new views, literally and metaphorically, open up. It is a place for mirroring and reflection, metaphorically, but also literally in 'Venetian Blinds'.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1987</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">painted wood, plexiglass, silk</dc:type><dc:identifier>2353</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In dit werk van Fortuyn/O'Brien staan zes rechthoekige vormen ter grootte van een deur naast elkaar tegen de wand geleund. Ze bestaan uit twee lagen plexiglas, gevat in een houten frame. Tussen het plexiglas zitten stukken dunne zijde geklemd. Het frame en een deel van het glas zijn geschilderd in één kleur. Een boogvormig stuk in het midden blijft transparant. Hierin is bij enkele 'deuren' een matte ellipsvorm zichtbaar. Twee 'deuren' zijn felroze geschilderd, twee lichtgeel en twee donkerbruin. 'Sinds 1983 werken de kunstenaars Irene Drooglever Fortuyn en Robert O'Brien samen onder de naam Fortuyn/O'Brien. Sinds de dood van O'Brien in 1988 blijft Fortuyn deze kunstenaarsnaam gebruiken. De sculpturen van Fortuyn/O'Brien roepen associaties op met interieur, woonhuis en architectuur. Ze refereren aan spiegels, deuren, balustrades of priëlen, maar functioneren meestal niet als zodanig. Het zijn meer rekwisieten. Ze zeggen: "Wij willen objecten maken die concurreren met de stoelen en de tafels waarmee iedereen zich omgeeft". Door de vorm van hun werk en door het gebruik van spiegelende en transparante materialen is er een sterke interactie met de omgeving: het werk beïnvloedt de ervaring van de ruimte en de ruimte die van het werk. De sculpturen zijn markeringen in een ruimte, maar dragen tegelijkertijd bij aan de ontkenning van de begrenzing en de materialitiet van die ruimte en van zichzelf. 'In 'Venetian Blinds' staan de 'deuren' tegen de muur. Het zijn geen werkelijke doorgangen. De titel verraadt dat het ook geen deuren zijn maar luiken. Maar voor luiken is hun plaatsing niet logisch. Ze hangen niet aan de wand en flankeren geen raam. Het zijn eerder ramen, met de maat van een deur. Maar als raam functioneren ze ook niet: het transparante materiaal wordt grotendeels teniet gedaan door overschildering, door er stof tussen te plaatsen of het mat te maken. Dus werken ze toch meer als blindering. De sculptuur roept associaties op met herkenbare objecten, maar is niet eenduidig. Het motief van een deur of poort komt regelmatig terug in het werk van Fortuyn/O'Brien. Het is het punt waar twee ruimtes, twee werelden verbinding krijgen en waar nieuwe gezichtsvelden letterlijk en figuurlijk ontsloten worden. Het is een plek voor bespiegeling en reflectie; figuurlijk, maar in 'Venetian Blinds' ook letterlijk.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Venetian Blinds</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">beschilderd hout, perspex, zijde</dc:type><dcterms:extent>(6x) 225 x 95 x 4 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Fortuyn/O'Brien</dc:creator><dc:date>1987</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2353"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2353"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2353.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2503"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2353.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>