<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1179"><dc:creator>Isa Genzken</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Feuervogel' by Isa Genzken is an elongated wooden sculpture, based on the mathematical figure, the hyperbole. The ends are widest and the sculpture stands on them on the floor. It becomes narrower towards the middle and separates from the ground. One rounded end is circular, the other elliptical. A quarter of the sculpture has been removed across the length. This part is then reduced slightly and has been shifted. At the rounded end, it sticks out slightly; at the elliptical end, it is indented. The outside of the sculpture is evenly painted with matt red paint. The part that is inlaid reveals an even transition of colour from yellow to orange. The narrow cutting edges are light green and the rounded ends are unpainted. 'Genzken made a number of wooden sculptures based on the ellipse and the hyperbole between 1976 and 1983, using drawings and computer calculations as a starting point. The ellipsoids are presented lying down, in one place on the floor. The hyperboles can be exhibited either lying down or standing up. Because of their streamlined and elongated shape, these sculptures look light and mobile. They are always colourfully painted. On the one hand, they evoke associations with primitive shapes such as spears or kayaks, while on the other hand, they almost look like contemporary design because of their polished perfection. 'In her sculptures Genzken unites all sorts of contrasts, both in terms of content and as regards form. In 'Feuervogel' there is a transition from the shape of a circle to an ellipse carried out with great precision. This fact, in combination with the fact that the wood is polished smooth and evenly painted, contributes to the technical and mathematical character of the work. However, on the rounded ends the original wooden material is still visible. Because of this material, the rounded shape and the length of the sculpture, there are also associations with the natural form of a tree trunk. This is further reinforced because the inlaid part of the sculpture looks like an exposed older annular ring. In this way Genzken combines nature and technology. The predominantly warm colours of this sculpture, in combination with the title 'Feuervogel', give this work an expressive power which seems to contradict the tight mathematical character of the work.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>(h x b x d) :ø 20 x 521,5 x ø 26 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">beschilderd hout</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1981</dc:date><dcterms:created>1981</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>1179</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Feuervogel' van Isa Genzken is een langgerekte houten sculptuur, gebaseerd op een wiskundige figuur: de hyperbool. De uiteinden zijn het breedste. Daarmee rust de sculptuur op de vloer. Naar het midden toe wordt zij smaller en komt ze los van de grond. De ene kopse kant is cirkelvormig, de andere elliptisch. Over de lengte is een vierde deel van de vorm verwijderd. Dit deel is daarna iets verkleind en enigszins verschoven teruggeplaatst. Aan de ronde kant steekt het iets uit, aan de elliptische kant springt het in. De buitenkant van het beeld is egaal beschilderd met matte rode verf. Het ingelegde deel laat een gelijkmatige kleurovergang zien van geel naar oranje. De smalle snijvlakken zijn lichtgroen. De kopse kanten zijn onbeschilderd. 'Tussen 1976 en 1983 maakt Genzken een aantal houten sculpturen, gebaseerd op de ellips en de hyperbool. Ze gaat daarbij uit van tekeningen en computerberekeningen. De ellipsoïden worden liggend gepresenteerd. Ze rusten op één plaats op de vloer. De hyperbolen kunnen liggend of staand tentoongesteld worden. Door hun gestroomlijnde vorm en hun langgerektheid lijken deze sculpturen licht en beweeglijk. Ze zijn altijd kleurrijk beschilderd. Enerzijds roepen ze de associatie op met oervormen als speren of kajaks, anderzijds ogen ze door hun perfectie en gepolijstheid bijna als hedendaags design. 'Genzken verenigt in haar beelden allerlei contrasten, zowel inhoudelijk als formeel. In 'Feuervogel' treedt een vormverandering op van cirkel naar ellips, die met grote precisie is uitgevoerd. Dit gegeven, evenals het feit dat het hout glad gepolijst en strak geschilderd is, draagt bij aan het technisch-mathematische karakter van het beeld. Aan de kopse kanten is echter het oorspronkelijke materiaal hout zichtbaar. Door dit materiaal, de ronde vorm en de lengte van de sculptuur ontstaat de associatie met een natuurvorm, een boomstam. Deze wordt nog versterkt doordat het ingelegde deel van de sculptuur een blootgelegde oudere jaarring lijkt te zijn. Zo verenigt Genzken natuur en techniek. De overwegend warme kleuren van deze sculptuur, in combinatie met de titel 'Feuervogel', geven dit werk een expressieve lading die in tegenspraak lijkt met de mathematische strakheid van de vorm.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">painted wood</dc:type><dc:title>Feuervogel</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1179"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1179"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1179.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1179.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1431"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>