<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3466"><dc:date>2015-2018</dc:date><dc:identifier>3466</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this video Amina Osse, Chair of Committee of Foreign Affairs in Rojava, and visual artist Jonas Staal introduce the People’s Parliament of Rojava. Osse speaks of the political background of the Rojava Revolution and the future use of the new parliament. The video, shot by Ruben Hamelink, further provides a short impression of the city of Dêrik in the canton of Cezîrê, which is known in Rojava as one of the most successful examples of democratic self-governance while hosting one of the most ethnically and religiously diverse communities in the region.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:extent>duur / duration 00:03:21</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Jonas Staal</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In deze video introduceren Amina Osse, voorzitter van het Comité van Buitenlandse Zaken in Rojava, en beeldend kunstenaar Jonas Staal het Volksparlement van Rojava. Osse schetst de politieke achtergrond van de Revolutie van Rojava en het beoogde toekomstige gebruik van het nieuwe parlement. De film, geschoten door Ruben Hamelink, biedt tevens een korte impressie van de stad Dêrik in het kanton van Cezîrê, dat in Rojava bekend staat als een van de succesvolste voorbeelden van democratisch zelfbestuur met een van de meest diverse etnische en religieuze gemeenschappen in de regio.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (kleur, geluid)</dc:type><dc:title>New World Summit - Rojava video introduction</dc:title><dcterms:created>2015-2018</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3466"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C12645"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3466"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>