<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/775"><dcterms:extent>41,2 x 31,2 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">'When Attitude Offend Form' is one of the 158 prints which the Van Abbemuseum owns of Barry Flanagan’s works. These prints (etchings and linoleum cuts) clearly reveal the multidimensional aspect of Flanagan’s work. The subjects are very diverse. In a number of prints Flanagan confronts the viewer with something or someone from his immediate environment, for example portraits of artists who are friends, household objects or landscapes he has seen. In other prints he harks back to old masters such as Rembrandt, refers to drawing itself or makes studies of animals. A number of prints contain references to people or events in literature or the history of art. The cash box in “When Attitude Offend Form” is an ironic comment on the much talked about exhibition “When Attitude Become Form” organized by Harald Szeeman in 1968-69. 'Flanagan studied sculpture at St Martin’s School of Art in London from 1964 to 1966. With a number of fellow students, including Long, Fulton and Gilbert &amp; George, he reacted against the traditional views about sculpture which were taught there, and a new generation of artists looked for new possibilities in sculpture. Flanagan did this in a playful and investigative way using unconventional materials such as jute and sand. For him the creative process was of central importance: he allowed himself to be led by the specific character of a material or technique. This applies to his graphic work as well as his sculptures. In the graphic work the emphasis is on the line; the line as a defining element or boundary. 'Usually Flanagan only used form very sparingly. A landscape, animal or situation was depicted with just a few precise lines. The attention and sensitivity with which this was done gave the work a poetic strength. In fact, Flanagan’s source was life itself, rich and inexhaustible and he freely used anything that was available. His work was at the same time serious and light-hearted. Flanagan’s drawings and graphic work often have the character of sketches and look like notes more than carefully considered works of art. Even when he used heavy and “serious” materials such as bronze or stone, his sculptures have the same light-hearted vitality. The theme of the hare, a symbol for the lively and unexpected, regularly recurs in Flanagan’s work.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">etching on paper</dc:type><dc:identifier>775</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'When attitude offend form' is één van de 158 prenten die het Van Abbemuseum bezit van Barry Flanagan. Deze prenten (etsen en linoleumsnedes) geven een goed beeld van Flanagans veelzijdigheid. De onderwerpen lopen sterk uiteen. In een aantal prenten confronteert Flanagan de kijker met iets of iemand uit zijn directe leefomgeving, bijvoorbeeld portretten van bevriende kunstenaars, huiselijke objecten of landschappen die hij gezien heeft. In andere prenten grijpt hij terug op oude meesters zoals Rembrandt ,verwijst hij naar het tekenen zelf, of maakt hij studies van dieren. Een aantal prenten bevat verwijzingen naar personen of gebeurtenissen uit de literatuur of kunstgeschiedenis. Het geldkoffertje in 'When attitude offend form' is een ironisch commentaar op de spraakmakende tentoonstelling 'When Attitudes Become Form', georganiseerd door Harald Szeeman in 1968-69 . 'Van 1964 tot 1966 studeert Flanagan sculptuur aan St. Martin's School of Art in Londen. Met een aantal medestudenten, waaronder Long, Fulton en Gilbert &amp; George, reageert hij op de traditionele opvattingen over beeldhouwkunst die daar dan gedoceerd worden. De nieuwe generatie kunstenaars zoekt nieuwe mogelijkheden voor sculptuur. Flanagan doet dit op een speelse, onderzoekende manier. Hij gebruikt onconventionele materialen, zoals jute en zand. Het maakproces staat voor hem centraal: hij laat zich leiden door het specifieke van een materiaal of techniek. Dit geldt behalve voor zijn sculpturen ook voor zijn grafiek. Hierin ligt het accent op de lijn; de lijn als begrenzend of markerend element. 'Flanagan maakt meestal een spaarzaam gebruik van vormen. Een landschap, dier of situatie kan met enkele rake lijnen worden neergezet. De aandacht en de gevoeligheid waarmee dit gebeurt, geven het werk een poëtische kracht. Flanagans bron is in feite het leven zelf, rijk en onuitputtelijk. In alle vrijheid maakt hij gebruik van wat er voorhanden is. Zijn werk is tegelijkertijd serieus en lichtvoetig. Flanagans tekeningen en grafiek hebben vaak een schetsmatig karakter. Het lijken eerder notities dan doordachte kunstwerken. Zijn sculpturen hebben, ook wanneer hij zware en 'serieuze' materialen als brons of steen gebruikt, eenzelfde lichtvoetige levendigheid. Het motief van de haas, symbool voor het levendige en het onverwachte, keert regelmatig terug in Flanagans werk.</dc:description><dc:date>1971</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">ets op papier</dc:type><dc:creator>Barry Flanagan</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:created>1971</dcterms:created><dc:title>When Attitude Offend Form</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/775"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/775"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1096"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0775.JPG"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0775.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>