<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3531"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3531.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C12438"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3531.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3531"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3531"><dc:description xml:lang="en">Jonas Staal produced the photo series Anatomy of a Revolution: Rojava (2015) during his first travel to Rojava in 2014. It documents the emergence of radical new institutions since the start of the Rojava Revolution. 'Members from neighborhood councils and cooperatives present themselves as candidates for the position of co-chair of the People’s Council of the city of Qamislo. The slogan on stage "Her Tist Jibo Jiyanek Azad û Avakirina Civakek Demokratîk" translates as “Everything for a Free Life and the Foundation of a Democratic Society.” On the right, a portrait of Kurdish revolutionary and thinker Abdullah Öcalan.</dc:description><dc:creator>Jonas Staal</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="nl">diasec print</dc:type><dc:title>Anatomy of a Revolution: Rojava</dc:title><dc:identifier>3531</dc:identifier><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>2015</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De fotoserie Anatomie van een Revolutie: Rojava (2015) realiseerde kunstenaar Jonas Staal tijdens zijn eerste reis naar Rojava in 2014. De serie documenteert het ontstaan van de radicale nieuwe instituties sinds de Revolutie van Rojava. 'Leden van wijkraden en coöperatieven presenteren zichzelf als kandidaten voor de positie van co-voorzitter van de Volksraad van de stad Qamislo. De slogan op het podium, 'Her Tist Jibo Jiyanek Azad û Avakirina Civakek Demokratîk', kan worden vertaald als ‘Alles voor een vrij leven en het fundament van een democratische samenleving’. Rechts is een portret zichtbaar van de Koerdische revolutionair en denker Abdullah Öcalan.</dc:description><dcterms:created>2015</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>