<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/513"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/513"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0512-0513.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C852"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0512-0513.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/513"><dc:type xml:lang="en">wood</dc:type><dc:title>Saint Sébastien</dc:title><dcterms:created>1929</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">hout</dc:type><dc:identifier>513</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">This wooden statue by Zadkine represents the body of a man. He is stretched out with a slight rotating movement from the ankles up to the raised left arm which has been cut off. The head is bent and hangs down onto the right shoulder. Zadkine's statue follows the natural form of the tree trunk. Only very little material was removed to create 'Saint Sébastien'. Zadkine used the branches at the top of the tree trunk to distinguish the head and the arm. The statue does not have any feet, and in addition to the left arm, Saint Sébastien's head has also been cut flat. The ribs and elbow of the right arm are represented by sharp grooves. The other lines of the statue are more flowing. The traces of the gouging process are clearly visible on the skin of the statue. 'When the Russian Ossip Zadkine arrived in Paris in 1909, Cubism was in full swing there. The painters Braque and Picasso analysed elements from reality in rather geometric faceted forms which they arranged on the canvas in a new way. This iconography was translated into three-dimensional sculptures by Lipchitz, amongst others. Zadkine was also influenced by Cubism. However, he was not interested so much in its formal iconography as in the free way in which visual motifs were used. Zadkine’s work was almost always based on the human figure. He did not consider that it was necessary to represent this in a way that was anatomically correct. For him the expressive force of the image was much more important. In this respect, Zadkine said: “if something has to be copied in art, it is the spirit, never the letter of the original.” ''Saint Sébastien' is more traditional than a number of Zadkine’s older statues in terms of form. The figure is slightly elongated and stylized and Zadkine felt free to cut off the statue at the top and bottom, but as regards their form and position, the parts of the body were represented in a way that is anatomically correct. The bent head with the closed eyes and the grooves of the ribs give the statue the tragedy and vulnerability which are suitable for the martyr Saint Sebastian. This martyr is usually represented standing against a tree trunk with arrows piercing his body, but in Zadkine’s statue the tree and the figure are one.</dc:description><dc:date>1929</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit houten beeld van Zadkine laat een mannenlichaam zien. Het strekt zich uit met een licht draaiende beweging, vanaf de enkels tot de geheven linkerarm, die afgesneden is. Het hoofd is gebogen en hangt op de rechterschouder. Zadkines beeld volgt de natuurlijke vorm van de boomstam. Er is slechts weinig materiaal weggehaald om 'Saint Sébastien' vorm te geven. De vertakking bovenaan de boomstam gebruikt Zadkine om hoofd en arm van elkaar te onderscheiden. Het beeld heeft geen voeten, en behalve de linkerarm is ook het hoofd van Sint Sebastiaan vlak afgesneden. De ribben en de elleboogholte van de rechterarm zijn met scherpe kerven weergegeven. De overige lijnen van het beeld zijn vloeiender. Op de huid van het beeld zijn de sporen van het gutsen duidelijk zichtbaar. 'Wanneer de Rus Ossip Zadkine in 1909 in Parijs aankomt, is daar het kubisme volop in ontwikkeling. De schilders Braque en Picasso ontleden gegevens uit de werkelijkheid in tamelijk geometrische, facetachtige vormen, die ze op een nieuwe manier rangschikken op het beeldvlak. Deze vormentaal wordt door onder meer Lipchitz vertaald naar driedimensionale beelden. Ook Zadkine ondergaat invloed van het kubisme. Hij is echter niet zozeer geïnteresseerd in de formele beeldtaal ervan, als wel in de vrije manier waarop er wordt omgegaan met een visueel motief. Zadkine gaat vrijwel altijd uit van de menselijke gestalte. Hij vindt het niet noodzakelijk deze anatomisch correct weer te geven. Van veel groter belang is voor hem de expressieve kracht van het beeld. Zadkine zegt daarover: "Indien er in kunst iets gekopieerd moet worden, dan is het de geest en nooit de letter". ''Saint Sébastien' is wat vorm betreft traditioneler dan een aantal oudere beelden van Zadkine. De figuur is enigszins uitgerekt en gestileerd en Zadkine neemt de vrijheid het beeld als het ware aan de onder- en bovenkant af te snijden, maar de lichaamsdelen zijn wat hun vorm en plaatsing betreft anatomisch juist weergegeven. Het gebogen hoofd met de gesloten ogen en de ingekerfde ribben geven het beeld de tragiek en de kwetsbaarheid die passen bij de martelaar Sint Sebastiaan. Gewoonlijk wordt hij afgebeeld, staande tegen een boomstam en doorboord met pijlen. In Zadkines beeld zijn boom en figuur echter één.</dc:description><dc:creator>Ossip Zadkine</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>hoogte 267,5 cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>