<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3598"><dc:type xml:lang="en">wood, metal, rope (parasol frame, pulley system, foot), embroidered linen, audio</dc:type><dc:identifier>3598</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">Mounira Al Solh (1978 Beirut) made this tent in response to an Arab canopy of the Shah of Persia (1834-1848) that is richly decorated. With this space - originally reserved for men - power and wealth were conveyed. 'When you enter the red tent ‘Lackadaisical Sunset to Sunset’ (2019) by Mounira, you will see mountain animals, plant motifs and stylized female organs embroidered on the canvas. Stories can be read all around - in a series of medallions at eye level. For example, Rawiya, a ten-year-old girl who, as a woman, was not allowed to camp with the men in her family. Their previous stories about wild boars, foxes and rock badgers had sparked her curiosity to such an extent that she secretly hitched a ride in the back of her father and brothers' bus. With this action she forced her participation in this men's outing. 'The artist wants to share with us stories about women who survive a system of inequality with humor, solidarity and determination. "A tent also became, for me, like a library," she explains, "like a little reading room, where you can read those stories and save them from being forgotten." 'The names of the hours are embroidered in the tent roof in Arabic calligraphy. Through a speaker you can hear the voice of the Lebanese singer Rima Khcheich, she reads the hours of the day. This refers to the biological clock and the ticking of time.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">hout, metaal, touw (parasol frame, katrolsysteem, voet), geborduurd linnen, audio</dc:type><dcterms:created>2019</dcterms:created><dc:title>Mina El Shourouk Ila Al Fahma</dc:title><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Mounira Al Solh</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Mounira Al Solh (1978 Beiroet) maakte deze tent als reactie op een Arabisch prieel van de Shah van Perzië (1834-1848) dat rijkelijk versierd is. Met deze - oorspronkelijk voor mannen gereserveerde - ruimte werd macht en rijkdom uitgedragen. 'Wanneer je de rode tent ‘Lackadaisical Sunset to Sunset’ (2019) van Mounira binnentreedt, zie je op het doek bergdieren, plantmotieven en gestileerde vrouwelijke organen geborduurd. Rondom - in een serie medaillons op ooghoogte - zijn verhalen te lezen. Bijvoorbeeld dat van Rawiya, een meisje van tien dat als vrouw niet met de mannen in haar gezin mee mocht komen kamperen. Door hun eerdere verhalen over wilde zwijnen, vossen en klipdassen was haar nieuwsgierigheid zodanig aangewakkerd, dat ze toch stiekem in de laadbak van de bus van haar vader en broers meeliftte. Met deze actie dwong ze haar deelname aan dit mannenuitje af. 'De kunstenares wil verhalen met ons delen over vrouwen die met humor, solidariteit en vastberadenheid zich staande houden in een systeem van ongelijkheid. ‘Een tent werd voor mij ook een soort bibliotheek”, legt ze uit, “een kleine leesruimte waar je zulke verhalen kunt lezen en kunt voorkomen dat ze worden vergeten.” In Arabische kalligrafie zijn de namen van de uren in het tentdak geborduurd. Via een speaker hoor je de stem van de Libanese zangeres Rima Khcheich, zij leest de uren van de dag voor. Dit verwijst naar de biologische klok en het wegtikken van de tijd.</dc:description><dc:date>2019</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3598"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3598"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C13119"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>