<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/119"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1948</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">Eindhoven was put on the map by Philips. A number of bombing raids during the Second World War by both the British and the Germans had resulted in the large-scale devastation of the centre of Eindhoven and the site of the Philips factory at Strijp. This painting 'Philips Factories' by Charles Eyck is almost identical to the coloured graph in his set of prints of the city and the reconstruction of Philips which Eyck was commissioned to do by ‘N.V. Philips Gloeilampenfabrieken’ in Eindhoven. The accompanying caption states: “The factories have risen up again from the chaos with the help of thousands of industrious hands, so that their many different products can now find their way to every country in the world in even greater numbers than before the war.” '[exhibition text 2013]</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Eindhoven werd wereldwijd op de kaart gezet door Philips. Een aantal bombardementen tijdens de Tweede Wereldoorlog door zowel de Britten als de Duitsers zorgde voor een grote verwoesting van het Eindhovense centrum en het Philips fabrieksterrein op Strijp. Het schilderij 'Philipsfabrieke' van Charles Eyck is bijna identiek aan de kleurengrafiek uit zijn prentenset over de stad en de wederopbouw van Philips, die Eyck maakte in opdracht van ‘N.V. Philips’ Gloeilampenfabrieken te Eindhoven’. Het bijschrift daarin vermeldt: ‘Duizenden nijvere handen hebben uit de chaos die was de fabrieken weer doen herrijzen, zodat haar vele verscheidene producten in veel groter mate nog als voor de oorlog thans weer hun weg vinden naar alle landen ter wereld.' '[tentoonstellingstekst 2013]</dc:description><dc:title>Philipsfabrieken</dc:title><dc:identifier>119</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>83,2 x 92 x 5,9 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Charles Eyck</dc:creator><dc:date>1948</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/119"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0119.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C460"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0119.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/119"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>