<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/887"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>887</dc:identifier><dc:title>Un albero di sei metri</dc:title><dc:creator>Giuseppe Penone</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Un Albero di sei metri' means “a tree of six metres”. The Italian artist Guiseppe Penone used a long wooden beam for this work, showing the annual rings of the original tree at the ends. From the bottom he followed a particular annular ring to the top, by removing the wood from later annular rings. Side branches which appeared were left in place. Through this process, the work that was created is still a bar on one side, but on the other side the natural form of a tree is exposed. The work is presented diagonally against the wall, preferably in combination with other trees by Penone. 'Nature plays an important role in Penone’s work, in which he reveals processes such as growth and change. Sometimes he intervenes in the natural growth process of a tree, for example, by wrapping the trunk up with wire or by attaching a cast of his hand to it. In the course of time, the trunk and the addition grow together. In 'Un Albero di sei metri' Penone draws attention to the growth process by reversing it: by removing the annular rings he goes back in time in some way and an earlier growth stage of the tree appears in the beam. In this work, nature and culture are inextricably linked in the form of the tree and the beam. Penone comes from Garessio, a place in Italy where the farming population has strong links with nature. The farmer depends on nature, but also influences it with his activities and a respectful relationship between man and nature is in the interests of both. This interrelationship is expressed in Penone’s work. His “alberi” are good examples both of natural energy and of human labour. For Penone the process of peeling away is the real work of art. Western society has become increasingly materialistic in its aim for progress and there is little attention left for nature. 'In the late 1960s many artists felt the need to reverse this process. New anti-materialist art forms such as land art and performance art were introduced. In Italy, Arte Povera made an appearance. Its representatives, including Penone, respected tradition and attention for nature.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Un albero di sei metri' betekent 'een boom van zes meter'. De Italiaanse kunstenaar Giuseppe Penone heeft voor dit werk een lange houten balk gebruikt waarbij de jaarringen van de oorspronkelijke boom aan de korte kanten zichtbaar zijn. Hij heeft vanaf de onderkant een bepaalde jaarring gevolgd naar de top door het hout van latere jaarringen te verwijderen. Zijtakjes die te voorschijn kwamen heeft hij laten zitten. Via dit proces is er een werk ontstaan dat aan één kant nog steeds een balk is, maar aan de andere kant de natuurlijke vorm van een boom blootlegt. Het werk wordt schuin tegen de wand gepresenteerd, bij voorkeur in combinatie met andere bomen van Penone. 'In Penones werk speelt de natuur een belangrijke rol. Hij maakt processen als groei en verandering zichtbaar. Soms grijpt hij in het natuurlijke groeiproces van een boom in door bijvoorbeeld de stam te omwikkelen met ijzerdraad of er een afgietsel van zijn hand aan te bevestigen. In de loop der tijd vergroeien stam en toevoeging met elkaar. In 'Un albero di sei metri' vraagt Penone aandacht voor het groeiproces door dit om te keren: door jaarringen te verwijderen gaat hij als het ware terug in de tijd. Uit de balk komt een eerder groeistadium van de boom te voorschijn. In dit werk zijn natuur en cultuur, in de vorm van boom en balk, onlosmakelijk met elkaar verbonden. 'Penone komt uit Garessio, een plaats in Italië waar de boerenbevolking een sterke band heeft met de natuur. De boer is van de natuur afhankelijk, maar beïnvloedt deze door zijn ingrepen. Een respectvolle omgang van de mens met de natuur is in beider belang. Deze verwevenheid komt tot uitdrukking in Penones werk. Zijn 'alberi' zijn toonbeelden van zowel natuurlijke energie als menselijke arbeid. Voor Penone is het proces van het afpellen het eigenlijke kunstwerk. De westerse samenleving is in haar vooruitgangsstreven steeds materialistischer geworden. Er is weinig aandacht meer voor de natuur. Eind jaren '60 ontstaat er onder kunstenaars de behoefte dit proces te keren. Nieuwe anti-materialistische kunstvormen als land art en performance doen hun intrede. In Italië ontstaat de arte povera. De vertegenwoordigers hiervan, waaronder Penone, hebben respect voor traditie en aandacht voor de natuur.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1969</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">wood</dc:type><dc:date>1969</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="nl">dennenhout</dc:type><dcterms:extent>561,5 x 19,5 x 11,6 cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/887"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/887"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1193"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0887.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0887.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>