<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3400"><dc:identifier>3400</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">Woensel-West was constructed for Philips employees in the 1920s in Eindhoven. In order to make this nowadays outdated neighbourhood more attractive, a process of demolition and reconstruction was set in motion in 2010. TAAK and the Van Abbemuseum asked Julieta García Vazquez to respond to this eventful period. Together with the residents, she developed plans to preserve the socio-cultural history of the neighbourhood. 'The title 'I is somebody else' refers to the letter by the poet Arthur Rimbaud: ‘Je est un autre’ which is about the displacement of identity. The artist became a co-resident; the residents became fellow artists. Together they map the collective memory of the neighbourhood, which is based on individual stories. The video and wall text are accounts of this community project. Take a leaflet as a souvenir.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Woensel-West werd in de jaren twintig van de vorige eeuw aangelegd voor arbeiders van Philips. Om deze nu verouderde wijk in Eindhoven aantrekkelijker te maken, ging in 2010 een proces van woningsloop en herbouw van start. TAAK en het Van Abbemuseum vroegen Julieta García Vazquez om op deze onrustige periode te reageren. Samen met de wijkbewoners ontwikkelde zij plannen om de sociaal-culturele geschiedenis van de buurt te bewaren. 'De titel 'I is somebody else' verwijst naar de brief van dichter Arthur Rimbaud: ‘Je est un autre’ waarin het draait om identiteitsverplaatsing. De kunstenaar werd medebewoner; de bewoners werden medekunstenaars. Samen brengen ze het collectieve geheugen van de wijk in kaart, dat gestoeld is op individuele verhalen. De video en wandtekst vormen de verslaglegging van dit gemeenschapsproject. Neem als aandenken een vouwblad mee.</dc:description><dc:date>2012-2016</dc:date><dcterms:created>2012-2016</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (colour, sound) duration 14:58 min., print on paper, vinyl wall print</dc:type><dc:title>I is somebody else</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (kleur, geluid), print op papier, vinyl muurtekst</dc:type><dc:creator>Julieta García Vazquez</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3400"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3400-A3.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C11988"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3400"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3400-A3.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>