<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/359"><dc:description xml:lang="en">The title of this painting tells us that this is a hommage to the Polish-English writer Joseph Conrad. His photograph is included in this still life, which also includes references to maritime shipping, such as an image of a large sailing ship, a map with signal flags and a large nautical telescope. Before Conrad started writing novels, he was a sailor. In 1890, he captained a Belgian ship that sailed deep into the Congo. Later, he sailed as captain on board British merchant ships. Conrad incorporated his experiences at sea in his novels, and the tribulations that sailors undergo and the self-control required to endure them feature prominently in them. 'Dirk Nijland was a great admirer of Conrad. He was also fascinated by the ocean, ports and ships, and produced a lot of work depicting water. Behind the box office in the entrance hall of the Van Abbemuseum, you can see a seascape mural by Nijland. 'In his still lifes, Nijland works very disciplined way, paying close attention to the rendering of materials, and his compositions are carefully structured. Here the objects are strictly arranged, lying parallel to the edges of the table. Nijland’s use of colour is sober. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De titel van dit schilderij geeft aan dat het hier gaat om een eerbetoon aan de Pools-Engelse schrijver Joseph Conrad. Zijn foto is opgenomen in dit stilleven, dat verder bestaat uit verwijzingen naar de zeevaart, zoals een afbeelding van een groot zeilschip, een kaart met seinvlaggen en een grote zeekijker (een uitschuifbare telescoop). Voordat Conrad romans ging schrijven, was hij zeeman. Als kapitein op een Belgisch schip maakte hij in 1890 een reis naar de binnenlanden van Congo. Later heeft hij als kapitein op Britse koopvaardijschepen gevaren. In zijn romans verwerkt Conrad zijn belevenissen op zee. Daarbij spelen de beproevingen die zeelui ondergaan en de zelfbeheersing die vereist is om deze te doorstaan een belangrijke rol. 'Dirk Nijland had grote bewondering voor Conrad. Ook hij werd gefascineerd door de zee, havens en schepen. Hij heeft veel werk gemaakt waarop water voorkomt. In de entreehal van het Van Abbemuseum, achter de kassa, is een wandschildering van Nijland te zien met de zee als onderwerp. 'In zijn stillevens gaat Nijland zeer beheerst te werk. Hij besteedt veel aandacht aan stofuitdrukking en zijn composities zijn zorgvuldig opgebouwd. Hier liggen de voorwerpen strikt geordend, parallel aan de randen van het tafeltje. Nijlands kleurgebruik is sober. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:date>1935</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:identifier>359</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>91,6 x 126,8 x 7 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Dirk Nijland</dc:creator><dcterms:created>1935</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:title>Hommage à Conrad</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/359"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0359.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C699"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0359.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/359"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>