<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/659"><dc:date>1962</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 1962 Henk Peeters stretched a piece of white silk over a framework. He hung one white down ostrich feather from the middle of the top edge. The ostrich feather is attached at the back and moves softly when you walk by the canvas. There is a moiré effect in the silk. The feather casts a shadow onto the canvas. 'Peeters made this work when he was a member of Nul. Previously, as a member of the Informal Group, he said: “We try to see and show our own age.” In the Informal Group, emotions, spontaneity and a personal signature played an important role. Nul stepped back from this. For Nul, the artist’s own age was also a starting point, but it had to be represented in an objective way. Peeters worked with modern materials such as nylon, formica and chrome, which were unusual in the arts at that time. He also used materials which were soft and invited the viewer to touch them, such as cotton wool, synthetic furs and feathers. Nul wanted to open the public’s eyes to the beauty of the everyday environment and to the achievements of western welfare society. The work of the Nul artists consisted of fragments of isolated reality. 'Peeters said: “I always wanted my work to look fresh, as though it was on display in the Hema supermarket. It shouldn’t look artificial….” Art should not be the privilege of a small elite, but something in which everyone could recognize their own world. Nul was similar to Zero in Germany. They both wanted to make a new start in the arts and both used their own age as a starting point, preferably using contemporary materials. However, Zero had a more spiritual orientation than Nul. The Nul artist was an observer, not a seer. For Zero, immaterial phenomena such as light and movement had central place. Of all the Nul members, Peeters was the one who was closest to Zero. 62-22 subtly shows his interest in the effects of light and shade and in movement. These phenomena, combined with the softness of the feather and the glossy satin, made 62-22 a poetic piece of reality.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">struisveer, zijde</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>659</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Henk Peeters</dc:creator><dcterms:created>1962</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent>120 x 100 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">ostrich plume, silk</dc:type><dc:title>62-22</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 1962 spant Henk Peeters een stuk witte zijde over een spieraam. Vanaf het midden van de bovenrand laat hij een witte donzen struisveer naar beneden hangen. De struisveer is aan de achterkant vastgemaakt en beweegt zachtjes wanneer je langs het doek loopt. De zijde vertoont een moiré-effect. De veer geeft een schaduw op het doek. 'Peeters maakt dit werk wanneer hij lid is van Nul. Eerder, als lid van de Informele Groep, zegt hij: "Wij proberen onze eigen tijd te zien en zichtbaar te maken." Bij de Informele Groep spelen emotie, spontaniteit en persoonlijk handschrift een belangrijke rol. Nul neemt hiervan afstand. Ook voor Nul is de eigen tijd het uitgangspunt, maar deze moet op een objectieve manier worden weergegeven. Peeters werkt met voor die tijd moderne en in de kunst ongebruikelijke materialen als nylon, formica en chroom. Ook gebruikt hij stoffen die zacht zijn en uitnodigen tot aanraken, zoals watten, kunstbont en veren. Nul wil het publiek de ogen openen voor de schoonheid van de dagelijkse omgeving, voor de verworvenheden van de westerse welvaartsmaatschappij. Het werk van de Nulkunstenaars bestaat uit stukjes geïsoleerde werkelijkheid. '"Met mijn werk heb ik altijd gewild dat het er net zo fris uitzag alsof het bij de Hema lag. 't Moest niet het verkunstelde hebben...", zegt Peeters. Kunst moet geen voorrecht van een kleine elite zijn, maar iets waar iedereen zijn eigen leefwereld in kan herkennen. Nul heeft overeenkomst met Zero in Duitsland. Beide willen een nieuw begin maken in de kunst. Beide nemen de eigen tijd als uitgangspunt en gebruiken bij voorkeur eigentijdse materialen. Zero is echter spiritueler georiënteerd dan Nul. De Nulkunstenaar is een waarnemer, geen ziener. Bij Zero staan immateriële verschijnselen als licht en beweging centraal. Van de Nulleden is Peeters degene die het dichtste bij Zero staat. '62-22' toont op een subtiele manier zijn interesse in licht- en schaduwwerking en in beweging. Deze verschijnselen in combinatie met het zachte van de veer en de glanzende satijn maken '62-22' tot een poëtisch stukje werkelijkheid.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/659"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0659.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C991"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/659"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0659.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>