<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/449"><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:date>1929</dc:date><dc:identifier>449</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>112,7 x 92,2 x 3,1 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">In his early years Sluijters experimented with various modern movements, which he became particularly acquainted with during his stay in Paris. Fascinated by the expressive possibilities of shape and colour, he often painted exuberant pictures. He strove for a personal interpretation of his subject rather than an objective representation of reality. He searched experimentally ‘for the eternal concepts of beauty and harmony’, as he himself put it. During the 1920s, certain aspects of his work became more traditional. In terms of the subject matter, his 1929 "Vaas met bloemen" (Vase of Flowers) is in keeping with the long tradition of floral still lifes we can see throughout the history of Dutch art. The middle of the picture features a vase or jug with various flowers painted against a dark background. We can see a small section of the table or cabinet on which the vase is standing in an otherwise undefined room. Here Sluijters paints a blue cloth around the base of the vase. The white, red and pink flowers light up against the purple-grey background. The artist’s loose brushstrokes and the way he opts to suggest details rather than hone them in an intricate way betray his knowledge of Expressionism. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:creator>Jan Sluijters</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Vaas met bloemen</dc:title><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:created>1929</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Sluijters experimenteert in zijn jonge jaren met diverse moderne stromingen in de kunst, die hij vooral tijdens zijn verblijven in Parijs leert kennen. Gefascineerd door de expressieve mogelijkheden van vorm en kleur maakt hij vaak uitbundige schilderijen. Hij streeft daarin niet naar een objectieve weergave van de werkelijkheid, maar naar een persoonlijke vertaling van zijn onderwerp. Hij zoekt op een experimentele manier “naar de eeuwige begrippen van schoonheid en harmonie”, zoals hij het zelf omschrijft. In de loop van de jaren twintig van de 20ste eeuw wordt zijn werk in bepaalde opzichten traditioneler. Zijn 'Vaas met bloemen' uit 1929 sluit qua onderwerp aan bij de lange traditie van bloemstillevens die de Nederlandse kunstgeschiedenis kent. In het midden van het beeld staat een vaas of kan met diverse bloemen geschilderd tegen een donkere achtergrond. Er is een klein stukje zichtbaar van de tafel of kast waarop de vaas staat in een verder ongedefinieerde ruimte. Hier schildert Sluijters een blauwe doek rond de vaas. De witte, rode en roze bloemen lichten op tegen de paarsgrijze omgeving. De losse toets van de schilder en zijn keuze om details meer te suggereren dan verfijnd uit te werken, verraden zijn kennis van het expressionisme. '[2020]</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/449"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0449-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/449"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0449-01.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C789"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>