<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/341"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C681"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0341.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/341"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0341.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/341"><dc:date>(1922-1930) replica 1970</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">The 'Licht-Raum-Modulator' by László Moholy-Nagy, an artist originating from Hungary, consists of various elements. The most eye-catching element is a round plateau with geometric forms made of different materials attached to it. These shapes are set in motion by a system of cogs and a chain which connects the plateau to an electric motor in a metal case. The geometric shapes on the plateau are divided into three sectors, with the main forms of a rectangle, a circle and a diagonal. Moholy-Nagy mainly used transparent and reflecting materials. The whole work is illuminated by lamps, creating a very varied pattern of light and shade on the floor, the walls and the ceiling of the space where the work is exhibited. 'In the early 1920s, Moholy-Nagy moved from Hungary to Berlin, where he came into contact with representatives of Futurism, Constructivism and Dada, schools in which movement and machines played an important role. The combination of art and technology was also a central concept in the Bauhaus, where Moholy-Nagy lectured from 1923 to 1928, and this work also dates from that period. The idea of a machine as a work of art is based on the wish not to consider art and technology as separate disciplines which are actually opposites. There was a belief in art which did not exist alongside life, but was part of it, following the pattern of life at the same time as determining its design. This explained the interest in and use of modern industrial materials and technology. 'The 'Licht-Raum-Modulator' is a work of art and a machine at the same time. The theatrical aspect which is created when the machine is put into operation extends far beyond its technical operation alone. As the title indicates, light changes and modulates the space. The work does not consist only of the tangible object, but just as much of the elements which cannot be captured such as movement, light, shadow and reflection.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:extent>201,7 x 78,8 x 69,7 cm (incl. houten ombouw / wooden casing)</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:title>Licht-Raum Modulator</dc:title><dc:creator>László Moholy-Nagy</dc:creator><dc:identifier>341</dc:identifier><dcterms:created>(1922-1930) replica 1970</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">metaal, hout, glas, elektromotor</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">metal, wood, glass, electromotor</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De 'Licht-Raum-Modulator' van de van oorsprong Hongaarse kunstenaar László Moholy-Nagy bestaat uit verschillende onderdelen. Het meest in het oog springt een rond plateau waarop geometrische vormen uit verschillende materialen bevestigd zijn. Die vormen worden in beweging gebracht door een systeem van tandwielen en een ketting dat het plateau verbindt met een elektromotor in een metalen kast. De geometrische vormen op het plateau zijn ondergebracht in drie sectoren met als hoofdvorm de rechthoek, de cirkel en de diagonaal. Moholy-Nagy heeft vooral transparante en reflecterende materialen gebruikt. Het geheel wordt belicht door lampen. Zo ontstaat er een zeer gevarieerd licht- en schaduwspel op de vloer, de muren en het plafond van de ruimte waarin het werk is opgesteld. 'Moholy-Nagy gaat in de vroege jaren twintig van de twintigste eeuw vanuit Hongarije naar Berlijn. Hij komt daar in contact met vertegenwoordigers van het futurisme, constructivisme en Dada. In deze stromingen spelen beweging en machines een belangrijke rol. Aan het Bauhaus - waar Moholy-Nagy van 1923 tot 1928 leraar is - staat de gedachte van het samengaan van kunst en techniek centraal. Uit deze periode stamt ook dit werk. Het idee van een machine als kunstwerk komt voort uit de wens kunst en techniek niet te beschouwen als afzonderlijke disciplines die elkaars tegenpool vormen. Men gelooft in een kunst die niet nààst maar ìn het leven staat; die de vorm van het leven volgt, en tegelijkertijd het leven vorm geeft. Vandaar de interesse in en het gebruik van moderne industriële materialen en technieken. 'De 'Licht-Raum-Modulator' is tegelijkertijd een kunstwerk en een machine. Het schouwspel dat ontstaat wanneer het apparaat in werking wordt gesteld, reikt veel verder dan het technisch functioneren alleen. Zoals de titel al aangeeft, verandert en moduleert het licht de ruimte. Het werk bestaat niet alleen uit het tastbare object, maar evenzeer uit de ongrijpbare elementen beweging, licht, schaduw en reflectie.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>