<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1404"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1644"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1404.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1404"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1404.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1404"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf, acrylverf op doek</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1984</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil &amp; acrylicpaint on canvas</dc:type><dcterms:extent>200,2 x 160,2 x 2,2 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Landschapschilderij</dc:title><dc:creator>René Daniëls</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>1404</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">We could regard the reddish-brown shape in the middle of the painting as being a mountain landscape. The blue and blue-grey lines around it would then be water. The yellow ‘rays’ above it and the yellow outlined dark shape appear to be a light source in this predominantly gloomy painting. The orange-yellow rectangle in the top left corner is reminiscent of a lit window, although it does not fit in with the representation of the landscape. The three blue shapes in the foreground of the landscape are not easy to interpret. They could ‘carry’ the landscape. 'René Daniëls’s paintings are rarely unambiguous, and that is his intention. In an interview with art critic Anna Tilroe in 1983, Daniëls said, "There is a disease that typifies this day and age: the meddling of art historians in art. It often seems they are only seeking to confirm their ideas about art. Consequently, their interpretation is far too unambiguous, simply so that they can pigeon-hole you as quickly as possible". Daniëls admires artists who never allow themselves to be pushed into a corner, but take the liberty of associating or playing with the range of possibilities that painting has to offer. Here he breaks through the pattern of expectation that a painting must be explainable, and prompts the observer to draw their own associations. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De roodbruine vorm in het midden van het schilderij zou gezien kunnen worden als een berglandschap. De blauwe en blauwgrijze lijnen eromheen zouden dan water kunnen zijn. De gele ‘stralen’ erboven en de geel omlijnde donkere vorm lijken een lichtbron te zijn in dit overwegend donkere schilderij. De oranjegele rechthoek linksboven doet denken aan een verlicht raam, maar sluit niet aan bij de voorstelling van het landschap. De drie blauwe vormen onder het landschap zijn moeilijk te duiden. Ze zouden het landschap kunnen ‘dragen’. 'De schilderijen van René Daniëls zijn zelden eenduidig en dat is ook zijn bedoeling. In een in 1983 gehouden interview met kunstcriticus Anna Tilroe zegt Daniëls : “Er heerst een ziekte die typisch is voor deze tijd: de bemoeienis van de kunsthistorici met kunst. Ze lijken vaak alleen maar te zoeken naar bevestiging van hun ideeën over kunst. Het gevolg is dat er veel te eenduidig wordt geïnterpreteerd om zo snel mogelijk een stempel op je te kunnen drukken”. Daniëls bewondert kunstenaars die zich nooit in een hoek laten drukken, maar de vrijheid nemen om te associëren of te spelen met de mogelijkheden die het schilderen biedt. Hij doorbreekt hier het verwachtingspatroon dat een schilderij verklaarbaar moet zijn en zet de kijker aan tot eigen associaties. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:date>1984</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>