<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/725"><dcterms:created>1974</dcterms:created><dc:identifier>725</dc:identifier><dc:title>Twenty-fifth Steel Cardinal</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">steel sheets, hot rolled</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">staalplaten, warmgewalst</dc:type><dc:date>1974</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Twenty-fifth Steel Cardinal' is an artwork which consists of 25 separate steel plates measuring 50 x 50 cm. They are placed on the floor of the museum gallery in the shape of a square with one side of the square against the wall. The steel plates have been left untreated and are not evenly coloured. Scratches, dents, marks and discoloration mean that the plates are all different. 'The work radiates tranquillity and balance as a result of symmetry, repetition, the grey shades of the steel and the flatness of the work. Carl Andre explained: “I do not want to make works which overwhelm or blind you. I like work you can spend time with in a room and that you can ignore if you want to.” As the plates are half a centimetre thick, the artwork only takes up little space. Despite the fact that it is quite thin, the floor sculpture does have mass and weight because of the material that it used. According to Andre, the space around the artwork is just as important as the work itself. His sculptures appear to emphasise the empty space around them. He believes that his artworks suit some places better than others and therefore he believes that it is best for an artist to create a work of art in situ. 'Carl Andre’s work belongs to the school of Minimal Art. In this movement the perception of the artwork has priority. However, Andre’s floor sculptures are not only about looking, but also about listening and feeling/experiencing. The visitor is permitted to walk on the floor sculpture. Walking over the steel plates changes the appearance of the work. Instead of just looking at it from a distance, there is also the tangible experience. Every type of material sounds and feels different when you walk over it. Andre used iron, steel, aluminium, lead, copper, and zinc, amongst other materials, because he believed that: “the difference between copper and aluminium goes a lot further than the difference between red and green.”</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Twenty-fifth Steel Cardinal' is een kunstwerk dat bestaat uit vijfentwintig losse stalen platen van 50 x 50 cm. Ze liggen in de vorm van een vierkant op de vloer van de museumzaal. Met één zijde ligt het vierkant tegen de muur aan. De stalen platen zijn onbehandeld en niet egaal van kleur. Krassen, deuken, vlekken en verkleuringen zorgen ervoor dat de platen van elkaar verschillen. 'Het werk straalt rust en evenwicht uit. Dit ontstaat door de symmetrie, herhaling, de grijstinten van het staal en de platheid van het werk. Carl Andre zegt daarover "Ik wil geen werken maken die je overdonderen of verblinden. Ik houd van werk waar je je mee in een kamer kunt bevinden en dat je kan negeren als je wilt". Doordat de platen een halve centimeter dik zijn neemt het kunstwerk maar weinig ruimte in beslag. Ondanks de geringe dikte, bezit de vloersculptuur wel massa en gewicht door het gebruikte materiaal. Volgens Andre is de ruimte rondom het kunstwerk net zo belangrijk als het werk zelf. Zijn beelden benadrukken als het ware de lege ruimte eromheen. Andre vindt dat zijn kunstwerken op sommige plaatsen beter passen dan op andere. Volgens hem kan een kunstenaar daarom het beste ter plekke zijn kunstwerk creëren. 'Het werk van Carl Andre wordt tot de minimal art gerekend. In deze kunststroming staat de waarneming van het kunstwerk voorop. Bij de vloersculpturen van Andre gaat het echter niet alleen over kijken, maar ook over luisteren en voelen/ervaren. Het is toegestaan de vloersculptuur te betreden. Lopen over de stalen platen verandert het aanzien van het werk. In plaats van het alleen op afstand bekijken is er dan ook de tastbare ervaring. Elke materiaalsoort klinkt en voelt anders wanneer er over heen gelopen wordt. Andre gebruikt o.a. ijzer, staal, aluminium, lood, koper of zink, omdat volgens hem "het verschil tussen koper en aluminium heel wat verder gaat dan dat tussen rood en groen".</dc:description><dcterms:extent>(geïnstalleerd / installed) 0,5 x 250 x 250 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Carl Andre</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/725"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1054"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/725"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0725-03.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0725-03.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>