<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/379"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0379.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0379.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/379"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C719"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/379"><dc:description xml:lang="en">This still life by Bart Peizel gives the viewer an insight into the artist’s interests. Originally from Groningen, in 1910 he moved to Amsterdam where he became acquainted with Impressionism, and the loose brushstrokes with which he painted reveal how he was influenced by this style. In "Stilleven met boeken" he also shows his interest in this movement by depicting reproductions of two paintings by the French Impressionist Manet: "Woman Reading", and "On the Beach". There are also references to Japanese print art. At the top left of the painting we can make out a Japanese figure, and on the table there is an open book in which we can make out the word ‘holzschnitt’ (woodcut) and the letters ‘kusai’ which we can assume refer to the famous Japanese printmaker Hokusai, who was very popular in Western Europe around 1900. 'The fact that Peizel loved sailing could be the reason why he depicts the book "Sur la Route du Retour" by Alain Gerbault. This French yachtsman became famous because of the accounts he wrote of his voyages, for instance to islands in the Pacific Ocean. 'The still life also features the rolled-up magazine "Rire", a satirical magazine that was published in Paris between 1894 and 1971. The novel "De heks van Gouda" (The Witch of Gouda) by J.W. van Cittert, was published in 1931 and tells about the alleged evil influence exerted by an old woman in 16th century Gouda. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:title>Stilleven met boeken</dc:title><dcterms:created>1933</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:identifier>379</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit stilleven geeft de kijker een inzicht in de interesses van de schilder Bart Peizel. Afkomstig uit Groningen vestigt hij zich in 1910 in Amsterdam, waar hij kennis maakt met de stijl van het impressionisme. Zijn werk vertoont invloed daarvan door de losse toets waarmee hij schildert. Daarnaast laat hij in ‘Stilleven met boeken’ zijn interesse in deze stroming zien door reproducties van twee schilderijen van de Franse impressionist Manet af te beelden: 'Woman Reading' (Lezende vrouw), en 'On the Beach' (Op het strand). Verder zijn er verwijzingen naar de Japanse prentkunst. Linksboven in het schilderij is een Japanse figuur te herkennen, en op de tafel staat een opengeslagen boek waarin de woorden ‘holzschnitt’ (houtsnede) en ‘kusai’ te lezen zijn. ‘kusai’ zal verwijzen naar de beroemde Japanse prentkunstenaar Hokusai, die rond 1900 zeer geliefd was in West-Europa. 'Dat Peizel van zeilen hield, zou de reden kunnen zijn dat hij het boek ‘Sur la route du retour’ van Alain Gerbault afbeeldt. Deze Franse zeezeiler werd beroemd door de verslagen die hij maakte van zijn reizen, o.a. naar eilanden in de Stille Oceaan. 'In het stilleven valt ook het opgerolde tijdschrift 'Rire' op, een satirisch blad dat tussen 1894 en 1971 werd uitgegeven in Parijs. De roman ‘De heks van Gouda’, van J.W. van Cittert, werd in 1931 gepubliceerd en vertelt over de vermeende kwade invloed van een oude vrouw in Gouda in de 16de eeuw. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:creator>Bart Peizel</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>60,1 x 80,5 x 2,3 cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1933</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>