<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3428"><dc:identifier>3428</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Tony Chakar</dc:creator><dc:title>Of Other Worlds That Are In This One</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">iron, laser cutting, direct UV print on iron, spot lights</dc:type><dc:date>2014-2017</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Of Other Worlds that Are in This One' werd voor de eerste keer getoond op de Biënnale van São Paulo in 2014 en kreeg een nieuwe vorm in Chakar's grote solotentoonstelling in het Beiroet Art Center in 2017. De installatie bestaat uit een metalen wand met afbeeldingen van personen die Chakar bij toeval ontdekte op foto’s die hij tijdens zijn reizen maakte van lege stadsgezichten. De software slaagde er slechts ten dele in een menselijk gezicht van een object te onderscheiden. Deze irrationaliteit identificeerde Chakar als 'momenten van visie', als breuken in het weefsel van onze wereld die mogelijk inzicht geven in 'een andere wereld die zich in deze bevindt'. Deze afbeeldingen combineert hij met teksten van esoterische geschriften uit de islam, het christendom en de Kabala, die uit de metalen wand zijn gesneden. Het licht van de tentoonstellingsruimte projecteert de teksten op de muur achter de metalen wand, in een spel van licht en schaduw. 'Tony Chakar woont en werkt in Beiroet. Sinds 1999 ontwikkelt hij projecten die ingaan op de complexe sociale, politieke en religieuze geschiedenis van zijn geboortestad en regio. Sporen van oorlog en vernietiging, nieuwbouw en gentrificatie domineren de publieke ruimte, monotheïstische religies strijden om de suprematie in de regio. Chakar gebruikt taal, afbeeldingen en architecturale vormen om deze complexiteit te vangen in een lichamelijke ervaring.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>installatie afmeting variabel / installation dimensions variable</dcterms:extent><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">ijzer, lasersnijden, direct UV print op ijzer, lichtspotjes</dc:type><dcterms:created>2014-2017</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Of Other Worlds that Are in this One' was first shown at the São Paulo Biennial in 2014 and developed further in Chakar’s major solo exhibition 'On Becoming Two' at Beirut Art Centre in 2017. A metal wall holds images of strangers that Chakar discovered by coincidence through facial recognition software in photographs of empty cityscapes taken during his travels. The randomness of the software, and its regular failure to distinguish a human face from an object, show an irrationality in the midst of what is considered the most rational of all human constructs. Chakar identified them as ‘moments of vision’ – as mystics might describe them. They appear as ruptures in the fabric of our world that might allow insight into ‘another world that is in this one’. The images are combined with texts from esoteric writings – Muslim, Gnostic Christian and Kabballah mysticism – which are cut out of the metal wall and thus become negative tracts. The light from the exhibition space projects the texts on the wall behind the metal, creating a game of light and shadow in the narrow corridor behind that disturbs the cold, sharp logic of the materials. 'Tony Chakar lives and works in Beirut. Since 1999 he has developed projects that address the complex social and political histories of his hometown and region. The material evidence of war and conflict that have stood in the city since the Lebanese Civil War 1975-1990, are intersected by jarring moments of renewal and gentrification – as though everything is happening simultaneously. Against this background, Chakar explores the idea and reality of public space and how different temporalities and communities come to recognise and use it. The religious complexity of Lebanon also leaves its mark on the work, as the world’s major monotheist religions still battle it out for supremacy in the region. In the works in the exhibition, he uses language, images and architectural forms to create a bodily experience of narrative where time is out of joint and modernity meets its limits.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3428"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C12240"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3428-A1.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3428-A1.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3428"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>