<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/318"><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Giant' by the Dutch artist Lucebert is a dark painting. A head consisting of thin white lines can be discerned against a background of mainly brown and black paint. The eyes are right at the top; the mouth is above the centre of the head, which fills the painting. It is difficult to determine exactly what forms the mouth – the black outline with vertical lines or the thin white lines and colours between them, or everything together. At any rate, an image of a large mouth with teeth is evoked. 'In 1949 Lucebert’s work was part of an exhibition of the Cobra movement. In fact, that movement, which was established in 1948, existed for only three years. Afterwards the artists each went their own way, though they continued to carry their traces of Cobra with them. The Cobra painters often used mythological creatures, fabulous animals or tortured characters as a starting point for a painting and these creatures were represented in a childlike or naïve way. The Cobra painters were very interested in the visual expressions of people who directly expressed their feelings, unhindered by artistic rules and conventions. They related this to children, the mentally ill, and “primitive” people. They aimed for the same direct approach in their own work, also devoting attention to the materials with which they worked: how paint drips or splashes, how stains merge together, how colours and forms behave as independent elements. 'The Cobra influence is clearly present in 'Giant'. The work is very much part of the movement in terms of the subject and method of painting. Lucebert used the possibilities of his materials. In one place he allowed the paint to drip freely, in other places he deliberately painted a firm line. Some of the lines result from pouring the paint over the canvas and letting it run, while others are scratched into the paint. The way the materials are used contributes to the expressive force of the painting: the dark colours, the spots and scratches emphasize the threatening and “ugly” aspects evoked by the subject of a giant. The eyes placed high up in the face are typical of a child’s drawing.</dc:description><dc:creator>Lucebert</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1961</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Reus' van de Nederlandse kunstenaar Lucebert is een donker schilderij. Op een ondergrond van hoofdzakelijk bruine en zwarte verf tekent zich in dunne witte lijnen een hoofd af. De ogen zitten helemaal bovenin; de mond nog boven het midden van de beeldvullende kop. Wat precies de mond vormt, is moeilijk te bepalen; de zwarte omtrek met verticale strepen, of de dunne witte lijnen en kleuren daartussen, of dat alles bij elkaar. In ieder geval wordt het beeld van een grote mond met tanden opgeroepen. 'Luceberts werk maakt in 1949 deel uit van een tentoonstelling van de Cobrabeweging. Feitelijk heeft deze beweging - opgericht in 1948 - maar drie jaar bestaan. Daarna gaan de kunstenaars ieder hun eigen weg, maar ze dragen de sporen van Cobra met zich mee. De Cobraschilders nemen vaak mythologische wezens, fabeldieren of gekwelde personen als uitgangspunt voor een schilderij. Deze wezens worden op een kinderlijk naïeve manier weergegeven. De schilders rond Cobra zijn zeer geïnteresseerd in de beeldende uitingen van mensen die, niet gehinderd door artistieke regels en conventies, hun gevoelens direct in beeld brengen. Zij denken daarbij aan kinderen, geesteszieken, 'primitieve' volkeren. Eenzelfde directheid streven ze na in hun eigen werk. Daarbij hebben ze ook aandacht voor het materiaal waarmee ze werken: hoe verf spat of druipt, hoe vlekken in elkaar lopen, hoe kleuren en vormen zich als zelfstandige elementen gedragen. 'In 'Reus' is de invloed van Cobra duidelijk terug te vinden. Qua onderwerp en schilderwijze sluit het schilderij bij deze beweging aan. Lucebert benut de mogelijkheden van zijn materiaal. Op de ene plaats laat hij de verf vrij druipen, op de andere plaats zet hij gericht een stevige lijn. Sommige lijnen ontstaan door de verf kringelend over het doek te gieten, andere worden in de verf gekrast. Het materiaalgebruik draagt bij aan de expressieve lading die het schilderij heeft: de donkere kleuren, de vlekken en krassen benadrukken het dreigende en het 'lelijke' dat het onderwerp 'reus' oproept. De hoog in het gezicht geplaatste ogen zijn typerend voor een kindertekening.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1961</dcterms:created><dc:identifier>318</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>buitenmaat incl.lijst: 150,9 x 101,4 x 5 cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:title>Reus</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/318"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/318"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0318.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0318.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C658"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>