<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/472"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0472.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/472"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0472.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C812"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/472"><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this painting, Charley Toorop presents her own face from the front. It virtually fills the whole canvas. On either side she has painted a pattern of white and black lines, which, in combination with the title of the work, evokes an association with bare, snowy branches. It works more as an abstract flat background than as a naturalist spatial environment. The various parts of the face are indicated with sharp outlines. Every line and wrinkle is clearly visible and there is a marked contrast between light and shade. It is as though the subject of the portrait is illuminated by a powerful source of light. She has a penetrating gaze, looking at the viewer (and therefore also at herself while she was painting the portrait) in an inquisitive way. Her hair forms the transition between her face and the background, not only because of the space it takes up, but also because of the way she painted it. 'In Charley Toorop’s paintings – especially her portraits – the subject of a head was often shown from the front and filled the entire canvas, which gives the impression of something inescapable. She was interested in the essence of the subjects of her portraits. She preferred to paint people who exuded strength and led an individual life, like she did herself. She did this in an objective way and presented what she saw in a very business-like way. In this respect her work is linked to that of the Neue Sachlichkeit in Germany. In that art movement artists aimed at objectivity, avoiding any form of idealism or sentiment. 'In the Netherlands there was a group of artists including Carel Willink and Pyke Koch, who were related to the Neue Sachlichkeit in terms of their style of painting. However, their work had a more singular atmosphere and is therefore described with the term “Magic Realism”. Toorop was also associated with them, although she painted in a less sophisticated style and her work was more expressive. Its strength does not lie in the alienation of Willink’s work, but actually in a raw style devoid of artifice. In that respect her work reveals similarities to Expressionist painters such as Chabot. Although her style of painting maintained a distance, she had a strong social commitment to the people that she painted. She painted portraits of artists, writers and art lovers who were friends (sometimes in groups) and the members of her family, including her father Jan Toorop and her son Edgar Fernhout ,were also the subject of her paintings several times.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>68 x 58 x 3,5 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:date>1944-1945</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:creator>Charley Toorop</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:title>Zelfportret met wintertakken</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Op dit schilderij beeldt Charley Toorop haar eigen gezicht frontaal af. Het vult vrijwel het hele doek. Aan weerszijden ervan schildert zij een patroon van witte en zwarte strepen dat, in combinatie met de titel van het werk, de associatie met kale, besneeuwde takken oproept. Het werkt meer als abstracte, vlakke achtergrond dan als naturalistische, ruimtelijke omgeving. De verschillende onderdelen van het gezicht worden met scherpe contouren aangegeven. Iedere lijn en rimpel is duidelijk zichtbaar. Licht- en schaduwpartijen staan in sterk contrast met elkaar. Het is alsof de geportretteerde door een sterke lichtbron beschenen wordt. Haar blik is indringend; ze kijkt de beschouwer (en dus ook zichzelf terwijl ze het portret schildert) onderzoekend aan. Het haar vormt de overgang tussen gezicht en achtergrond; niet alleen door de plaats die het heeft, maar ook door de manier waarop Toorop het schildert. 'In Charley Toorops schilderijen - vooral haar portretten - wordt het hoofdmotief vaak frontaal en vlakvullend in beeld gebracht. Het geeft de voorstelling iets onontkoombaars. Toorop is geïnteresseerd in het wezen van de door haar geportretteerden. Ze schildert bij voorkeur mensen waar een kracht vanuit gaat; die een eigenzinnig leven leiden (zoals Toorop zelf). Ze doet dit op een objectiverende manier: ze geeft op zakelijke wijze weer wat haar oog ziet. In dit opzicht sluit haar werk aan bij de Neue Sachlichkeit in Duitsland. In deze richting in de kunst streeft men naar objectiviteit; iedere vorm van idealisme of sentiment wordt vermeden. 'In Nederland is er een groep kunstenaars, waaronder Carel Willink en Pyke Koch, die qua schilderstijl verwantschap hebben met de Neue Sachlichkeit. Hun werk heeft echter een vreemdere sfeer. Daarom wordt het aangeduid met de term magisch realisme. Toorop wordt wel met hen in verband gebracht. Ze schildert echter minder verfijnd. Haar werk is expressiever. De kracht ervan ligt niet in het vervreemdende zoals bij Willink, maar juist in het rauwe en ongekunstelde. Wat dat betreft vertoont haar werk overeenkomst met expressionistische schilders als Chabot. Hoewel haar schilderstijl afstandelijk is, heeft zij een sterke sociale betrokkenheid bij de mensen die zij schildert. Bevriende kunstenaars, schrijvers en kunstkenners worden door haar (soms in groepsverband) geportretteerd. Ook haar familieleden, waaronder haar vader Jan Toorop en haar zoon Edgar Fernhout, keren diverse malen terug als onderwerp voor een schilderij.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1944-1945</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>472</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>