<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/436"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C776"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0436.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0436.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/436"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/436"><dcterms:extent>76,9 x 66,5 x 6,5 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:title>Landscape Toledo</dc:title><dc:creator>Wim Schuhmacher</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1933-1934</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Aan het begin van zijn carrière als kunstschilder experimenteert Schuhmacher met nieuwe stromingen als het expressionisme en het kubisme. Vanaf 1925 kiest hij voor een meer realistische stijl, hoewel invloeden uit het modernisme zichtbaar blijven. In dit landschap gebruikt hij vooral grijze, vaalgroene en oker kleuren, een keuze die ook het vroege kubisme kenmerkt. De huizen van Toledo geeft hij tamelijk precies en in een realistisch perspectief weer, voor zover het grootte betreft. Het landschap eromheen wordt geabstraheerd door hoogteverschillen aan te duiden met diagonale lijnen die scherper zijn dan ze in werkelijkheid waargenomen zouden worden. De bomen op de voorgrond en de huizen in de verte zijn even helder geschilderd, waardoor de dieptewerking in het schilderij wordt tegengegaan, zoals bij het gebruik van een telelens. De stammen en takken van de bomen zijn zo dun dat de bovenste delen bijna aparte bomen lijken op de andere oever van de rivier. Maar deze corresponderen qua maat dan niet met de gebouwen in de stad. Al met al schept Schuhmacher een beeld dat herkenbaar èn vervreemdend is. Net als het 'Gezicht op Toledo' waarin de Grieks-Spaanse kunstenaar El Greco rond 1600 deze stad afbeeldt tegen een dreigende lucht. Schuhmacher bezocht Toledo in 1932. '[2020]</dc:description><dcterms:created>1933-1934</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>436</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">At the start of his career as an artist, Schuhmacher experimented with new movements such as Expressionism and Cubism. From 1925 onwards he opted for a more realistic style, although we can still see some influences from Modernism. In this landscape he principally uses grey, pale green and ochre, a choice that is also characteristic of early Cubism. In terms of their dimensions, he depicts the houses of Toledo fairly accurately, using realistic perspective. The surrounding landscape has been abstracted by indicating height differences using diagonal lines that are sharper than they would be when seen in real life. The trees in the foreground and the houses in the distance are painted as clearly as one another, foreshortening the perspective in the painting, as is the case when using a telephoto lens. The trunks and branches of the trees are so thin that the upper parts look almost like separate trees on the opposite riverbank. However, with regard to their size, they do not correspond with the buildings in the city. All in all, Schuhmacher creates an image that is at once recognizable and alienating. It is reminiscent of the "View of Toledo" in which the Greek-Spanish artist El Greco painted this city against a menacing sky in around 1600. Schuhmacher visited Toledo in 1932. '[2020]</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>