<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3475"><dcterms:created>2018</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">kranten (De Telegraaf, 20 juli 1943 / De Standaard, 27 juli 1943)</dc:type><dc:date>2018</dc:date><dc:identifier>3475</dc:identifier><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Erwin Thomasse</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">newspapers (De Telegraaf, 20 July 1943 / De Standaard, 27 July 1943)</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">This artwork by artist Erwin Thomasse from Eindhoven, is about his father’s and mother’s relationship, by using the front page of the newspaper from their dates of birth. Thomasse’s parents were born a week apart in 1943, in the middle of the Second World War. 'The idea behind the piece was a welcome gift from the newspaper 'De Telegraaf' to his father who, as a new subscriber, was given the front page published on his date of birth, 20 July, 1943. Thomasse realised that his father had simultaneously been handed a dubious piece of this newspaper's past. During the war, 'De Telegraaf' had represented the German occupiers in its reporting. 'While reflecting on his parents’ relationship, Thomasse, as a counterpart to 'De Telegraaf', looked for a newspaper that could serve as a model for the position of his mother. He opted for ‘De Standaard’, a newspaper that served as a sounding board for the Anti-Revolutionary Party (ARP) and the Reformed Church in the Netherlands (GKN). 'During the war, 'De Standaard' had mainly tried to adopt a neutral position. However, under pressure, the newspaper eventually bowed to the occupying forces, at which point it called upon a quote from the Bible: ‘Let every person be subject to the governing authorities. For there is no authority except from God, and those that exist have been instituted by God. 'By presenting newspaper front pages as a portrait, Thomasse forges a link between public life and private life. He shows how social, political and religious power structures determine our identities and affect one another. The relationship between the news on 20 July 1943 and the follow-up to it on 27 July shows the inescapable connection of events, which also applies to the relationship between his parents. 'The title of the piece refers to the medications that his parents used to make their lives bearable. In so doing, the artist demonstrates how intense their relationship was. In addition, Thomasse questions the use of medication to treat symptoms.</dc:description><dc:title>Nozinan &amp; Primidone</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit werk van de Eindhovense kunstenaar Erwin Thomasse is een portret van de relatie tussen zijn ouders aan de hand van de voorpagina van de krant op hun geboortedag. Thomasse’s ouders werden een week na elkaar geboren in hetzelfde jaar, 1943, midden in de Tweede Wereldoorlog. 'Aanleiding voor het werk was een schenking van dagblad De Telegraaf aan zijn vader als nieuwe abonnee. Deze ontving een kopie van de voorpagina van de krant van 20 juli 1943, zijn geboortedag. Thomasse realiseerde zich dat zijn vader een dubieus stukje verleden van de krant cadeau had gekregen. In de oorlog koos De Telegraaf wat berichtgeving betreft de zijde van de Duitse bezetter. Nadenkend over de relatie tussen zijn ouders, zocht Thomasse als tegenhanger voor De Telegraaf naar een dagblad dat model zou kunnen staan voor de positie van zijn moeder. Hij koos voor De Standaard, een dagblad dat de positie van de Anti-Revolutionaire Partij en de Gereformeerde Kerken in Nederland vertegenwoordigde. 'De Standaard bleef in de oorlog verschijnen en probeerde vooral een neutrale houding aan te nemen. Uiteindelijk zwichtte de krant voor de druk van de bezetters en beriep zich daarbij op de bijbel: Ieder mens moet zich onderwerpen aan de overheden, die boven hem staan. Want er is geen overheid dan door God en die er zijn, zijn door God gesteld.” 'Door de voorpagina’s als portret te presenteren, trekt Thomasse verbindingen tussen het persoonlijke met het publieke. Hij laat zien hoe sociale, politieke en religieuze machtsstructuren, onze identiteit bepalen en elkaar wederzijds beïnvloeden. De relatie tussen het nieuws van 20 juli en het vervolg daarvan op 27 juli 1943 toont de onontkoombare verbondenheid der gebeurtenissen, zoals die ook geldt voor de relatie tussen Thomasse’s ouders. 'De titel van het werk verwijst naar de medicijnen die zijn ouders gebruikten om hun leven leefbaar te maken. Daarmee geeft de kunstenaar aan hoe ingrijpend deze relatie was. Daarnaast stelt Thomasse het gebruik van geneesmiddelen als symptoombestrijding ter discussie.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3475"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C12251"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3475-01.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3475-01.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3475"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>