<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3528"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3528"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3528.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3528.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C12435"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3528"><dcterms:created>2015</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De fotoserie Anatomie van een Revolutie: Rojava (2015) realiseerde kunstenaar Jonas Staal tijdens zijn eerste reis naar Rojava in 2014. De serie documenteert het ontstaan van de radicale nieuwe instituties sinds de Revolutie van Rojava. 'Een oude fontein van het Assad regime in Qamislo is getransformeerd tot een monument voor de Revolutie van Rojava waarop portretten van martelaren, overleden revolutionairen, zijn afgebeeld. De constructie is overgeschilderd in de kleuren geel–rood–groen van de vlag van de Beweging voor een Democratische Samenleving (TEV-DEM), een parapluorganisatie van diverse politieke partijen en sociale bewegingen in Rojava.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">diasec print</dc:type><dc:identifier>3528</dc:identifier><dc:title>Anatomy of a Revolution: Rojava</dc:title><dc:creator>Jonas Staal</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">Jonas Staal produced the photo series Anatomy of a Revolution: Rojava (2015) during his first travel to Rojava in 2014. It documents the emergence of radical new institutions since the start of the Rojava Revolution. 'And old fountain dating from the period of the Assad regime in Qamislo has been turned into a monument of the Rojava Revolution, featuring several portraits of martyrs, deceased revolutionaries. The monument has been painted in yellow–red–green, the colors of the flag of the Movement for a Democratic Society (TEV-DEM), an umbrella organization for the different political parties and social movements in Rojava.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>2015</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>