<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/974"><dc:identifier>974</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">This lithograph shows a school of fish, busy eating members of own species, as can be seen by the tails sticking out of the fish’s mouths. Although it could refer to the saying ‘big fish eat small fish’, in this picture there appears to be no difference in size between the fish that are eating and the ones being eaten. Through his work, René Daniëls regularly uses various levels of symbolism to point out competition in the art world. Here he might be referring to the idea of young artists (the Hollandse nieuwe, which could be taken to mean Dutch novices as well as soused herring) trying to make a name for themselves by eliminating the competition. However Daniel once said that he came up with this idea while he himself was eating soused herring. It tasted so good that he thought to himself, "Imagine if they were to discover how good they taste. Perhaps they would eat each other up and we’d be left with nothing!" 'The print is part of a portfolio of ten lithographs by young artists from Brabant and Zeeland, and published by curator Geert Schriever. Figuration is important in their work, so by using it, they followed the international trend that, after a period in which minimalist and conceptual art had prevailed, the narrative would be considered important again. '[2020]</dc:description><dcterms:extent>64,9 x 79,8 x 2,8 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">litho op papier</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">lithograph on paper</dc:type><dc:date>1982</dc:date><dc:title>Hollandse nieuwe ontdekt hoe goed Hollandse nieuwe smaakt</dc:title><dcterms:created>1982</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>René Daniëls</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Deze litho laat een school vissen zien, bezig met het opeten van soortgenoten, wat blijkt uit de staarten die uit de bekken van de vissen steken. Het zou kunnen verwijzen naar het spreekwoord ‘grote vissen eten de kleine’, hoewel er geen verschil in grootte lijkt te zijn hier, tussen de vissen die eten en die gegeten worden. René Daniëls verwijst in zijn werk regelmatig in meer of minder bedekte termen naar de competitie in de kunstwereld. Het zou hier dus kunnen gaan om jonge kunstenaars (de Hollandse nieuwe) die proberen daarin een plek te bemachtigen door concurrenten weg te werken. Maar Daniëls vertelde eens dat hij op dit idee kwam toen hij haring zat te eten. Die smaakte zo goed dat hij dacht: “Stel dat ze ontdekken hoe lekker ze zelf zijn. Dan vreten ze elkaar misschien allemaal op en hebben wij niets meer!” 'De prent maakt deel uit van een portfolio met 10 litho’s van jonge kunstenaars uit Brabant en Zeeland, gepubliceerd door uitgever en curator Geert Schriever. Figuratie is belangrijk in hun werk. Zij sloten daarmee aan bij de internationale tendens dat het verhalende weer belangrijk gevonden werd, na een periode waarin minimalistische en conceptuele kunst de boventoon voerden. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/974"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0974.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/974"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1272"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0974.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>