<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/134"><dc:identifier>134</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Juan Gris</dc:creator><dcterms:created>1920</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>80,9 × 65,4 × 2,4 cm 85,8 × 70,3 × 3,5 cm (incl. lijst/ frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">The Spanish artist Juan Gris composed this painting from disparate elements. Some of them can be recognized by their shape as objects or fragments of objects, while others are abstract. All the shapes, both the recognizable and the abstract shapes, are completely equal in the composition and the work has been composed more or less symmetrically. The top corners are the same colour, as are the bottom corners. The ochre coloured planes to the left and right of the centre have been divided in a balanced way. The shapes have been painted as evenly as possible and there are no differences in colour within a plane and there are no clearly visible brushstrokes. 'In 'Nature morte' the emphasis is on the planes and flat surface and there is no suggestion of depth. The starting points of synthetic Cubism, the second stage of Cubism, are clearly visible in this work and fragments from reality are joined together on the canvas to create a new whole. This painting by Gris has been created with a great deal of thought using principles such as symmetry transformations, reflective symmetry and ”shape rhyme”. In terms of shape, the opening in the glass corresponds to the hole in the guitar, an example of shape rhyme, but in terms of colour they are opposite. There is also colour reversal in the bottom of the jug. Shape rhyme occurs again in the contours of the jug, which is the same shape as the guitar. These sorts of curves also occur in the bottom edge of the manuscript paper and in the outlines of the abstract planes at the bottom right. 'Gris was more of an architect than a painter in the composition of his paintings and his training as an engineer probably played a role in this. When Braque said “I can turn a bottle into a cylinder when I am painting,” Gris answered, “I can turn a cylinder into a bottle when I am painting.” They often painted the same objects, such as a musical instrument, a pipe, bottle, or bowl of fruit, but these objects had a different significance for each of them. For Braque they were familiar objects from his environment, while for Gris they were the concrete expression of abstract forms. Their comments illustrate the essential difference in their work.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De Spaanse kunstenaar Juan Gris heeft dit schilderij samengesteld uit losse elementen. Sommige zijn door hun vorm herkenbaar als objecten of fragmenten daarvan; andere zijn abstract. Alle vormen, herkenbare en abstracte, zijn volkomen gelijkwaardig binnen de compositie. Het werk is min of meer symmetrisch opgebouwd. De bovenhoeken hebben dezelfde kleur, de benedenhoeken ook. De okerkleurige vlakken links en rechts van het midden zijn evenwichtig verdeeld. De vormen zijn zo vlak mogelijk geschilderd. Er is geen sprake van kleurverschillen binnen een vlak en er is geen duidelijke penseelstreek zichtbaar. 'In 'Nature morte' ligt de nadruk op vlakken en vlakheid. Er wordt op geen enkele manier diepte gesuggereerd. In dit werk zijn de uitgangspunten van het synthetisch kubisme, de tweede fase van het kubisme, duidelijk terug te vinden. Fragmenten uit de werkelijkheid worden op het beeldvlak aaneengevoegd tot een nieuw geheel. Dit schilderij van Gris zit heel doordacht in elkaar. Hij past principes als symmetrie, omkering en beeldrijm toe. De opening in het glas correspondeert qua vorm met het gat in de gitaar (een voorbeeld van beeldrijm) maar qua kleur zijn ze tegengesteld. Ook in de bodem van de kan zit een kleuromkering. Beeldrijm komt opnieuw voor in de contour van de kan, die gelijkvormig is aan die van de gitaar. Dergelijke curven komen ook terug in de onderrand van het muziekpapier en in de begrenzing van de abstracte vlakken rechtsonder. 'Gris is meer architect dan schilder in zijn beeldopbouw. Zijn opleiding tot ingenieur speelt hier wellicht een rol. Op Braques opmerking: "van een fles maak ik al schilderende een cilinder", antwoordt Gris: "van een cilinder maak ik al schilderende een fles". Ze schilderen vaak dezelfde voorwerpen, zoals een muziekinstrument, pijp, fles, of fruitschaal, maar deze objecten hebben voor ieder van hen een verschillende betekenis. Voor Braque zijn het geliefde voorwerpen uit zijn omgeving; voor Gris zijn het concrete invullingen van abstracte vormen. Hun uitspraken illustreren het wezenlijke verschil in hun werk.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1920</dc:date><dc:title>Nature morte</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/134"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0134-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/134"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C475"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0134-01.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>