<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1403"><dc:title>Piccadilly Circus</dc:title><dc:identifier>1403</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:date>1980-1984</dc:date><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>(1x) 50,3 x 50,3 x 2,2 cm, (1x) 40,3 x 40,3 x 2,2 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De titel van dit werk verwijst naar het gelijknamige plein in Londen dat als een van de highlights van de Britse hoofdstad bekend staat. Het is een druk verkeersknooppunt en heeft een belangrijk metrostation. Grote lichtreclames trekken de aandacht van de bezoekers en passanten. Deze schilderijtjes van René Daniëls laten een heel ander Piccadilly Circus zien. De compositie is gebaseerd op de bocht van winkelstraat Regent Street gezien vanaf het plein. Een soort omgekeerde golf vormt de lucht die zichtbaar is tussen de donkere silhouetten van de gebouwen. Op het linker schilderij is de lucht donkerblauw, zoals bij nacht. Op het rechter werk is de lucht licht van kleur, met daarin enkele blauwe puntjes, alsof het een omgekeerde sterrenhemel is. Daniels richt de aandacht niet op de kleurrijke drukte van het plein, maar kijkt ervan weg en naar boven. '[2020]</dc:description><dcterms:created>1980-1984</dcterms:created><dc:creator>René Daniëls</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">The title of this work refers to the eponymous square in London that is one of the British capital’s best known highlights. As well as being a busy crossroads, it has a major underground station. Its large illuminated advertising screens grab the attention of visitors and passers-by. These paintings by René Daniëls show a completely different Piccadilly Circus. Their composition is based on the curve of Regent Street as viewed from the square. A kind of inverted wave forms the sky that can be seen between the dark silhouettes of the buildings. The painting on the left depicts the sky in dark blue, as it is at night. In the painting on the right, the sky is light with a few blue dots, as if it were a negative image of a starry sky. Rather than focusing his attention on the colourful crowds of the square, Daniëls casts his gaze away from it and upwards. '[2020]</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1403"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1403.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1403"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1643"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1403.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>