<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1457"><dc:title>Genetiese Heimwee</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">The artist juxtaposes warm and cold colours to render a certain aggressiveness to this portrayal of a woman. The colours contrast with the penetrating yet empty gaze of the subject. Dumas uses the medium of painting for its expressive qualities. Here it is used to create tension between depiction and representation. The human figure gives the impression of being tormented, as if she is engaged in a struggle with herself. The macabre and ominous character of the painting helps it ‘invade the soul’ of the viewer. 'Dumas’s work deals with the relationship between art and reality, intention and interpretation, the process of using language and images to convey meaning and to communicate. She portrays themes such as love, fear, cruelty and eroticism based on personal memories, emotions and experiences. 'As with all of her paintings, this work has not been painted using a live model, but with a Polaroid that works as a kind of buffer between the artist and the subject. The emotions captured by Dumas are predominantly her own rather than those of the person being portrayed. Consequently, she has been able to effectively refute the persistent misconception that the portrait conveys the subject’s state of mind. '-2019</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:created>1984</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De kunstenaar gebruikt zowel warme als koude kleuren om een nogal agressief beeld van een vrouw te schilderen. Deze kleuren contrasteren met de doordringende maar lege blik van de geportretteerde. Dumas gebruikt het medium verf vanwege zijn expressieve kwaliteiten: hier zien we de spanning tussen afbeelding en representatie. De menselijke figuur wekt de indruk dat ze wordt gefolterd, zozeer worstelt ze met zichzelf. Door zijn macabere en onheilspellende karakter slaagt het schilderij erin ‘door te dringen in de ziel’ van de kijker. 'Het werk van Dumas behandelt de relatie tussen kunst en werkelijkheid, intentie en interpretatie, het proces van betekenistoekenning en communicatie door middel van taal en beelden. Ze beeldt thema’s als liefde, angst, wreedheid en erotiek uit op basis van persoonlijke herinneringen, emoties en ervaringen. 'Zoals alle schilderijen van Dumas is dit werk niet geschilderd naar levend model, maar naar polaroids die ze als een soort buffer tussen zichzelf en het model plaatst. De emoties die Dumas vastlegt zijn voornamelijk die van haarzelf en niet die van de geportretteerde. Wat dat betreft is zij er inderdaad in geslaagd het hardnekkige misverstand dat het portret de gemoedstoestand van het model weerspiegelt uit de wereld te helpen. '-2019</dc:description><dc:identifier>1457</dc:identifier><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1984</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dcterms:extent>130,4 x 110,6 x 2,5 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Marlene Dumas</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1457"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1457"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1457-01.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1457-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1687"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>