<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/147"><dcterms:created>1960</dcterms:created><dc:creator>Anton Heyboer</dc:creator><dc:identifier>147</dc:identifier><dc:date>1960</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">This engraving by the Dutch artist Anton Heyboer was made with the use of two separate zinc plates which were printed one below the other with a small space in between. The four elements from the title can be seen in the lower print. Crisscrossing lines form a pattern of diamonds. On the left there are three coloured bars: black, white and a brownish red. In the middle there is a circle. The top right corner contains a square shape with rounded corners which could be seen as a face, also because of the marks which have been scratched into it. The top print joins the lower print on the right side. On the left side, it is slightly indented. Various vertical lines from the bottom plate continue onto the top plate. In addition to the above-mentioned elements, both plates contain a number of inscriptions that are like drawings. The engraving was made in very roughly polished zinc and countless scratches are visible in the background. 'Heyboer lived a very unconventional life. From the early 1960s he lived with four or five women and a large number of pets in very primitive conditions on a piece of land with a farmer’s shed. His aversion to what he considered an over-regulated western society could be explained to some extent by his earlier history when he spent part of his youth in Indonesia and Curaçao. In the Second World War he was captured by the Germans and was badly treated when he was put to work in a camp near Berlin. 'After the war Heyboer started to draw. In the 1950s, after spending some time in a psychiatric institution, he developed a philosophical system which was translated in the imagery of his work. He produced diagrammatic work in which lines, numbers, simple human and animal figures, written text and planes of colour are all shown in different combinations. All these elements and the way in which they are interrelated are significant. The circle represents unity, harmony and completeness. In many cases it is divided into two and in this way symbolizes the unification of opposites often found in philosophy and religion. Heyboer was seeking a balance in pictorial contrasts, but also a balance between the hand and the head, intuition and reason. The Cobra artists felt a spiritual affinity with Heyboer and valued his curious working methods and lifestyle.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Deze ets van de Nederlandse kunstenaar Anton Heyboer is gemaakt met behulp van twee afzonderlijke zinkplaten, die, met een kleine tussenruimte, onder elkaar zijn afgedrukt. In de onderste afdruk zijn de vier elementen uit de titel terug te vinden. Elkaar kruisende lijnen vormen een ruitpatroon. Aan de linkerkant bevinden zich drie gekleurde stroken: zwart, wit en bruinrood. In het midden is een cirkel getrokken. De rechter bovenhoek bevat een vierkante vorm met afgeronde hoeken, waarin je, mede door de tekens die erin gekrast zijn, een gezicht zou kunnen zien. De bovenste afdruk sluit aan de rechterkant aan bij de onderste. Aan de linkerkant springt hij een stukje in. Diverse verticale lijnen uit de onderste plaat lopen door in de bovenste. Beide platen bevatten, naast de genoemde elementen, een aantal tekenachtige inscripties. De ets is gemaakt in zeer grof gepolijst zink. Er zijn talloze krasjes zichtbaar in de ondergrond. 'Heyboer leidt een onconventioneel bestaan. Sinds het begin van de jaren zestig leeft hij met vier of vijf vrouwen en een grote hoeveelheid huisdieren onder primitieve omstandigheden op een stukje grond met een boerenschuur. Zijn warse houding ten aanzien van de in zijn ogen overgereglementeerde westerse maatschappij, is voor een deel te verklaren vanuit zijn voorgeschiedenis. Een gedeelte van zijn jeugd bracht hij door in Indonesië en op Curaçao. In de Tweede Wereldoorlog is hij opgepakt door de Duitsers en slecht behandeld tijdens zijn tewerkstelling in een kamp bij Berlijn. 'Na de oorlog begint Heyboer te tekenen. In de jaren vijftig, na een verblijf in een psychiatrische inrichting, ontwikkelt hij een filosofisch systeem, dat een beeldende vertaling krijgt in zijn werk. Hij maakt diagramachtige werken waarin lijnen, cijfers, eenvoudige mens- en dierfiguren, geschreven tekst en kleurvlakken in wisselende combinaties voorkomen. Al deze elementen, en de manier waarop ze met elkaar in verband staan, hebben hun betekenis. De cirkel staat voor eenheid, harmonie en volledigheid. Dikwijls is hij in tweeën gedeeld en symboliseert zo de in menige filosofie en religie nagestreefde vereniging van tegendelen. Heyboer zoekt evenwicht in beeldende contrasten, maar ook evenwicht tussen hand en hoofd, intuïtie en verstand. De kunstenaars van Cobra zien een geestverwant in Heyboer en waarderen zijn eigenzinnige werk- en levenswijze.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>52 x 40,5 cm 82,5 x 62,5 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Ruiten, stroken, cirkel en gezicht</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">ets op papier</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">etching on paper</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/147"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/147"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C488"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0147.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0147.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>