<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1472"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">acrylverf op doek</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">acrylic on canvas</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 'Participa alla Creazione', Nicola de Maria painted most of the canvas with black paint. The bottom part of the work consists of a band of light blue in which an unpainted area lights up. There is a “hole” in the black part through which a light bluish-green colour becomes visible. The paint has been applied fairly thinly. There is a horizontal brushstroke visible in the blue and bluish- green colour. The black paint has been applied in various directions and here and there drips have run. 'The title of this work (Participate in Creation) invites the viewer to see the image as the time at which the earth was created according to the Judaeo-Christian religion. Light is separated from dark, land from water. Order is created in chaos. The painting is at the same time both simple and complex. The horizontal division evokes associations with a landscape and the light blue and bluish green can be seen as water or air. However, the sky blue colour at the bottom of the painting is also confusing; it looks like the sky but it is in the wrong place. The “hole” in the black part can be seen as light breaking through a dark sky, but because of the colour, the association with water is more obvious. 'Participa alla Creazione' is an obscure example of De Maria’s work. However, the title is representative of his philosophy. He constantly created new worlds himself and invited the viewer to do the same. 'De Maria’s work is generally exuberant and colourful as well as poetic and energetic. It can contain figurative and abstract signs and sometimes also letters or words. It radiates a very positive attitude to life. De Maria described himself as “someone who is writing a poem with fingers full of colour.” He is not a theoretician and does not give any explanations, but shows what he has seen and experienced intensely using images, usually with nature as a starting point. It is as though he creates the world again. In doing so he does not have any preconceived plan, but works on the basis of what he feels. The creative process is clearly visible. Sometimes De Maria allows the paint to flow, sometimes he uses powerful brushstrokes. In 'Participa alla Creazione' the horizontal brushstrokes in the light parts and the strokes in every direction in the black part reinforce the contrast between the two: light and order, versus the darkness of chaos.</dc:description><dc:title>Partecipa alla creazione</dc:title><dc:identifier>1472</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 'Partecipa alla Creazione' beschildert Nicola de Maria het doek voor een groot deel met zwarte verf. Het onderste deel van het werk bestaat uit een lichtblauwe baan waarin een onbeschilderde vlek oplicht. In het zwarte gedeelte zit een 'gat' waardoor een lichte blauwgroene kleur zichtbaar is. De verf is tamelijk dun opgebracht. In het blauw en het blauwgroen is een horizontale penseelstreek zichtbaar. De zwarte verf is in diverse richtingen opgebracht. Hier en daar is er een druppel uitgelopen. 'De titel van dit werk (Neem deel aan de schepping) nodigt uit het beeld te lezen als het moment waarop volgens de joods-christelijke religie de aarde geschapen wordt. Het licht wordt gescheiden van het donker, het land van het water. Er ontstaat orde in de chaos. Het schilderij is eenvoudig en complex tegelijk. De horizontale verdeling roept de associatie met een landschap op. Het lichte blauw en het blauwgroen laten zich lezen als water of lucht. Maar het hemelsblauw onder in het schilderij werkt ook verwarrend: het lijkt een lucht, maar dan op de verkeerde plaats. Het 'gat' in het zwarte deel kan gezien worden als het doorbreken van licht in een donkere lucht, maar door de kleur is de associatie met water meer voor de hand liggend. 'Participa alla Creazione' is een sober werk binnen het oeuvre van De Maria. De titel is echter wel representatief voor zijn levenshouding. Hij schept zelf voortdurend nieuwe werelden en nodigt de kijker uit hetzelfde te doen. 'Het werk van De Maria is over het algemeen uitbundig en kleurrijk. Het is poëtisch en energiek. Het kan figuratieve en abstracte tekens bevatten, soms ook letters of woorden. Het straalt een zeer positieve levenshouding uit. De Maria beschrijft zichzelf als "iemand die een gedicht schrijft met vingers vol kleur". Hij is geen theoreticus, geeft geen uitleg, maar toont met beelden wat hij gezien en intens beleefd heeft, meestal met de natuur als uitgangspunt. Hij schept als het ware de wereld opnieuw. Daarbij gaat hij niet volgens een vooropgezet plan te werk, maar gevoelsmatig. Het maakproces is goed zichtbaar. Soms laat De Maria de verf vloeien, soms zet hij een stevige penseelstreek. In 'Participa alla Creazione' versterken de horizontale verfstreken in de lichte delen en de streken in alle richtingen in het zwarte deel het contrast tussen beide: licht en ordening tegenover duistere chaos.</dc:description><dc:date>1982</dc:date><dcterms:extent>110,3 x 150,5 x 3,3 cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1982</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Nicola de Maria</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1472"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1472.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1472.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1472"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1701"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>