<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/168"><dcterms:created>1938</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this painting Raoal Hynckes depicts various objects with great precision. A copper kettle, a dusty wine bottle, a bulb of garlic, a bunch of salsify, a knife and a piece of rope have been collected together on a stone which is in turn placed on other stones. On the left of the painting, there is a vertical wooden plank with a nail from which a bunch of keys is hanging and there is a smoked mackerel hanging above some vegetables. The painting is composed in various shades of brown and some white and black, and the objects are highlighted against a dark background, casting dark shadows. 'Initially Raoul Hynckes painted Impressionist landscapes until he became involved as a soldier in the battles for Liege during the First World War. In 1914 he fled to the Netherlands. Shortly afterwards he fell into a serious emotional crisis which he only managed to overcome in 1924. He destroyed all his old work and turned away from the Impressionist style of painting which was concerned with representing a transient moment. Hyncke’s new work had a much heavier tone and he mainly painted still lifes in dark colours. The way in which he combined shapes initially revealed the influence of Cubism, but Hynckes did not represent his objects in an abstract way and did not aim for an innovative method of painting. On the contrary, he worked “with the conviction that good paintings are not achieved by reaching for the broom or climbing onto the barricades.” 'Hynckes concentrated on a sophisticated expression of materials. His themes acquired a "vanitas" like character. He referred to death and transience, inter alia, by painting dead animals, eroded stones, skulls, pieces of rope, knives, rusty and dusty objects. However, his paintings are not exclusively about death; they are equally about the life which precedes it. Hynckes seems to bring time and life to a stop. His works from this period are classified as works of magic realism. He depicted everyday objects in a very realistic way, but the cold light of a strong light source, the dark backgrounds and the almost monochrome palette of the painter give the work a heavy, almost mysterious atmosphere. After 1950 he once again started to paint landscapes which were in lighter shades and more colourful – very like his work dating from before 1924.</dc:description><dc:title>Stilleven met koperen ketel</dc:title><dcterms:extent>84,9 x 96,5 x 8,2 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1938</dc:date><dc:identifier>168</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Op dit schilderij beeldt Raoul Hynckes met grote precisie verschillende voorwerpen af. Een koperen ketel, een stoffige wijnfles, een bolletje knoflook, een bosje schorseneren, een mes en een stuk touw zijn bijeengezet op een steen, die weer op andere stenen rust. Links op het schilderij is een verticale houten plank geschilderd, met daarin een spijker waaraan een sleutelbos hangt. Boven de groenten hangt een gerookte makreel. Het schilderij is uit diverse tinten bruin, wat wit en zwart opgebouwd. De voorwerpen lichten op tegen een donkere achtergrond. Ze hebben sterke slagschaduwen. 'Raoul Hynckes schildert aanvankelijk impressionistische landschappen tot hij in de Eerste Wereldoorlog als soldaat betrokken raakt bij de gevechten om Luik. In 1914 vlucht hij naar Nederland. Kort daarna raakt hij in een zware emotionele crisis die hij pas in 1924 weer te boven komt. Hij vernietigt dan al zijn oude werk en keert zich af van de impressionistische manier van schilderen, waarin het erom gaat het vluchtige moment weer te geven. Hynckes' nieuwe werk is veel zwaarder van toon. Hij schildert voornamelijk stillevens in donkere kleuren. De manier waarop hij vormen combineert, verraadt aanvankelijk invloed van het kubisme. Hynckes abstraheert zijn voorwerpen echter niet. Hij streeft niet naar een vernieuwende schilderkunst, integendeel, hij werkt "...in de overtuiging dat goede schilderijen niet tot stand komen door naar de bezem te grijpen of door op de barricades te klimmen." 'Hynckes concentreert zich op een verfijnde stofuitdrukking. Zijn motieven krijgen een vanitasachtig karakter. Hij verwijst hij naar dood en vergankelijkheid via onder meer dode dieren, aangetaste stenen, schedels, stukken touw, messen, verroeste en stoffige voorwerpen. Zijn schilderijen gaan echter niet uitsluitend over de dood; ze gaan evenzeer over het leven dat daaraan vooraf gaat. Hynckes zet de tijd en het leven als het ware stil. Hynckes' werk uit deze periode wordt gerekend tot het magisch realisme. Hij beeldt alledaagse objecten zeer waarheidsgetrouw af, maar het kille licht vanuit een sterke lichtbron, de donkere achtergronden en het bijna monochrome palet van de schilder, geven het werk een beladen, bijna mysterieuze sfeer. Na 1950 gaat hij opnieuw landschappen schilderen die, net als zijn werk van voor 1924, lichter van toon en kleurrijker zijn.</dc:description><dc:creator>Raoul Hynckes</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/168"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0168.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C509"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/168"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0168.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>