<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2215"><dc:identifier>2215</dc:identifier><dc:title>Portret van twee jongens (initiatie/chirurgie)</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">This painting by Tiong Ang shows the heads of two boys, almost in mirror image. The heads are shown diagonally from the side; in the middle there is a large eye painted from the front. Above each eye there is a shape like a sort of lid to cover it. The work consists of three parts: two side panels and a central part which is about twice as broad. On the sides where the different parts touch they are rounded. A thin piece of netting is stretched across each part. This work can also be exhibited in different ways. The side panels can be hung directly next to each other, or separately from each other on two opposite walls. In that case the central panel is left out. The central panel can also be placed diagonally against a wall. In that case the side panels rest against it, concealing the middle part. 'Ang often works with thick panels with rounded edges. He paints a scene on these based on photographic material and then stretches one or more layers of netting over it. The netting makes it difficult to recognize the representation, but at the same time attracts attention. The thickness of the panels and the rounded sides give the work a strong physical presence. In addition, the rounded edges give the work a sensual quality. The scenes shown on Ang’s paintings always run across the different parts, so that it is cut up in a way. In this way Ang refers to mutilation. During a trip in West Africa in 1990 he was fascinated by initiation rituals which were often accompanied by some form of disfigurement. The figures which Ang has painted here are also deformed: they have disfigured ears and eyes. 'Ang asks attention for seeing, not only literal seeing, but above all, inner seeing. The enormous flood of images which overwhelms people on a daily basis through media such as newspapers, magazines and television leads to a deadening of the senses or even immunity with regard to what is happening in the world. Ang wants to provide a counterweight to this. Both the form of his work and the presentation invite the visitor to make room for a while to reflect on seeing and then continue, enriched. This 'Portrait of two boys' also focuses attention on seeing. When all three parts are exhibited together, you can see that the eyes and the covers over the eyes are wide open. If only the side panels are shown, the eyes are missing, but it is precisely this which evokes the desire to see.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit schilderij van Tiong Ang laat twee bijna spiegelbeeldige jongenshoofden zien. De hoofden zijn schuin van opzij weergegeven; in het midden ervan zit een groot, frontaal geschilderd oog. Boven elk oog bevindt zich een vorm die lijkt op een afsluitklep daarvoor. Het werk bestaat uit drie delen: twee zijpanelen en een ongeveer twee maal zo breed middendeel. Aan de kanten waar de delen elkaar raken, zijn ze afgerond. Er is een dunne voile over elk deel gespannen. Dit werk mag ook op andere manieren tentoongesteld worden. De zijdelen kunnen direct tegen elkaar aan gehangen worden, of los van elkaar op twee tegenover elkaar liggende wanden. Het middenpaneel wordt dan weggelaten. Ook kan het middendeel iets schuin tegen een muur geplaatst worden. De zijpanelen rusten daar dan tegen en verbergen het middendeel. 'Ang werkt dikwijls met dikke panelen die afgeronde kanten hebben. Hij schildert daarop een voorstelling, die gebaseerd is op fotomateriaal. Daarover spant hij een of meer lagen voile doek. De voile bemoeilijkt het herkennen van de voorstelling, maar trekt tegelijkertijd juist de aandacht. De dikte van de panelen en de rondingen van de zijkanten zorgen voor een sterk fysieke aanwezigheid van het werk. Daarnaast geven de voiles en de rondingen het werk iets sensueels. De voorstelling op Angs schilderijen loopt altijd door over de verschillende delen. Ze wordt als het ware doorsneden. Ang verwijst hiermee naar verminking. Tijdens een verblijf in West-Afrika in 1990 raakt hij gefascineerd door initiatierituelen. Deze gaan vaak gepaard met een zekere vorm van verminking. De figuren die Ang hier schildert zijn ook misvormd: ze hebben afwijkende ogen en oren. 'Ang vraagt aandacht voor het zien: niet alleen het letterlijke zien, maar vooral ook het innerlijke zien. De grote stroom van beelden die de mens dagelijks over zich uitgestort krijgt via media als kranten, tijdschriften en televisie, leidt tot vervlakking of zelfs immuniteit ten aanzien van wat er in de wereld gebeurd. Ang wil daar een tegenwicht aan bieden. Zowel de vorm van zijn werk als de voorstelling, nodigen de bezoeker uit even pas op de plaats te maken, zich te bezinnen op het zien en daarna verrijkt weer verder te gaan. Ook dit 'Portret van twee jongens' vraagt aandacht voor het zien. Wanneer de delen alledrie getoond worden, zie je dat de ogen en de oogkleppen wijd open staan. Als alleen de zijpanelen zichtbaar zijn, ontbreken de ogen. Maar daardoor wordt juist het verlangen naar het zien opgeroepen.</dc:description><dc:date>1991</dc:date><dcterms:extent>140 x 247 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Tiong Ang</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1991</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">veil, alkyde paint on linen on wood</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">voile, alkydeverf op linnen op hout</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2215"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2215"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2379"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2215.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2215.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>