<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2224"><dc:description xml:lang="en">The Scottish artist Ian Hamilton Finlay printed a vertical blue field onto white paper in this work. The text, EVENING WILL COME THEY WILL SEW THE BLUE SAIL, is shown on the field in white capital letters. Finley is a poet and artist and his prints often consist of a combination of text and image. Sometimes the text requires the most attention, sometimes the image, and sometimes they demand equal attention. The image can be abstract or figurative, purely typographical or illustrative, simple or complex. The text can be poetic or informative, consist of a single word or of a number of sentences. Sometimes there is a direct relationship between the word and the image, but sometimes the word and the image appear to contradict each other, or sometimes you discover the links between the two by making associations. 'Finlay made sculptures as well as prints, which also often include a text. Many of these “poem-objects” can be found in his “philosophical” garden, Little Sparta, which is near Edinburgh. In this garden, which he designed and planted himself, Finlay endeavoured to bring art, philosophy and nature together. All the elements in the garden, such as the plants, ponds, objects and texts, have a specific, often symbolic meaning within the whole and are interrelated. For Finlay, the gardener is the symbol of someone who must do his work in harmony with nature in order to achieve a good result. This also applies for fishermen. Fishermen, boats and shipping are constantly recurring themes in his work. 'In 'Evening/Sail' the text is poetic and the image is simple. The combination of the two provides a wealth of possibilities for associations. The elongated blue field can be related to the words BLUE SAIL. In turn, these refer to boats and fishermen, and therefore to the sea. However, EVENING WILL COME also evokes an image of a darkening sky. The whole text suggests that the fishermen have returned safely and are making their sails. It is a moment of rest and blue is a restful colour. But BLUE also means a melancholy mood, which suits the evening time. In this way the blue field reinforces the words in all sorts of ways.</dc:description><dc:identifier>2224</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">zeefdruk op papier</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1970</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">silkscreen on paper</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De Schotse kunstenaar Ian Hamilton Finlay heeft in dit werk een verticaal blauw vlak op wit papier gedrukt. In dat vlak staat in witte hoofdletters de tekst EVENING WILL COME THEY WILL SEW THE BLUE SAIL. Finlay is dichter en beeldend kunstenaar. Zijn prenten bestaan dikwijls uit een combinatie van tekst en beeld. Soms vraagt de tekst de meeste aandacht, soms het beeld, dan weer komen beide even sterk aan bod . Het beeld kan abstract of figuratief zijn, zuiver typografisch of illustratief, eenvoudig of complex. De tekst kan poëtisch zijn of informatief, uit een enkel woord bestaan of uit een aantal zinnen. Soms is er een directe relatie tussen woord en beeld, soms lijken tekst en beeld elkaar tegen te spreken, soms ontdek je langs een associatieve weg verbanden tussen beide. 'Naast prenten maakt Finlay sculpturen. Ook hierin is dikwijls tekst opgenomen. Veel van deze 'gedicht-objecten' bevinden zich in zijn 'filosofische' tuin Little Sparta, in de buurt van Edinburgh. In deze door hemzelf ontworpen en aangelegde tuin streeft Finlay naar een samengaan van kunst, filosofie en natuur. Alle elementen in de tuin, zoals planten, vijvers, objecten en teksten hebben een specifieke, vaak ook symbolische betekenis binnen het geheel, en staan met elkaar in verband. De tuinman is voor Finlay het symbool voor iemand die zijn werk moet doen in harmonie met de natuur, om tot een goed resultaat te komen. Dit geldt ook voor de visser. Vissers, boten en scheepvaart zijn steeds terugkerende motieven in zijn werk. 'In 'Evening/Sail' is de tekst poëtisch, het beeld eenvoudig. De combinatie van beide biedt een rijkdom aan associatiemogelijkheden. Het langgerekte blauwe vlak kan in verband gebracht worden met de woorden BLUE SAIL. Deze verwijzen weer naar boten en vissers en dus naar de zee. EVENING WILL COME roept echter ook het beeld op van een donker wordende lucht. De gehele tekst suggereert dat de vissers veilig teruggekeerd zijn en hun zeilen maken. Het is een moment van rust. Blauw is een rustgevende kleur. Maar BLUE betekent ook droefgeestig, een stemming die past bij het vallen van de avond. Zo zet het blauwe vlak op allerlei manieren de woorden kracht bij.</dc:description><dc:creator>Ian Hamilton Finlay</dc:creator><dcterms:created>1970</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent>82,9 x 30,5 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Evening/Sail</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2224"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2224"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2388"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2224.JPG"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2224.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>