<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2054"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1992</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">synthetic paint on paper</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">synthetische verf op papier</dc:type><dc:identifier>2054</dc:identifier><dcterms:created>1992</dcterms:created><dc:title>Hijgende kraai</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">Using very thinned black paint, Elly Strik painted a huge crow on a sheet of paper. His beak is open and pointing towards the ground. A light spot on the grey ground, immediately beneath the beak, suggests that this represents the crow’s warm breath. ‘Making the breath of a bird visible was the underlying principle behind these works’, confirms Elly Strik, referring to a series of works depicting birds. She says, ‘The work had to be this big in order to make something so immaterial into something visible and tangible,’ and, ‘The visible breath can activate the viewer, so to speak, and stimulate the recognition of possible new connections.’ It’s all about the contact between the viewer and the crow (its eye is looking at you), the viewer and the work. It’s about the energy enclosed within the work that leaps across to the visitors as they view. This way, the crow becomes more than just a crow. It asks questions or gets the viewers to ask their own questions. ‘To me, the panting crow has always been a form of consciousness that is concerned with an awareness of death; the crow is preheating the ground, as it were,’ says Elly Strik. Because breath simultaneously stands for life and a beginning, the panting crow holds within it a kind of cyclical thinking. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Met sterk verdunde zwarte verf schildert Elly Strik een enorme kraai op een vel papier. Zijn bek is opengesperd en naar de grond gericht. Een lichte vlek op de grijze grond, precies onder de bek, doet vermoeden dat hiermee de warme adem van de kraai verbeeld wordt. “Het zichtbaar maken van de adem van een vogel was het uitgangspunt voor deze werken”, bevestigt Elly Strik, verwijzend naar een serie werken met vogels. Ze zegt: “Om zoiets immaterieels zichtbaar en voelbaar te maken moest het werk wel zo groot worden.” En ook: “De zichtbaar gemaakte adem kan de toeschouwer als het ware activeren en opent mogelijke associaties.” Het gaat om het contact tussen de kijker en de kraai (zijn oog kijkt je aan), de kijker en het werk; om de energie die in het werk besloten ligt en overspringt naar de bezoeker tijdens het kijken. De kraai wordt op die manier meer dan zomaar een kraai. Hij stelt vragen, of laat de kijker zichzelf vragen stellen. “De hijgende kraai is voor mij altijd een vorm van bewustzijn geweest die te maken heeft met een doodsbesef, de kraai is als het ware de grond aan het voorverwarmen”, zegt Elly Strik. Doordat de adem tegelijkertijd staat voor leven en voor een begin, draagt de hijgende kraai een cyclisch denken in zich. '[2020]</dc:description><dcterms:extent>201 x 319,5 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Elly Strik</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2054"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2054-01.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2054"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2054-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2220"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>