<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/177"><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 'Le monde perdu' Asger Jorn places colourful lines and marks next to each other in such a way that they create a few large shapes. A rounded, almost triangular shape in the top part of the painting leans on an elongated shape which goes from the edge of the canvas diagonally to the top of the painting. The shapes evoke associations with living creatures, although these cannot be clearly defined. The dark blue and green in the right corner of the shape at the top continues down and comes back along the left edge of the painting, curving on to the top edge, and the large shapes are surrounded by bright yellow brushstrokes. Within the outlines, Jorn used strongly contrasting colours such as blue and orange, green and red, alternating with light shades, next to each other. The whole work is dominated by rotating and flowing movements. 'At the end of the 1930s there was a group of artists in Denmark who were strongly inspired by Scandinavian mythology, in which nature with its mysterious forces is populated by creatures such as gods, trolls and dwarves. These artists also felt an affinity with their prehistoric past as well as with the surviving folklore. In 1941 they founded the journal entitled “Helhesten”, in which they promoted a direct method of expression through a spontaneous style of painting. The way in which these artists filled their canvases entirely with colour, devoting just as much attention to the figures as the background, expressed their sense of creatures and nature as being inextricably linked. Jorn, who was the only member of this group to feel the need for an international profile, adopted the Helhesten ideas when he became one of the co-founders of Cobra in Paris in 1948. 'The view that an artwork should be a direct expression of feelings and desires was also very influential in the Cobra movement, which included Dutch and Belgian artists as well as Danes. In addition to being inspired by mythology and folk art, the members of Cobra also sought inspiration in children’s drawings, the paintings produced by the mentally ill, and non-western art. Following the dissolution of Cobra in 1951, Jorn remained active as a thinker and as an inspiration for various international groups of artists, including the International Situationists. The relationship between art and society, the notion of art as a means of expression of what is important in a nation always had a central place for Jorn. In 'Le monde perdu' he evoked a menacing atmosphere with the distorted creatures which emerge from the flowing lines and glowing colours. The title confirms this sense of doom.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 'Le monde perdu' plaatst Asger Jorn kleurige lijnen en vlekken zo bij elkaar dat er enkele grote vormen uit ontstaan. Een afgeronde, enigszins driehoekige vorm in het bovenste deel van het schilderij leunt op een langgerekte vorm die linksonder vanaf de rand van het doek schuin naar boven het beeld in gaat. De vormen roepen associaties op met levende wezens, zonder dat die te definiëren zijn. Het donkere blauw en groen in de rechterhoek van de bovenste vorm, loopt door naar beneden, komt terug langs de linkerrand van het schilderij en buigt door naar de bovenrand. De grote vormen worden omringd door felgele penseelstreken. Binnen hun contouren zet Jorn sterk contrasterende kleuren als blauw en oranje, groen en rood, afgewisseld met lichte tinten, naast elkaar. Het geheel wordt gedomineerd door draaiende en vloeiende bewegingen. 'Eind jaren dertig is er in Denemarken een groep kunstenaars die sterk geïnspireerd wordt door de Skandinavische mythologie, waarin de natuur met haar geheimzinnige krachten bevolkt wordt door wezens als goden, trollen en dwergen, Ook voelen deze kunstenaars zich verbonden met hun prehistorische verleden en met nog levende folklore. In 1941 richten zij het tijdschrift Helhesten op. Hierin propageren zij een directe manier van uiten via een spontane schilderwijze. In de manier waarop deze kunstenaars hun doeken helemaal vullen met kleur, waarbij figuren en achtergrond evenveel aandacht krijgen, komt hun gevoel van wezens en natuur als onlosmakelijk geheel tot uitdrukking. Jorn, die als enige van deze groep de behoefte heeft zich internationaal te profileren, neemt het gedachtengoed van Helhesten mee, wanneer hij in 1948 in Parijs medeoprichter van Cobra is. 'Ook binnen de Cobrabeweging, die naast Denen uit Nederlanders en Belgen bestaat, heerst de opvatting dat een kunstwerk een directe uiting van gevoelens en verlangens dient te zijn. Naast mythologie en volkskunst zijn de leden van Cobra geïnspireerd door kindertekeningen, beeldende uitingen van geesteszieken en niet-westerse kunst. Na de ontbinding van Cobra in 1951 blijft Jorn actief als denker en inspirator achter diverse internationale kunstenaarsgroeperingen, waaronder de Internationale Situationisten. De samenhang tussen kunst en maatschappij, het idee van kunst als uitdrukkingsmiddel van wat er onder het volk leeft, staat voor Jorn altijd centraal. In 'Le monde perdu' roept Jorn via de verwrongen wezens die hij laat opdoemen uit de vloeiende lijnen en gloeiende kleuren, een onheilspellende sfeer op. De titel bevestigt dit vermoeden van onheil.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Le monde perdu</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dcterms:extent>117,6 x 90,5 x 3,6 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:creator>Asger Jorn</dc:creator><dc:identifier>177</dc:identifier><dc:date>1960</dc:date><dcterms:created>1960</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/177"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0177.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/177"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0177.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C518"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>