<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1164"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1419"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1164.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1164"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1164.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1164"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">metal, electronic components, plexiglass, transformer</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">The work 'Truisms' by the American artist Jenny Holzer uses an electronic text board, a so-called “light projection”, in which the letters are formed by means of a grid of green lamps. We see the words moving across the bar of light in a vertical or horizontal direction. They form sentences which pass by at different speeds, sometimes flashing. 'Truisms' comprises a few hundred sentences. They are statement of a political, social, philosophical or moralizing nature. Sometimes they are “open doors”; sometimes they provide food for thought. A few examples of these sentences include: HUMOR IS A RELEASE, ANY SURPLUS IS IMMORAL and MORALS ARE FOR LITTLE PEOPLE. 'In the early 1970s Jenny Holzer made abstract paintings. She was aware that these were appreciated by few people and went in search of an art form which appealed to a larger public. She said: “If you want to reach the general public, it’s not the subjects in art which will force them to stop on their way to lunch, they must be subjects from life.” She decided to start working with text because text sends a much more direct message than abstract images. Her work 'Truisms' was exhibited in 1977. She had the sentences comprising this work printed on posters which were then displayed in New York in large quantities. Holzer hoped that passers-by would read what was on the posters and become curious about their origin and significance. In 1982 Holzer started using light projections to spread her series of statements and 'Truisms' was also presented in this form. ''Truisms' can evoke a response of approval, but also lead to outrage or indifference. The statements are not Holzer’s own personal views. When she participated in a study program in New York in 1977, she was given a list of books with “heavy reading matter”. She was aware that what was in these books was important and profound, but it was not easily accessible, and she wanted to translate it into understandable language. Some of the statements or views were contradictory, but together they provided a reflection of reality. Holzer said: “I thought that the whole thing could be a reasonably reliable portrait of the way things are in the world because all these conflicting views exist at the same time.” She used the light projections as a medium because it is a better reflection of her own time than charcoal or another traditional material.</dc:description><dc:creator>Jenny Holzer</dc:creator><dc:date>1983</dc:date><dc:title>Truisms</dc:title><dcterms:extent>16 x 155 x 10,1 cm duur / duration 00:25:00</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1983</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">metaal, elektrische componenten, perspex, transformator</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In het werk 'Truisms' van de Amerikaanse kunstenaar Jenny Holzer wordt gebruik gemaakt van een elektronisch tekstbord, een zogenaamde lichtkrant. De letters worden gevormd door middel van een raster van groene lampjes. We zien de woorden in horizontale of in verticale richting bewegen over de lichtbalk. Ze vormen zinnen die in verschillende snelheden voorbijkomen. Soms knipperen ze. 'Truisms' bestaat uit een paar honderd zinnen. Het zijn uitspraken van politieke, sociale, filosofische of moralistische aard. Soms zijn het 'open deuren', soms geven zij stof tot nadenken. Een paar voorbeelden van zulke zinnen zijn: HUMOR IS A RELEASE (humor is een bevrijding), ANY SURPLUS IS IMMORAL (ieder teveel is immoreel) en MORALS ARE FOR LITTLE PEOPLE (zeden zijn voor kleinzielige mensen). 'Begin jaren zeventig maakt Jenny Holzer abstracte schilderijen. Ze beseft dat deze maar in kleine kring bijval vinden en gaat op zoek naar een vorm van kunst die een groter publiek aanspreekt. Ze zegt: "Als je een algemeen publiek wilt bereiken, dan zijn het niet de onderwerpen uit de kunst die hen zullen dwingen te stoppen op hun weg naar de lunch, het moeten onderwerpen uit het leven zijn". Ze besluit met tekst te gaan werken, omdat tekst een veel directere boodschap uitdraagt dan abstracte beelden. In 1977 verschijnt het werk 'Truisms'. Ze laat de zinnen waaruit dit werk bestaat drukken op posters, die ze vervolgens in grote hoeveelheden ophangt in New York. Holzer hoopt dat passanten gaan lezen wat er op de posters staat en nieuwsgierig worden naar de herkomst en de betekenis ervan. In 1982 gaat Holzer gebruik maken van lichtkranten om haar series uitspraken te verspreiden. Ook 'Truisms' verschijnt dan in deze vorm. 'De 'Truisms' kunnen reacties van bijval oproepen maar ook van verontwaardiging of onverschilligheid. De uitspraken zijn niet de persoonlijke meningen van Holzer. Wanneer ze in 1977 deelneemt aan een studieprogramma in New York krijgt ze een boekenlijst met 'zware kost' uitgereikt. Ze realiseert zich dat wat er in deze boeken staat belangrijk en diepzinnig is, maar moeilijk toegankelijk. Ze wil ze omzetten in begrijpelijke taal. Sommige uitspraken of opvattingen zijn tegenstrijdig, maar samen geven ze een afspiegeling van de werkelijkheid. Holzer zegt: "Ik dacht dat het geheel een redelijk betrouwbaar portret zou kunnen zijn van de manier waarop de dingen zijn in de wereld, omdat al deze tegenstrijdige meningen tegelijkertijd bestaan". Ze gebruikt de lichtkrant als medium omdat dit een betere afspiegeling van de eigen tijd is dan houtskool of een ander traditioneel materiaal.</dc:description><dc:identifier>1164</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>