<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2191"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Jan Vercruysse</dc:creator><dc:date>1994-1995</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">“Mijn tuinen zijn niet bedoeld om te versmelten met een landschap. Ze willen zich duidelijk manifesteren en je mag ze gerust ervaren als iets kunstmatigs. Als kunstenaar moet ik met niets en niemand rekening houden.” Aldus Vercruysse over zijn 'Labyrint &amp; Pleasure Gardens'. Hoewel hij zegt met niemand rekening te houden, zijn de voorstellen bedoeld voor tuinen in de openbare ruimte. Twee ervan zijn gerealiseerd. De plaats van kunst en kunstenaar in de samenleving, een belangrijk thema voor Vercruysse, krijgt in zijn tuinen letterlijk vorm. Hij cultiveert het landschap om een statement te maken over zijn identiteit als kunstenaar.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>(8x) 71,5 x 54,3 x 2,5 cm ( incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Labyrinth &amp; Pleasure Gardens</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">offset on paper</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">offset op papier</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">‘My gardens are not meant to merge with a landscape. They want to exhibit themselves plainly and you are allowed to experience them as artificial. Being an artist, I don’t have to consider anyone or anything.’ Speaking about the thinking behind his Labyrinth &amp; Pleasure Gardens, Jan Vercruysse claims he doesn’t need to consider anyone – despite the works being proposals for public gardens, two of which have been realized. The place of art and the artist in society is an important theme for Vercruysse, which quite literally takes shape in his gardens. Vercruysse cultivates landscapes to make statements about his identity as an artist.</dc:description><dc:identifier>2191</dc:identifier><dcterms:created>1994-1995</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2191"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2355"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2191-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2191-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2191"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>