<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2021"><dcterms:extent>169,1 x 197,8 x 6 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Zonder titel</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">inkt op papier</dc:type><dc:date>1976</dc:date><dc:identifier>2021</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">This ink drawing is made up of short strokes in different directions. Spatial shapes appear to be formed where the strokes intersect. Slightly to the right of centre you might spot the shape of a house. 'This early work by René Daniëls is associated with formal, fundamental art, where the emphasis is on the process of drawing or painting. Here, the artist examines the workings of expressive devices such as line, direction, rhythm and material, often in series. An explanation or deeper meaning is irrelevant. In his work Daniëls plays around with ideas about abstraction and recognizability, shape and meaning. His work literally and figuratively lacks sufficient linearity for it to be categorized as fundamental art. Rather than being subject to a rigid system, the brush strokes provide scope for associations in all directions. During his academy days (1972-1976) Daniëls had already showed an interest in artists who considered the subject to be important. After his graduation, figuration would play an increasingly significant part in his work. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Deze inkttekening is opgebouwd uit korte strepen in verschillende richtingen. Waar ze elkaar kruisen lijken er ruimtelijke vormen te ontstaan. Iets rechts boven het midden zou je de vorm van een huisje kunnen herkennen. 'Dit vroege werk van René Daniëls is verwant aan de formele, zogeheten fundamentele kunst waarin het accent ligt op het proces van het tekenen of schilderen. Daarin worden beeldmiddelen als lijn, richting, ritmiek en materiaal, dikwijls in series, door de kunstenaar onderzocht op hun werking. Een uitleg of diepere betekenis is niet relevant. Daniëls speelt in zijn werk met ideeën over abstractie en herkenbaarheid, over vorm en betekenis. Zijn werk is letterlijk en figuurlijk niet rechtlijnig genoeg om te horen bij de fundamentele kunst. De streepjes zijn niet onderworpen aan een strak systeem, maar bieden ruimte voor associaties in allerlei richtingen. Daniëls is in zijn academietijd (1972-1976) al geïnteresseerd in kunstenaars voor wie het onderwerp wèl belangrijk is. Na zijn afstuderen speelt figuratie een steeds grotere rol in zijn werk. '[2020]</dc:description><dcterms:created>1976</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">ink on paper</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>René Daniëls</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2021"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2021.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2192"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2021"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2021.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>