<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2131"><dc:type xml:lang="en">cement, wood, alabaster, iron</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">cement, hout, albast, ijzer</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Untitled' by the Spanish artist Cristina Iglesias consists of three walls made of wood covered in cement. They are linked by an iron frame containing thin plates of alabaster. The walls are not parallel, but are placed at different angles to each other. The alabaster roof consists of various segments which are all a different shape. In some places there is an opening between two segments, but in most places they join together forming a curved cover. The work should be placed with the middle wall against the wall of the exhibition space. 'Cristina Iglesias’s works are somewhere between sculpture and architecture. In terms of size, slightly taller than a human figure, they correspond most to sculpture, but in terms of form they are similar to a building or part of a building. Usually they are connected to a wall in the exhibition space. Sometimes it is not clear whether you can enter them or not. The materials used are very diverse. In Untitled, Iglesias combined simple and cheap materials such as cement and wood with a sophisticated and expensive material, alabaster. The alabaster plates are so thin that they let the light through and therefore influence the light and colour of the space they are covering. Therefore it is not only the material that is used that plays a role in the experience of this work; Iglesias also allows the viewer to experience immaterial things such as light and space. 'The space in the work does not have precise borders because the walls are not parallel and because the cover does not join the walls precisely. You could imagine passing around and through the work in different ways, resulting in new spatial experiences and views every time. It is a space within a space, separate and still connected. Untitled is a hiding place and a starting point at the same time; both for a physical experience, but also for a mental one. The vertical and structural character of the work and the translucence of the alabaster cover produce an effect of light and space which is reminiscent of a chapel, a place for contemplation and meditation. This is also how Iglesias’s sculpture works. It provides a concrete if not sharply defined place, inviting the viewer to experience a new perspective every time; a place for experience and reflection, or as one critic once described it: “A home to be in.”</dc:description><dc:creator>Cristina Iglesias</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Untitled' van de Spaanse kunstenaar Cristina Iglesias bestaat uit drie wanden van met cement bekleed hout. Ze zijn met elkaar verbonden door ijzeren frame, waarin dunne platen albast gevat zijn. De wanden zijn niet evenwijdig; ze staan onder verschillende hoeken t.o.v. elkaar. Het albasten dak bestaat uit diverse segmenten die allemaal verschillend van vorm zijn. Op sommige plaatsen is er een opening tussen twee segmenten, op de meeste plaatsen sluiten ze op elkaar aan. Ze vormen een gebogen overkapping. Het werk dient met de middelste wand tegen een muur van de tentoonstellingsruimte geplaatst te worden. 'De beelden van Cristina Iglesias nemen een positie in tussen sculptuur en architectuur. Qua maat, iets meer dan manshoog, komen ze het meest overeen met sculptuur, qua vorm hebben ze overeenkomst met een gebouw of een onderdeel daarvan. Meestal zijn ze verbonden met een muur van de expositieruimte. Soms is het niet duidelijk of je ze mag betreden of niet. Het gebruikte materiaal is heel divers. In 'Untitled' combineert Iglesias eenvoudige en goedkope materialen als cement en hout met het verfijnde en dure materiaal albast. De albasten platen zijn zo dun dat ze licht doorlaten en daardoor het licht en de kleur van de ruimte die ze overkappen beïnvloeden. Niet alleen het gebruikte materiaal speelt dus een rol bij de ervaring van dit werk; Iglesias maakt onstoffelijke dingen als licht en ruimte ook ervaarbaar. 'De ruimte binnen het werk is niet precies af te bakenen omdat de wanden niet parallel zijn en omdat de overkapping niet precies aansluit op de wanden. Je kunt je voorstellen dat je op diverse manieren om en door het werk heen kunt gaan. Je krijgt dan telkens nieuwe ruimte-ervaringen en doorzichten. Het is een ruimte in een ruimte, apart en toch verbonden. 'Untitled' is een schuilplaats en een vertrekpunt tegelijk; voor een fysieke ervaring, maar ook voor een mentale. Het verticale en gebouwachtige karakter van het werk en het doorschijnende van de albasten overkapping geven een licht- en ruimtewerking die doet denken aan een kapel: een plaats voor contemplatie en meditatie. Zo functioneert ook Iglesias' beeld. Het biedt een concrete, zij het niet scherp afgebakende plek die uitnodigt telkens een nieuw gezichtspunt in te nemen; een plek voor ervaring en bezinning of, zoals een criticus het eens noemde, een 'woning voor het zijn'.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>2131</dc:identifier><dc:title>Untitled</dc:title><dcterms:extent>240 x 215 x 220 cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1994</dcterms:created><dc:date>1994</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2131"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2131.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2295"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2131.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2131"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>