<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/194"><dc:title>Die Macht der Musik</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">There are two figures in Oskar Kokoschka’s painting 'The Power of Music'. To the left, a woman holding a lilac flower in her hand is blowing on a trumpet-like instrument; to the right, a boy, who is crouching down with his arms over his head, is turning away from her. In the distance there is an animal walking away. The boy is painted in warm colours: red, orange and yellow, while the woman is mainly painted in green and a chilly greenish yellow. The environment consists mainly of dark, predominantly blue fields of colour. The paint is applied thickly with rough brushstrokes in all sorts of directions. 'As a result of his experiences on the front during the First World War and during a turbulent love affair with Alma Mahler between 1912 and 1915 Kokoschka had become physically and psychologically damaged. He expressed his turbulent emotions in 'The Power of Music'. The subject is the conflict between the sexes in which the woman puts a spell on the man just as in Kokoschka’s own personal life, and drives him to despair. At first he called this work 'Weakness and Strength', but when it was finished he changed the title. The way in which Kokoschka designed his work is directly related to the content. The position of the figures reflects his emotions. The boy is hemmed in, in the bottom right corner. The woman’s head is slightly pulled back as though she is withdrawing, but she stretches out her hand with the flower to the boy in an inviting gesture. The animal that is fleeing is a sort of echo of the boy’s withdrawal. 'The colours which Kokoschka used together in groups – warm and sultry for the boy, chilly for the woman, and dark and threatening in the background – directly determine the atmosphere of the painting. They were chosen more to reinforce the narrative than to depict a real situation. This personal choice of colour and the use of paint as a paste are characteristics of Expressionism. After the First World War, Kokoschka settled in Dresden where the group of Expressionist artists, “Die Brücke'”, was founded. Previously he had already seen the work of avant-garde artists such as Kandinsky, Chagall and Nolde in Berlin. Kokoschka developed his own personal style, but was influenced by this innovative art.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:extent>104,5 x 154,3 x 6 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Oskar Kokoschka</dc:creator><dcterms:created>1918</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Op het schilderij 'Die Macht der Musik' van Oskar Kokoschka zijn twee figuren te zien. Links in het beeld blaast een vrouw met een lila bloem in haar hand op een trompetachtig instrument. Rechts keert een jongen, half in elkaar gedoken, met zijn armen langs zijn hoofd, zich van haar af. In de verte zie je een dier weglopen. De jongen is geschilderd in de warme kleuren rood, oranje en geel, de vrouw hoofdzakelijk in groen en een kil groenachtig geel. De omgeving bestaat vooral uit donkere, overwegend blauwe kleurvlekken. De verf is dik aangebracht met grove penseelstreken in allerlei richtingen. 'Door zijn ervaringen aan het front tijdens de Eerste Wereldoorlog en als gevolg van een turbulente liefdesaffaire met Alma Mahler tussen 1912 en 1915, is Kokoschka geestelijk en lichamelijk beschadigd geraakt. In 'Die Macht der Musik' brengt hij zijn heftige gevoelsleven tot uitdrukking. Het thema is de strijd tussen de seksen, waarbij de vrouw, zoals in Kokoschka's persoonlijke leven, de man betovert en tot wanhoop drijft. Eerst noemt hij dit werk 'die Schwachheit und die Stärke', maar wanneer het af is, wijzigt hij de titel. De manier waarop Kokoschka zijn voorstelling vormgeeft, staat in direct verband met de inhoud ervan. De positie van de figuren verraadt zijn emoties. De jongen zit ingeklemd in de rechter benedenhoek. De vrouw neigt met haar hoofd iets naar achteren, alsof ze zich terugtrekt, maar strekt haar hand met de bloem uitnodigend naar de jongen uit. Het vluchtende dier is een soort echo van de terugdeinzende jongen. 'De kleuren, die Kokoschka hier in groepen bij elkaar zet - warm en broeierig voor de jongen, kil voor de vrouw, en donker en dreigend in de achtergrond - zijn direct bepalend voor de sfeer van het schilderij. Ze zijn eerder gekozen om het verhaal kracht bij te zetten, dan om een werkelijke situatie af te beelden. Deze persoonlijke kleurkeuze en het pasteuze verfgebruik zijn kenmerken van het expressionisme. Na de Eerste Wereldoorlog vestigt Kokoschka zich in Dresden, waar de expressionistische kunstenaarsgroep 'Die Brücke' gevestigd is. Eerder al heeft hij in Berlijn het werk van avant-garde kunstenaars als Kandinsky, Chagall en Nolde gezien. Beinvloed door deze vernieuwende kunst, ontwikkelt Kokoschka zijn persoonlijke stijl.</dc:description><dc:date>1918</dc:date><dc:identifier>194</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/194"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0194-01.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C535"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0194-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/194"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>