<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2147"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">For '10 ms-1' a large screen is set up in a metal frame, slightly leaning backwards, inside a dark exhibition gallery. A black and white film is projected onto the screen with the following content. A man dressed only in his underpants stands a few steps away from a hospital bed in a bare room. His head and shoulders are not in the picture, and the bed is only partly visible. The man takes a few steps back, then forward, to and fro, and then falls down. He is out of the picture for a moment, but then the camera shows the whole of him. He has caught himself with his hands and rolls onto his back. He sits down and makes many attempts to stand up, but in vain. At the end he is lying down on his back again, slightly moving his head, but then remains lying still. The film comes to an end but immediately starts again. The images are rather jumpy and the film is of poor quality. 'For this work Gordon used film which was made at the beginning of the twentieth century for medical purposes. In this case it concerns observing a man who is unable to remain standing, not because of a physical disorder, but as a result of psychological trauma. Gordon transposed the original film onto the video, slowing it down. As a result of the larger than life-size projection and the way it is set up in the space so that the screen can be seen from both sides, the viewer is confronted with the struggling man in a very insistent way. The viewer can only watch, impotently. With regard to these sorts of works, Gordon said: “I hoped that people would be surprised about being confronted with this sort of material and that it would be presented in such a way that they would start thinking about a whole series of questions.” Exactly which questions these might be depends on the interests and sensibilities of the viewer. 'With the title '10 ms-1' Gordon was referring to the laws of the British physicist Isaac Newton, who made discoveries in the field of forces in relation to speed and moment. This work by Gordon is about physical forces. However, physical forces are subordinate here to psychological forces. Therefore Gordon was referring to the relative nature of these forces. He was intrigued by the question of which mechanisms direct consciousness. In general it was his intention to destabilize the viewer and confront him with things that are recognizable and with which he can identify, but which also have something unexpected and are therefore often uncomfortable.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>duur / duration 00:10:37 (schermgrootte / screen size) 229 x 304,5 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">16 mm film overgezet op video (PAL, zwart-wit, zonder geluid, loop); metalen scherm &amp; stang</dc:type><dc:creator>Douglas Gordon</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Voor '10 ms-1' staat er een groot scherm in een metalen frame vrij opgesteld in een verduisterde expositieruimte. Het helt iets achterover. Op het scherm wordt een zwartwitfilmpje geprojecteerd met het volgende verloop. Een man, slechts gekleed in onderbroek, staat op enkele stappen afstand van een ziekenhuisbed in een kale ruimte. Zijn hoofd en schouders zijn niet in beeld; het bed slechts gedeeltelijk. De man doet enkele passen achteruit, vervolgens vooruit, heen en weer, en valt. Even is hij buiten beeld. Vervolgens laat de camera hem helemaal zien. Hij heeft zich opgevangen met zijn handen en rolt door op zijn rug. Hij gaat zitten en doet vele tevergeefse pogingen op te staan. Uiteindelijk ligt hij weer op zijn rug, beweegt nog wat met zijn hoofd maar blijft dan stil liggen. Het filmpje is afgelopen, maar begint direct opnieuw. Het beeld is wat schokkerig en het filmpje is van slechte kwaliteit. 'Voor dit werk gebruikt Gordon filmmateriaal dat in het begin van de 20e eeuw is gemaakt voor medische doeleinden. Het betreft in dit geval de observatie van een man die niet vanwege een fysieke stoornis, maar vanwege een psychisch trauma niet in staat is te blijven staan. Gordon zet het originele filmpje vertraagd over op video. Door de meer dan levensgrote projectie en de opstelling daarvan vrij in de ruimte, waardoor het scherm van beide kanten te bekijken is, wordt de toeschouwer zeer indringend met de worstelende man geconfronteerd. De kijker kan slechts machteloos toezien. Over dit soort werken zegt Gordon: "Ik hoopte dat mensen verbaasd zouden zijn met dit soort materiaal geconfronteerd te worden en dat het zo getoond zou worden dat ze na zouden gaan denken over een lange reeks van vragen." Welke vragen dit precies zijn, hangt af van de interesses en gevoeligheid van de kijker. 'Met de titel '10 ms-1' refereert Gordon aan de wetten van de Britse natuurkundige Isaac Newton, die ontdekkingen deed op het gebied van krachten in relatie tot snelheid en moment. Dit werk van Gordon gaat over krachten. Fysische en fysieke krachten zijn hier echter ondergeschikt aan psychische. Gordon wijst dus op de betrekkelijkheid hiervan. Hij is gegrepen door de vraag welke mechanismen het bewustzijn sturen. In het algemeen is het zijn bedoeling de kijker te destabiliseren; hem te confronteren met dingen die herkenbaar zijn, waarin hij zich kan inleven, maar die tevens iets onverwachts hebben en daardoor dikwijls oncomfortabel zijn.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1994</dcterms:created><dc:date>1994</dc:date><dc:identifier>2147</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">16 mm film transferred to video (PAL, black-and-white, silent, loop), duration 10:37 min.; front surface screen, metal frame and pole</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:title>10 ms-1</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2147"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2311"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2147.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2147"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2147.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>