<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/146"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 216.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 169.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1632</dcterms:created><dc:title xml:lang="nl">De anatomische les van Dr Nicolaes Tulp</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">アムステルダムの外科医たちの肖像画という重要な制作依頼を受けたとき、レンブラントはまだ25歳でした。この肖像画は1632年の1月、ニコラース・テュルプ博士の解剖学講義が開かれたのを機に注文されました。 レンブラントは、モデルの外科医たちを動きのあるポーズでとらえました。絵の中の医者たちは、それぞれ違う方向を見ています。明暗の強烈なコントラストが、この場面にさらなる躍動感を与えています。若かりしレンブラントは、すでにこの集団肖像画において、驚くべき絵画技術と、生き生きした人物を描く才能をあますところなく見せつけています。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Rembrandt aveva appena 25 anni quando gli fu chiesto di ritrarre i chirurghi di Amsterdam. Il ritratto fu commissionato per la lezione di anatomia data dal Dottor Nicolaes Tulp nel gennaio 1632. Rembrandt ritrasse i chirurghi in azione, mentre erano tutti intenti a osservare cose diverse. Un ulteriore dinamismo viene dato alla scena da forti chiaroscuri. In questo ritratto di gruppo, il giovane artista dimostrò la sua tecnica leggendaria e il suo grande talento per la realizzazione di ritratti realistici.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Когда Рембрандту предложили написать групповой портрет амстердамских хирургов, ему было всего 25 лет. Этот портрет был заказан ему в январе 1632 г. доктором Николасом Тульпом, проводившим урок анатомии. Рембрандт пишет хирургов в движении, все они смотрят в разные точки. Резкий контраст света и тени придает этой сцене еще большую динамику. На этом групповом портрете молодой тогда еще художник демонстрирует свою легендарную технику и величайший талант создания портретов, герои которых выглядят точно, как в жизни.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Mit fünfundzwanzig Jahren erhielt Rembrandt den bedeutenden Auftrag, die Amsterdamer Chirurgen zu porträtieren. Vorlage war die Anatomiestunde des Dr. Nicolaes Tulp im Januar 1632. Rembrandt hielt die Chirurgen bei ihrem Tun fest – jeder sieht sich etwas anderes an. Durch den großen Hell-Dunkel-Kontrast bekommt die Darstellung zusätzliche Dynamik. Der junge Maler bewies mit diesem lebensechten Gruppenbild bereits sein grandioses technisches Können und sein enormes Talent als Porträtist.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">当伦勃特被委托创作阿姆斯特丹外科医生的肖像画时，他才25岁。画的内容是尼古拉斯·蒂尔普医生在1632年1月份所上的一堂解剖课。 伦勃朗所画的外科医生是带有动作的，他们都在看不同的东西。明暗之间的强烈对比给这幅画增添了动感。在这幅群像中，年轻的画家展示了他卓越的技巧以及他绘画高逼真肖像的天赋。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ko-kr">Rembrandt was only twenty-five when he was asked to paint the portraits of the Amsterdam surgeons. The portrait was commissioned for the anatomy lesson given by Dr Nicolaes Tulp in January 1632. Rembrandt portrayed the surgeons in action, and they are all looking at different things. Dynamism is added to the scene by the great contrasts between light and dark. In this group portrait, the young painter displayed his legendary technique and his great talent for painting lifelike portraits.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Rembrandt n’a que 25 ans lorsqu’on lui demande de peindre le portrait des chirurgiens d’Amsterdam. Ce tableau est commandé dans le cadre de la leçon d’anatomie du Docteur Nicolaes Tulp en janvier 1632. Rembrandt représente les chirurgiens à l’ouvrage, chacun observant un élément différent. Le dynamisme est apporté par les vifs contrastes entre la lumière et l’obscurité. Dans ce portrait de groupe, le jeune peintre fait montre de sa technique légendaire et de son immense talent pour peindre des portraits vivants.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">Rembrandt was only twenty-five when he was asked to paint the portraits of the Amsterdam surgeons. The painting was commissioned for the anatomy lesson given by Dr Nicolaes Tulp in January 1632. Rembrandt portrayed the surgeons in action, and they are all looking at different things. Dynamism is added to the scene by the great contrasts between light and dark. In this group portrait, the young painter displayed his legendary technique and his great talent for painting lifelike portraits.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 216.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Rembrandt tinha somente 25 anos quando lhe foi solicitado pintar os retratos dos cirurgiões de Amsterdã. O quadro foi comissionado para a aula de anatomia do Dr. Nicolaes Tulp, em janeiro de 1632. Rembrandt retratou os cirurgiões em ação e cada um deles observa algo diferente. O forte contrate entre luz e sombra adiciona dinamismo à obra. Neste retrato em grupo, o jovem pintor exibiu sua técnica legendária e seu grande talento para pintar retratos quase reais.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Rembrandt tenía sólo veinticinco años cuando recibió el encargo de pintar a los cirujanos de Ámsterdam. El retrato en cuestión representa la lección de anatomía impartida por el doctor Nicolaes Tulp en enero de 1632. Rembrandt retrató a los cirujanos en plena acción, por lo todos miran a puntos distintos de la escena. El dinamismo de la escena se ve acentuado por el marcado contraste entre luz y sombra. En este retrato de grupo, el joven pintor hace gala de su proverbial técnica y su gran talento para el retrato realista.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 169.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>146</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Rembrandt van Rijn</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1632</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Rembrandt was pas 25, toen hij de belangrijke opdracht kreeg om de Amsterdamse chirurgijns te portretteren. Het portret werd besteld naar aanleiding van de anatomische les die Dr Nicolaes Tulp in januari 1632 gaf. Rembrandt beeldde de chirurgijns in actie af – ze kijken allemaal ergens anders naar. De voorstelling krijgt extra dynamiek door het grote licht-donkercontrast. De jonge schilder toonde met dit groepsportret zijn fabelachtige schildertechniek en zijn grote talent om levendige portretten te schilderen.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/146"><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/146"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>