<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/239"><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Portret van Peeter Stevens (c.1590-1668)</dc:title><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 99.4 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 99.4 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">En 1627 un comerciante de telas de Amberes llamado Peeter Stevens encargó su retrato a Anthony van Dyck. Un año más tarde, cuando se casó, encargó a Van Dyck que pintara también a su esposa. Anna fue colocada a la izquierda para evitar que Stevens le diera la espalda, a pesar de que la convención establecida para los retratos de pareja era que el hombre colgara a la izquierda y la mujer a la derecha. Después de Rubens, Van Dyck fue el retratista más importante de su época. Parte de su popularidad se debió a su habilidad para representar siempre a sus clientes algo más favorecidos y elegantes de lo que eran en realidad.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Nel 1627, Peeter Stevens, un mercante di tessuti di Anversa, si fece ritrarre da Antoon van Dyck. Quando Stevens si sposò, un anno dopo, chiese a Van Dyck di ritrarre anche la moglie Anna. Anna fu posizionata sulla sinistra, in modo da permettere a Stevens di non darle le spalle. In realtà, le consuetudini dell’epoca volevano che fosse l’uomo a essere posizionato a sinistra, mentre la donna andava sulla destra. Dopo Rubens, Van Dyck fu il ritrattista più importante del suo tempo. La sua popolarità era dovuta alla sua capacità di rendere i clienti più attraenti ed eleganti di quanto non fossero in realtà.</dc:description><dc:date>1627</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">En 1627, Antoine van Dyck peint le portrait du marchand de tissus anversois, Peeter Stevens. Et lorsqu’un an plus tard, celui-ci se marie, il passe commande au peintre d’un portrait de sa femme Anne. Celle-ci est placée sur la gauche pour que Stevens ne lui tourne pas le dos. Car, normalement, selon la coutume, l’homme devait être placé à gauche et la femme à droite. Van Dyck était le portraitiste le plus important de son époque, après Rubens. Il était très apprécié, car il représentait ses commanditaires un peu plus beaux et plus élégants qu’ils ne l’étaient en réalité.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 112.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Anthony van Dyck</dc:creator><edm:isRelatedTo>https://collectienederland.nl/page/aggregation/mauritshuis/240</edm:isRelatedTo><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">1627 ließ der Antwerpener Tuchhändler Peeter Stevens sich von Anthony van Dyck porträtieren. Als Stevens ein Jahr später heiratete, beauftragte er van Dyck auch mit dem Porträt seiner Ehefrau Anna. Obwohl es damals bei Hochzeitsporträts die Regel war, dass der Ehemann links und die Frau rechts hing, bekam Annas Bildnis ausnahmsweise links seinen Platz, damit Stevens ihr nicht den Rücken zukehrte. Nach Rubens war van Dyck der bedeutendste Porträtmaler seiner Zeit. Er war beliebt, weil er die Auftraggeber ein wenig schöner und eleganter darstellte, als sie in Wirklichkeit waren.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">在1627年，安特卫普的布商彼特·史蒂文斯委托安东尼·凡·代克为他画肖像。当史蒂文斯一年以后结婚时，他又委托凡·代克为他的妻子安娜画肖像。安娜的肖像挂在左边，这样史蒂文斯就不用背对着她。但事实上，一般来说男人的肖像应该挂在左边，女人的在右边。 凡·代克是他那个时代除鲁本斯以外最著名的画家。他的出名是因为他可以将他的买家画得比实际看起来更加美丽和优雅一些。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Торговец тканями из Антверпена Петер Стевенс заказал Антонису Ван Дейку этот портрет в 1627 году. Год спустя, когда Стевенс женился, он заказал Ван Дейку и портрет своей жены Анны. Портрет Анны был помещен слева, чтобы Стевенс не был повернут к ней спиной. Но обычно портрет мужа было принято вывешивать слева, а портрет жены - справа. Антонис Ван Дейк был самым известным после Рубенса портретистом своего времени. Его популярность объяснялась тем, что герои его портретов выглядели чуть лучше и чуть элегантнее, чем в жизни.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 1627 liet de Antwerpse lakenkoopman Peeter Stevens zich portretteren door Anthony van Dyck. Toen Stevens een jaar later trouwde, gaf hij Van Dyck de opdracht om ook zijn vrouw Anna te schilderen. Anna kwam links, zodat Steevens niet met zijn rug naar haar toe zou staan. Maar eigenlijk schreven de regels van het huwelijksportret voor dat de man links en de vrouw rechts hing. Van Dyck was na Rubens dé Vlaamse portrettist van zijn tijd. Hij was geliefd omdat hij zijn opdrachtgevers net iets mooier en eleganter maakte dan ze werkelijk waren.</dc:description><dc:identifier>239</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 112.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1627</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Em 1627, o comerciante de tecidos de Antuérpia, Peeter Stevens, teve seu retrato pintado por Anthony van Dyck. Um ano depois, quando Stevens casou, encomendou a Van Dyck um retrato de sua mulher Anna. Anna foi colocada à esquerda para que Stevens não ficasse de costas para sua esposa. Mas as convenções determinavam que o retrato do homem deveria ser pendurado à esquerda e o da mulher à direita. Depois de Rubens, Van Dyck foi o mais importante retratista de sua época. Ele era popular, pois fazia seus patronos parecerem mais bonitos e elegantes do que realmente eram.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 1627, the Antwerp cloth merchant Peeter Stevens had his portrait painted by Anthony van Dyck. When Stevens got married a year later, he commissioned Van Dyck to paint his wife Anna as well. Anna was placed on the left, so that Stevens did not have his back turned to her. But actually convention dictated that the man should hang on the left and the woman on the right. After Rubens, Van Dyck was the most important portraitist of his day. He was popular because he made his patrons look just a bit more beautiful and elegant than they really were.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">1627年、アントワープの布地を取引する商人ペーター・ステーフェンスは、アンソニー・ヴァン・ダイクに自分の肖像画を依頼しました。その翌年に結婚したステーフェンスは、新妻アンナの肖像もヴァン・ダイクに注文しました。絵の中のステーフェンスが、妻に向かって背を向けることがないように、アンナの肖像画は左に展示されています。本来この配置は逆で、夫婦の肖像画は、男性が左、女性を右に飾るのが決まりでした。 ヴァン・ダイクは、同時代ではルーベンスに次ぐ重要なフランドルの肖像画家でした。彼は、発注者を実物よりも幾分か美しく上品に描いたため好評を得ました。</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/239"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/239"/><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0239_repro/1000</edm:object><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0239_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>