<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/17"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 193.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Het godenmaal bij de bruiloft van Peleus en Thetis</dc:title><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 164.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Abraham Bloemaert</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">In Bloemaert’s painting of the wedding feast of Peleus and Thetis, the happy couple are nowhere to be seen.The real subject is the moment Eris, the goddess of strife, throws a golden apple inscribed with ‘for the fairest’ down to the table. The supreme ruler Jupiter dares not judge himself and instead asks Paris to hand the apple to either Juno, Minerva or Venus. Paris chooses Venus, with her splendid pale back. His judgement leads to a dramatic end to the feast, and ultimately sparks the Trojan War. William V purchased this painting at an auction at the age of 23. It was one of the last pieces he acquired for his collection, but with it he was adding a painting that brought an enduring word of warning to rulers: look out for judgements like that of Paris, as they will only bring misery.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:date>1638</dc:date><dc:identifier>17</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 164.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1638</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Op Bloemaerts schilderij van het bruiloftsmaal van Peleus en Thetis is het bruidspaar zelf nergens te bekennen. Het eigenlijke onderwerp is het moment dat de godin van de tweedracht, Eris, een gouden appel op tafel gooit. Voor de mooiste godin. Oppergod Jupiter durft er zijn vingers niet aan te branden en geeft de herder Paris opdracht om de appel aan Juno, Minerva of Venus te geven. Paris kiest voor Venus – haar blanke rug is dan ook prachtig. Maar zijn oordeel leidt tot een dramatische afloop van het feest. En tot de Trojaanse Oorlog. Prins Willem V kocht dit schilderij op een veiling toen hij 23 jaar was. Het was een van de laatste stukken die hijaanschafte voor zijn collectie. Maar hij haalde er wel een blijvende vermaning aan bestuurders mee in huis: kijk uit voor beslissingen zoals die van Paris, want daar komt enkel ellende van.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 193.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/17"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/17"/><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0017/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0017/1000</edm:object><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>