<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/276"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/276"/><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0276_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0276_repro/1000</edm:object></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/276"><dcterms:created>1533</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">ラテン語の書き込みにより、この肖像画のモデルが誰なのかが分かります。「ロバート・チーズマン、1533年、48歳」。チーズマンは、イングランド王ヘンリー8世の鷹狩り主任をつとめる貴族でした。これは大変名誉ある官職でした。チーズマンは彼の手にとまっている鷹を優しくなでています。 ドイツの画家ハンス・ホルバインは、イングランドに移住して間もなくこの傑作を制作しました。彼の驚くべき熟達した絵画技術は、チーズマンの鋭いまなざし、光沢のあるサテン生地の袖、そして小さな銅製の鈴といった細部にも明らかです。</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 62.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">The Latin inscription clarifies the identity of this nobleman: Robert Cheseman, 48 years old in 1533. Cheseman was the chief falconer to the English king Henry VIII, an honourable position. He is stroking the bird on his hand with a tender gesture. The German painter Hans Holbein painted this masterpiece shortly after he had settled for good in England. His amazing painting technique is shown to great advantage in the man’s intent gaze, in the shiny satin of his sleeves and in the little brass bell.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">这拉丁文告诉了我们这位贵族的身份：罗伯特奇斯曼，1533年的时候是48岁。奇斯曼是英国国王亨利八世的猎鹰者，这是一个很高贵的职位。他正在用温柔的手势安抚他手上的鹰。 德国画家汉斯·荷尔拜因画这幅时，刚刚在英国定居不久。他卓越的绘画技巧通过画中这个男人专注的凝视、袖口奢华的绸缎和黄铜小钟展现无遗。</dc:description><dc:creator>Hans Holbein the Younger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hans Holbein de Jonge</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">L’inscription latine nous révèle l’identité de ce noble gentilhomme : Robert Cheseman, 48 ans en 1533. Cheseman était le fauconnier du roi d’Angleterre, Henri VIII, une fonction qui était un honneur. Il caresse l’oiseau posé sur sa main d’un geste tendre. Le peintre allemand Hans Holbein peignit ce chef-d’œuvre peu après s’être définitivement établi en Angleterre. Sa merveilleuse technique picturale est particulièrement visible dans le regard attentif de l’homme, dans le satin brillant de ses manches et dans la petite cloche de laiton.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">A inscrição em latim nos informa sobre a identidade deste nobre: Robert Cheseman, 48 anos, em 1533. Cheseman era o falcoeiro-chefe do rei inglês Henrique VIII, uma posição de grande honra. Ele está acariciando o pássaro com delicadeza. O pintor alemão Hans Holbein pintou esta obra de arte assim que se instalou na Inglaterra. Sua impressionante técnica de pintura pode ser fortemente observada no olhar do homem, no brilho do cetim de suas mangas e no pequeno sino de latão.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 58.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 62.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Надпись на латыни говорит нам о том, кто изображен на портрете: Роберт Чизмен, сорока восьми лет, 1533 год. Чизмен занимал должность главного сокольничего при дворе английского короля Генриха VIII. На портрете он бережно касается оперения птицы, сидящей у него на руке. Немецкий художник Ганс Гольбейн написал этот шедевр вскоре после того, как навсегда обосновался в Англии. Его виртуозная техника живописи особенно хорошо проявляется при передаче пристального взгляда мужчины, отливающего блеском атласа рукавов, в изображении маленького медного колокольчика.</dc:description><dc:identifier>276</dc:identifier><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">La inscripción latina nos revela la identidad de este noble: Robert Cheseman, 48 años en 1533. Cheseman era el halconero mayor del rey inglés Enrique VIII, una posición de gran prestigio. Aquí le vemos acariciando con ternura el pájaro que reposa en su mano. El artista alemán Hans Holbein pintó esta obra maestra poco después de haberse trasladado a Inglaterra de manera definitiva. Su extraordinaria técnica pictórica se aprecia especialmente en la intensidad de la mirada del sujeto, en el brillo del satén de sus mangas y en el pequeño cascabel de latón.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 58.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">L’iscrizione latina ci rivela l’identità di questo nobiluomo: Robert Cheseman, 48 anni nel 1533. Cheseman era il capo falconiere del re d’Inghilterra Enrico VIII - un incarico davvero onorevole. Cheseman accarezza in un tenero gesto l’uccello appoggiato sulla sua mano. Il pittore tedesco Hans Holbein dipinse questo capolavoro appena dopo essersi trasferito permanentemente in Inghilterra. La sua incredibile tecnica pittorica viene esaltata nello sguardo assorto dell’uomo, nel lucido raso delle maniche e nella campanellina di ottone.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het Latijnse opschrift maakt duidelijk wie deze edelman is: Robert Cheseman, 48 jaar in 1533. Cheseman was grootvalkenier van de Engelse koning Hendrik VIII, een erefunctie. Met een teder gebaar aait hij de vogel die op zijn hand zit. De Duitse schilder Hans Holbein maakte dit meesterwerk kort nadat hij zich definitief in Engeland vestigde. Zijn verbluffende schildertechniek is goed te zien, bijvoorbeeld in de ingespannen blik van de man, het glanzende satijn van zijn mouwen en in het koperen belletje.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Portret van Robert Cheseman (1485-1547)</dc:title><dc:date>1533</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Die lateinische Inschrift stellt diesen Edelmann vor: Robert Cheseman, 48 Jahre alt, 1533. Cheseman war der Hoffalkenier des englischen Königs Heinrich VIII. – eine ehrenvolle Position. Behutsam berührt er den Vogel auf seiner Hand. Der deutsche Maler Hans Holbein schuf dieses Meisterwerk bald nachdem er sich endgültig in England niederließ. Seine phänomenale Maltechnik zeigt sich im angespannten Blick des Mannes, dem schimmernden Satinstoff der Ärmel und dem Kupferglöckchen.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>