<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/136"><dc:identifier>136</dc:identifier><dc:date>1647</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Das Gemälde ist eins der berühmtesten im Mauritshuis. Der Stier ist so besonders, weil Potter damit etwas ausgesprochen Gewöhnliches im Großformat darstellte – das war bisher nie dagewesen. Und dass er – trotz dieses Formats – den kleinsten Details viel Aufmerksamkeit widmete, wie der Lerche am Himmel, dem Sonnenschein auf der Weide, den Fliegen auf dem Rücken des Tieres und den Schnurrhaaren der Kuh. Damit wurde dieses Bild zum Inbegriff des holländischen Naturalismus.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 235.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Essa é uma das pinturas mais famosas, expostas no Mauritshuis. O que faz O touro tão especial é o fato de que Potter pintou algo tão extraordinário como um touro em tão grandes dimensões – o que nunca havia acontecido. E, apesar de seu enorme tamanho, o pintor preocupou-se com os menores detalhes, como o vôo da cotovia, o brilho do Sol na campina, as moscas nas costas do touro e o bigode da vaca. Isso transformou esta obra num exemplo típico da pintura naturalista holandesa.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">マウリッツハウスで最も有名な絵の一つです。この絵の何が特別かと言うと、牡牛のようなありきたりの主題が大きく描かれていることです。このような試みは、それまで一度もありませんでした。大きな画面にも関わらず、画家は隅々まで細心の注意を払っています。例えば、空を飛ぶヒバリ、草に映える日の光、牡牛の鼻ヒゲや背にたかるハエなどです。そのため、この絵はオランダ自然主義絵画の代表作とみなされています。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit is een van de beroemdste schilderijen van het Mauritshuis. Wat &lt;i&gt;De stier&lt;/i&gt; zo bijzonder maakt, is het feit dat Potter op dit grote formaat zoiets gewoons als een stier weergaf – dat was ongekend. En dat hij – ondanks dat formaat – veel aandacht besteedde aan de kleinste details, zoals de leeuwerik in de lucht, het zonlicht op de wei, de vliegen rond de stierenrug en de snorharen van de koe. Daarmee werd dit schilderij het boegbeeld van de Hollandse naturalistische schilderkunst.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 339 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 235.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">C’est un des tableaux les plus célèbres du Mauritshuis. Ce qui fait la singularité de ce Taureau, c’est que Potter a peint un sujet aussi banal qu’un taureau à une très grande échelle, ce qui n’avait encore jamais été fait. Et malgré ce format, il accorde une très grande attention aux plus petits détails, comme l’alouette dans le ciel, le soleil sur la prairie, les mouches sur le dos du taureau, ainsi que les poils sur le mufle de la vache. C’est ce qui fait de ce tableau un exemple parfait de la peinture naturaliste hollandaise.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Éste es uno de los cuadros más famosos del Mauritshuis. El Toro destaca especialmente por el hecho de que Potter representara a un animal de granja común y corriente a tan gran escala, algo que no se había hecho nunca hasta entonces. A pesar de las grandes dimensiones, el artista puso mucha atención en los detalles, como la alondra en el cielo, el sol sobre la pradera, las moscas en la espalda del toro y los bigotes de la vaca. Todo ello convirtió esta obra en el máximo exponente de la pintura naturalista holandesa.</dc:description><dc:creator>Paulus Potter</dc:creator><dc:title xml:lang="nl">De stier</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">This is one of the most famous paintings in the Mauritshuis. What makes &lt;i&gt;The Bull&lt;/i&gt; so special is the fact that Potter painted something as ordinary as a bull on such a grand scale – which had never been done before. And despite this large size, he paid great attention to the smallest details, such as the lark in the sky, the sunshine on the meadow, the flies on the bull’s back and the cow’s whiskers. This made the painting the epitome of Dutch naturalistic painting.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">这是莫瑞泰斯最著名的绘画之一。《公牛》有什么特别呢？因为波特把像公牛这样普通的东西画成了这么大的规模——这是史无前例的。而且尽管画面的尺寸那么大，他还是非常关注微小的细节，比如天空里的百灵鸟、草坪上的阳光、公牛背部的苍蝇和母牛的腮须。这使得这幅画成为了荷兰自然主义绘画的典范。</dc:description><dcterms:created>1647</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 339 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Questo è uno dei dipinti più celebri del Mauritshuis. A rendere Il Toro così speciale è il fatto che Potter ritrasse un soggetto ordinario come un toro su una scala così grande, un progetto mai tentato prima di allora. Nonostante le enormi dimensioni, l’artista riuscì a prestare particolare attenzione ai minimi dettagli, come l’allodola nel cielo, la luce del sole sul prato, le mosche sulla parte posteriore del toro e i baffi della mucca. Ciò rese il dipinto un simbolo della pittura naturalistica olandese.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Перед нами одна из самых знаменитых картин в Маурицхёйсе. Что поражает в ней больше всего - это то, что в качестве главного персонажа столь огромной по размеру картины у Поттера выступает самый обыкновенный бык. Это было впервые в живописной практике. Но несмотря на размеры полотна, он уделял огромное внимание мельчайшим деталям - жаворонку в небе, солнечным бликам на лугу, мухам, облепившим спину быка, волоскам на теле коровы. Все это делает это произведение лучшим образцом натуралистического направления в голландской живописи.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/136"><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/136"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>