<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/605"><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0605_repro/1000</edm:object><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0605_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/605"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/605"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 33.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Un chardonneret est posé sur sa mangeoire, enchainé par la patte. Les chardonnerets étaient des oiseaux de compagnie très populaires, car on pouvait leur apprendre des tours, comme puiser l’eau d’un bol avec un petit seau. C’est l’une des rares œuvres que nous connaissions de Fabritius. Il a peint ce chardonneret avec des coups de pinceaux tout à fait visibles. Pour les ailes, il a appliqué une épaisse couche de jaune, qu’il a ensuite grattée avec le manche de son pinceau.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1654</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Un jilguero reposa sobre su comedero, al que está encadenado por una pata. Los jilgueros eran muy populares como animales domésticos y eran capaces de aprender trucos como, por ejemplo, sacar agua de un cuenco con un cubo en miniatura. Ésta es una de las pocas obras que se conocen de Fabritius. Pintó el jilguero con pinceladas claramente visibles. En el ala aplicó pintura amarilla espesa, que luego raspó con el mango del pincel.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Um pintassilgo está em seu comedor, preso pelo pé. Os pintassilgos eram animais de estimação populares, pois aprendiam truques como tirar água de uma tigela com um baldinho. Este é um dos poucos trabalhos conhecidos de Fabritius. Ele pintou o pintassilgo com pinceladas claramente visíveis. Ilustrou a asa com uma grossa camada de tinta amarela que raspou com o cabo de seu pincel.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">金翅雀正坐在它的喂食器上，腿上被锁着。金翅雀是非常受欢迎的宠物，因为他们可以学会一些小把戏，比如用一个小水桶从碗中取水喝。 这是我们了解到的法布里修斯为数不多的作品之一。他画这个金翅雀用的是非常清晰可见的笔触。他用很厚的黄色颜料画翅膀，用画笔的手把将其随意抹开。</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Un cardellino siede sulla sua mangiatoria, attaccato con una catena alla zampetta. I cardellini erano animali domestici molto popolari, in quanto erano in grado di imparare piccoli trucchi, come prelevare acqua da un recipiente con un secchietto. Questo è uno dei pochi lavori di Fabritius di cui siamo a conoscenza. L’artista dipinse il cardellino con pennellate chiaramente visibili, tracciando l’ala con una spessa pittura gialla, che poi strofinò con il manico del pennello.</dc:description><dc:date>1654</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Een distelvink zit, met een ketting aan zijn pootje, op zijn voederbakje. Distelvinken waren populair als huisdier, omdat je ze kon leren zelf met een miniatuuremmertje water uit een bakje putten. Vandaar dat ze puttertjes worden genoemd. Dit is een van de weinige werken van Fabritius, die bekend zijn. Hij schilderde het puttertje met duidelijk zichtbare penseelstreken. De vleugel gaf hij aan met dikke gele verf, waar hij met de achterkant van zijn penseel een kras in zette.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">ゴシキヒワが、えさ箱に足を鎖でつながれています。この鳥は当時人気のあるペットでした。水入れから小さなバケツで水をくみ出すといった芸当を覚えることができたからです。 この絵は、現存する数少ないファブリティウスの作品の一つです。鳥は筆跡を残したままで仕上げられています。彼は翼を表現するために、まず黄色い絵具を分厚く塗り、それから筆の柄で乾いていない絵具を引っ掻く技法を用いました。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="en">A goldfinch is sitting on its feeder, chained by its foot. Goldfinches were popular pets, as they could be taught tricks like drawing water from a bowl with a miniature bucket. This is one of the few works we know by Fabritius. He painted the goldfinch with clearly visible brushstrokes. He depicted the wing in thick yellow paint, which he scratched with the handle of his brush.</dc:description><dc:identifier>605</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Carel Fabritius</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Ein Goldfink sitzt, am Füßchen angekettet, auf seinem Futterhaus. Goldfinken waren damals beliebte Haustiere, denn sie lernten sogar, mit einem Eimerchen Wasser aus einer Schüssel zu schöpfen. Dies ist eines der wenigen Werke von Carel Fabritius. Mit deutlich erkennbaren Pinselstrichen hielt er den Goldfinken fest. Den Flügel betonte er mit dicker gelber Farbe und einem Kratzer mit dem Pinselstiel.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 22.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 22.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Het puttertje</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Щегол сидит на кормушке, прикованный к ней цепью. Щеглы были очень популярны в те времена, поскольку их можно было обучать разным трюкам, например, черпанию воды из миски крошечным ведерком. Это - одна из немногих известных нам работ Фабрициуса. Он изображает щегла хорошо видными мазками. Художник пишет крыло птицы толстым слоем желтой краски, а затем процарапывает его рукояткой кисти.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 33.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>