<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/256"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 122.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1645</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 151 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>256</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Daniel Seghers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Willeboirts Bosschaert</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">The Antwerp painter Daniël Seghers often worked with other artists. In this case, he asked Thomas Willeboirts Bosschaert to paint the statue of the Virgin Mary, while he did the stone frame and the flowers himself. Besides being a flower painter, Seghers was also a Jesuit. This large painting was a gift from his order to the Protestant stadholder Frederik Hendrik, Prince of Orange and his wife Amalia van Solms, which explains the oranges and the orange blossom. As a token of the stadtholder’s appreciation, Seghers received a gold rosary and two gold crucifixes. The painting was hung above the mantelpiece in Huis ten Bosch.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Bloemencartouche met Mariabeeld</dc:title><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 151 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:date>1645</dc:date><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Daniël Seghers</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De Antwerpse schilder Daniël Seghers werkte vaak samen met andere kunstenaars. In dit geval liet hij Thomas Willeboirts Bosschaert het Mariabeeldje schilderen en deed hij de stenen omlijsting en de bloemen zelf. Seghers was niet alleen bloemenschilder maar ook Jezuïet. Dit grote schilderij was een geschenk van zijn orde aan de protestante stadhouder Frederik Hendrik, prins van Oranje en diens vrouw Amalia van Solms – vandaar de oranjebloesem en oranjeappeltjes. Als beloning ontving Seghers een gouden rozenkrans en twee gouden crucifixen. Het schilderij kreeg een bestemming als schoorsteenstuk in Huis ten Bosch.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 122.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/256"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/256"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0256/1000</edm:object><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0256/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>