<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/854"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 70.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dcterms:created>1510 - 1520 </dcterms:created><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 158.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Master of Frankfurt</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en"> This painting is part of the Netherlands Art Property Collection (‘NK collection’): objects that were stolen, seized or purchased during the Nazi regime. After the Second World War they were placed under the administration of the Dutch State. In recent decades, applications for restitution are taken into consideration again and some objects have been returned to the heirs of their rightful owners.   For more information: &lt;a href="https://www.mauritshuis.nl/en/our-collection/restoration-and-research/provenance-research/"&gt;visit our page on provenance research&lt;/a&gt; </dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 70.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">Catherine of Alexandria was one of the most popular female saints in the late Middle Ages. She is recognisable by her instruments of torture: the sword and wheel that lies broken at her feet. Here Catharine wears a magnificent gown that has been painted in meticulous detail. Equally detailed is the depiction of the surrounding countryside. This painting belongs with the panel hanging to the right. Together they formed the side panels of an altarpiece that is now in Liverpool. The painter is an anonymous Antwerp artist known rather misleadingly as the Master of Frankfurt.</dc:description><dc:creator>Meester van Frankfurt</dc:creator><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 158.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit schilderij behoort tot de Nederlands Kunstbezit collectie (NK-collectie): objecten die tijdens het naziregime zijn geroofd, geconfisqueerd of aangekocht. Na de oorlog kwamen ze onder beheer van de Nederlandse Staat. De afgelopen decennia worden verzoeken tot teruggave weer in behandeling genomen en zijn objecten geretourneerd aan de erven van de rechtmatige eigenaren. Voor meer informatie: &lt;a href="https://www.mauritshuis.nl/herkomstonderzoek"&gt;mauritshuis.nl/herkomstonderzoek&lt;/a&gt;</dc:description><dc:identifier>854</dc:identifier><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:date>1510 - 1520 </dc:date><edm:isRelatedTo>https://collectienederland.nl/page/aggregation/mauritshuis/855</edm:isRelatedTo><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Catharina van Alexandrië was een van de populairste vrouwelijke heiligen in de late Middeleeuwen. Ze is te herkennen aan haar martelwerktuigen: het zwaard en het rad dat gebroken aan haar voeten ligt. Catharina draagt hier een schitterend gewaad dat heel minutieus is geschilderd. Maar ook de natuur en het landschap zitten vol details. Het schilderij hoort bij het paneel dat rechts hangt. Het waren de zijluiken van een altaarsuk dat zich nu in Liverpool bevindt. De schilder is een anonieme, Antwerpse kunstenaar die bekend staat onder de misleidende noodnaam Meester van Frankfurt.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:title xml:lang="nl">De heilige Catharina</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/854"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/854"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>