<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/897"><dcterms:created>1520</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en"> This painting is part of the Netherlands Art Property Collection (‘NK collection’): objects that were stolen, seized or purchased during the Nazi regime. After the Second World War they were placed under the administration of the Dutch State. In recent decades, applications for restitution are taken into consideration again and some objects have been returned to the heirs of their rightful owners.   For more information: &lt;a href="https://www.mauritshuis.nl/en/our-collection/restoration-and-research/provenance-research/"&gt;visit our page on provenance research&lt;/a&gt; </dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 97 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 110 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 97 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:date>1520</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">Anne lies in a big four-poster bed with green curtains. She has just given birth to her daughter Mary, who will later become the mother of Jesus. While Anne recovers, two maternity nurses occupy themselves with the child. A midwife is taking a rest from her work at the table. An anonymous German painter copied this panel from a print by Dürer. Not only did he copy the composition, but also the attention to everyday details, such as the still-life on the table.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In een groot hemelbed met groene gordijnen ligt Anna. Ze is zojuist bevallen van haar dochter Maria, de latere moeder van Jezus. Terwijl Anna ligt bij te komen, zijn twee kraamvrouwen in de weer met het kind. Aan tafel zit een vroedvrouw uit te rusten van haar werk. Een onbekende Duitse schilder maakte dit paneel naar een prent van Dürer. Hij nam niet alleen de compositie over, maar ook de aandacht voor alledaagse details, zoals het stilleven op tafel.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 110 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Anonymous (Germany)</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anoniem (Duitsland)</dc:creator><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl"> Dit schilderij behoort tot de Nederlands Kunstbezit collectie (NK-collectie): objecten die tijdens het naziregime zijn geroofd, geconfisqueerd of aangekocht. Na de oorlog kwamen ze onder beheer van de Nederlandse Staat. De afgelopen decennia worden verzoeken tot teruggave weer in behandeling genomen en zijn objecten geretourneerd aan de erven van de rechtmatige eigenaren.  Voor meer informatie: &lt;a href="https://www.mauritshuis.nl/herkomstonderzoek"&gt;mauritshuis.nl/herkomstonderzoek&lt;/a&gt;</dc:description><dc:identifier>897</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:title xml:lang="nl">De geboorte van Maria</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/897"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/897"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>