<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/1118"><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1118"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1118"><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Cet homme semble à son aise : sa veste est ouverte, son col lâche et son chapeau penché vers l’arrière. Sa posture est inhabituelle dans la mesure où les gens, en général, se montrent à leur avantage quand ils posent pour un portrait. Cet homme était peut-être une connaissance de Rembrandt et ce portrait n’était probablement pas une commande formelle. Le portrait est d’une grande virtuosité et Rembrandt savait exactement ce qu’il faisait. A certains endroits il s’est servi de sa spatule, ailleurs il a gratté la peinture encore fraîche avec le manche de son pinceau. C’est de cette façon qu’il évoque les cheveux gris sous les bords du chapeau.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Старик на портрете явно чувствует себя непринужденно - куртка его расстегнута, воротник развязан, а шляпа сдвинута набок. Подобное нечасто увидишь на портретах, поскольку их герои обычно стремились увековечить себя в лучшем виде. По всей вероятности, это был не официальный заказ, а просто портрет хорошего знакомого. Портрет написан с виртуозным мастерством, и Рембрандт точно знал, что делает. Если в одних местах он использует шпатель, то в других процарапывает влажную краску рукояткой кисти. Именно так он изображает волнистые седые волосы старика под полями шляпы.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Deze man zit er op zijn gemak bij: zijn jas open, zijn kraag los, de hoed naar achteren geschoven. Zo’n houding is ongebruikelijk, want op portretten liet men zich juist op zijn best zien. Mogelijk was deze man een bekende van Rembrandt en was het portret geen officiële opdracht. Rembrandt schilderde het portret heel virtuoos – hij wist precies wat hij deed. Op sommige plaatsen gebruikte hij zijn paletmes, elders kraste met de achterkant van zijn penselen in de natte verf. Zo suggereerde hij springerige grijze haren voor de rand van de hoed.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 81.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 81.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 67.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>1118</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Quest’uomo appare a proprio agio, con la giacca aperta, il colletto allentato e il cappello inclinato all’indietro. La sua è una posa inusuale, in quanto coloro che posano per un ritratto di solito vogliono apparire al meglio di se stessi. Forse Rembrandt conosceva personalmente quest’uomo e il ritratto non fu una commissione formale. Il ritratto rivela una grande abilità pittorica e Rembrandt sapeva esattamente ciò che stava facendo. In alcuni punti fece uso della sua spatola, mentre altrove strofinò la pittura non ancora asciutta con il manico del pennello. Questo è il modo in cui riuscì a ritrarre i capelli grigi e ondulati sotto il bordo del cappello.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Portret van een oude man</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Este homem parece estar à vontade: seu casaco está aberto, seu colarinho solto e sua cabeça levemente inclinada para trás. Sua pose não é comum, pois as pessoas procuravam ter sua melhor aparência quando posavam para um retrato. Este homem, talvez, era conhecido de Rembrandt, e o retrato foi executado informalmente. O retrato é muito virtuoso, e Rembrandt sabia exatamente o que estava fazendo. Em alguns lugares usou a faca de sua palheta e, em outros, raspou a tinta úmida com o cabo de seu pincel. Foi assim que ele representou os cabelos grisalhos que escapam da borda do chapéu.</dc:description><dc:creator>Rembrandt van Rijn</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 67.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">This man looks at ease: his jacket open, his collar loosened and his hat tilted back. His pose is unusual, as people normally looked their best when sitting for a portrait. This man may have been an acquaintance of Rembrandt, and the portrait was probably not a formal commission. The portrait is very virtuoso, and Rembrandt knew exactly what he was doing. In some places he used his palette knife, and elsewhere he scratched in the wet paint with the handle of his brush. This is how he suggested the springy grey hairs under the edge of the hat.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Este hombre parece encontrarse a gusto y relajado: lleva la chaqueta abierta, el cuello desabrochado y el sombrero ligeramente ladeado. Se trata de una pose inusual, puesto que todo el mundo quiere mostrar su mejor aspecto cuando posa para un retrato. Es posible que fuera un conocido de Rembrandt y que el retrato no fuera un encargo formal. No obstante, es un retrato de gran virtuosismo en el que Rembrandt sabía muy bien lo que hacía. En algunos lugares ha utilizado la espátula y en otros ha rascado la pintura húmeda con el mango del pincel. Así es como insinúa los cabellos grises que asoman por debajo del sombrero.</dc:description><dc:date>1667</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Dieser Mann hat es sich gemütlich gemacht: mit offener Jacke, gelöstem Kragen und nach hinten geschobenem Hut. Was unüblich ist, denn auf Porträts zeigte man sich eher von seiner besten Seite. Womöglich handelte es sich um einen Bekannten Rembrandts und nicht um ein offizielles Porträt. Rembrandt zeigte sein ganzes Können – er wusste genau, was er tat. An manchen Stellen benutzte er sein Palettmesser, an anderen kratzte er mit dem Pinselstiel in der nassen Farbe. So deutete er auch die widerspenstigen grauen Haare vor dem Hut an.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">絵の男性はくつろいだ様子で腰を下ろしています。上着は開き、襟は緩められ、帽子は斜め後ろにずれています。このような姿勢で描かれた肖像画はまれです。なぜなら、肖像画のモデルは通常、最も見栄えがよい姿を捉えてもらおうとするからです。この男性はレンブラントの知り合いで、正式の注文ではなかったのかもしれません。 レンブラントは、この肖像を巨匠の作にふさわしいできばえに仕上げています。パレットナイフで絵具を塗りつけたり、乾いていない絵具を筆の柄で引っ掻くなど、彼は、どのような技法をどこで用いるべきか知り尽くしていました。帽子の縁の下に見える灰色の髪の毛は、その筆の柄を利用した技法で表現されています。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">这个男人看起来很放松：他的外套是开着的，衣领松了，他头上的帽子倾斜着。他的鼻子有点特别，因为人们一般在画肖像时会表现出最好的状态。这可能是伦勃朗的一个熟人，这幅肖像也可能不是一个正式的委托任务。 这幅肖像画是一幅杰作，伦勃朗非常清楚他在做什么。在有些地方他使用的是调色刀，其他地方他将沾水的颜料用画刷的手柄随意的抹开 。他就是通过这种方式，来展现帽子边缘下面充满弹性的灰发。</dc:description><dcterms:created>1667</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>