<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/818"><dc:description xml:lang="en">Jan Steen’s paintings often have a touch of eroticism. Here, a young woman is looking at us coquettishly while preparing an oyster. Oysters were known as an aphrodisiac, and this girl seems to be offering more than just good food. This small painting is meant to be studied close up. So Steen painted it very precisely and in great detail. Take the silver tray with bread and salt, for example. Or the fashionable jacket with fur and velvet – you can almost stroke it.</dc:description><dc:date>1658 - 1660 </dc:date><dc:identifier>818</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Les tableaux de Jan Steen comportent souvent une touche d’érotisme. Ici, une jeune femme nous regarde avec coquetterie, tout en préparant une huître. Les huîtres étaient connues pour être aphrodisiaques et cette jeune femme semble offrir davantage qu’un excellent mets. Ce petit tableau est fait pour être étudié de près. Steen l’a réalisé avec une grande précision et un sens remarquable du détail. Regardez le plateau d’argent avec le pain et le sel, par exemple, ou le velours et la fourrure de la veste à la mode. On pourrait presque y passer la main.</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">ヤン・ステーンの絵には、エロティックな気配が漂っていることがよくあります。この絵では、若い娘が意味あり気なまなざしをこちらに向けながら、生牡蠣の準備をしています。当時、牡蠣には媚薬の効果があると思われていました。この娘も、おいしいものを食べる以上に何か期待しているようです。 小さなサイズのこの作品は、近くから注意深く観賞するように描かれています。パンと塩をのせた銀のプレート、また、当時流行していた上着の、手触りまで感じさせてくれるような毛皮やビロードは、非常に正確かつ丹念に描き込まれています。</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 20.4 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">As pinturas de Jan Steen têm sempre um toque de erotismo. Aqui, uma jovem mulher nos olha faceira enquanto prepara uma ostra. As ostras eram conhecidas como afrodisíaco, e a garota parece estar oferecendo algo mais do que boa comida. A intenção era de que este pequeno quadro fosse observado muito de perto. Assim, Steen o pintou com muita precisão e detalhismo. Veja, por exemplo, a bandeja de prata com o pão e o sal. Ou o elegante casaco com peles e veludo – que você pode quase acariciar.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">В работах Яна Стена нередко присутствует налет эротики. Здесь молодая женщина кокетливо смотрит на нас, посыпая устрицу солью. Устрицы были известны как афродизиак, и девушка, похоже, предлагает нам не только вкусную еду. Эта маленькая картина создавалась для того, чтобы рассматривать ее вблизи, поэтому Стен писал ее с особой тщательностью, уделяя большое внимание деталям - таким, например, как серебряный поднос с хлебом и солью или модная накидка на девушке. Меха и бархат выглядят так естественно, что к ним хочется прикоснуться.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 15.1 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">扬·斯蒂恩的绘画经常有一丝讽刺色彩。这幅画中，一个年轻的女子正一边准备牡蛎，一边卖弄风情地看着我们。因为牡蛎是一种春药，这个女孩不只是提供食物而已。 这幅小画是需要近距离观摩的。所以斯蒂恩画得非常精细，比如这个装有面包和盐的银盘，带有羽毛和天鹅绒的时尚外套---几乎都可以让你中风。</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">I dipinti di Jan Steen spesso rivelano un tocco di erotismo. Qui una giovane ci guarda con aria civettuola mentre prepara un’ostrica. Le ostriche erano note per i propri poteri afrodisiaci e questa ragazza sembra offrirci ben più di ottimo cibo. Questo piccolo dipinto fu ideato per essere osservato da vicino. Steen lo realizzò con grande precisione e cura dei dettagli. Prendiamo, ad esempio, il vassoio d’argento con pane e sale. Oppure la giacca alla moda con pelliccia e velluto: sembra quasi di poterla accarezzare.</dc:description><dc:creator>Jan Steen</dc:creator><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 15.1 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Las obras de Jan Steen suelen incorporar un toque de sensualidad. Aquí, una joven nos mira coqueta mientras prepara una ostra. Las ostras se conocían por sus propiedades afrodisíacas, y esta chica parece estar ofreciéndonos algo más que una buena comida. Este pequeño cuadro estaba pensado para ser admirado de cerca. Por ello, Steen lo pintó con gran precisión y atención al detalle. Observe, por ejemplo, la bandeja plateada con el pan y la sal. O la elegante chaqueta de piel y terciopelo, que casi podemos acariciar.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Het oestereetstertje</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Häufig haben Jan Steens Bilder eine Prise Erotik. Hier gönnt uns eine junge Frau beim Zubereiten von Austern einen koketten Blick. Austern gelten als Aphrodisiakum und dieses Mädchen hat offenbar mehr zu bieten als eine kulinarische Delikatesse. Nur aus der Nähe sind alle Einzelheiten dieses kleinen Gemäldes zu entdecken, das Steen enorm präzise ausführte. Zum Beispiel das Silbertablett mit Brot und Salz, oder die modische Samtjacke mit Pelzbesatz, die zum Streicheln einlädt.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Jan Steens schilderijen bezitten vaak een vleugje erotiek. Hier kijkt een jonge vrouw ons schalks aan, terwijl ze een oester klaarmaakt. Oesters staan bekend als een lustopwekkend middel. Dit meisje lijkt dus meer te willen dan lekker eten alleen. Dit kleine schilderijtje is bedoeld om van dichtbij te bekijken. Steen schilderde hier dan ook heel precies en fijn, zoals bij het zilveren dienblad met het brood en zout. Of het modieuze jasje met aaibaar bont en fluweel.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1658 - 1660 </dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 20.4 cm, cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/818"><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/818"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>