<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/12"><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0012/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0012/1000</edm:object><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/12"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/12"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 77.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1659</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 50.3 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Wilde zwijnenjacht</dc:title><dc:identifier>12</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">Berchem depicts the action of a hunting party in full swing here. A huntsman aims his gun at a wild boar that is running for its life. At the edge of the woods another boar is being roused, while a dead roe lies in the foreground. Several dogs at the left are panting with exertion. This hunting scene belonged to the small yet exquisite collection of Govert van Slingelandt, which William V purchased in its entirety in 1768 when he was only twenty years old. Aristocratic landscapes like this would have appealed to the prince – he was brought up on the hunting parties at Het Loo Palace. This was his world.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 50.3 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Nicolaes Pietersz Berchem</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Berchem toont hier de volle actie van een jachtpartij. Een jager richt zijn loop op het wilde zwijn dat vecht voor zijn leven. Langs de bosrand wordt een ander zwijn opgejaagd, terwijl op de voorgrond een dode ree ligt. Links liggen de honden uit te hijgen. Deze jachtscène bevond zich in de kleine maar uitgelezen verzameling van Govert van Slingelandt. Toen die in 1768 overleed, kocht prins Willem V de hele collectie op. Hij was toen 20 jaar oud. Dit soort deftige landschappen zullen de prins aangesproken hebben – de jachtpartijen op Paleis het Loo waren hem met de paplepel ingegoten. Dit was zijn eigen wereld.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1659</dc:date><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 77.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>