<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/293"><dcterms:created>1740 - 1750 </dcterms:created><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 101 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:title xml:lang="nl">De watervallen bij Tivoli met de villa van Maecenas</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">The majority of the 200 works in William V’s collection were Dutch or Flemish, but there were a small number of Italian, German and French pieces. Of the French paintings, these two works by Vernet are undoubtedly the finest. Vernet spent a considerable amount of time in Italy and specialised in imagined Italianate landscapes and seascapes. He excelled at contrasting the insignificance of man with the majesty of nature. Both paintings were originally in the collection of Cardinal Gonzaga of Rome. After his death, the two Vernets were put up for auction in Amsterdam, where they were purchased for Prince William V.</dc:description><dc:creator>Claude-Joseph Vernet</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 101 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:date>1740 - 1750 </dc:date><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 138 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De meeste van de 200 werken in de collectie van Willem V waren Hollands of Vlaams, maar een klein deel is Italiaans, Duits of Frans. Van die Franse schilderijen zijn de twee van Vernet ongetwijfeld de mooiste. Vernet was lange tijd in Italië geweest en specialiseerde zich daar in Italiaans aandoende, gefantaseerde landschappen en zeegezichten. Hij was een meester in het weergeven van de nietigheid van de mens, naast de overrompelende grootsheid van de natuur. Beide schilderijen zijn afkomstig uit de verzameling van kardinaal Gonzaga uit Rome. Na diens overlijden werden de twee Vernets in Amsterdam geveild, waar ze voor prins Willem V werden aangekocht.</dc:description><dc:identifier>293</dc:identifier><edm:isRelatedTo>https://collectienederland.nl/page/aggregation/mauritshuis/292</edm:isRelatedTo><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 138 cm, cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/293"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/293"/><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0293_repro/1000</edm:object><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0293_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>