<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/679"><dcterms:created>1618</dcterms:created><dc:identifier>679</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Dieses bunte Bukett aus dreißig Blumensorten ist ein Meisterwerk von Ambrosius Bosschaert. Präzise setzte er die Blumen ins Bild, dass sie einzeln gut zu erkennen sind. So bietet das Gemälde einen Überblick über die schönsten Blüten, die Bosschaert kannte – darunter auch Tulpen, die zu jener Zeit in Holland noch selten waren. Bosschaert komponierte sein Bukett aus einzelnen Studien im Verlauf eines Jahres. So konnte er Blumen zu einem Strauß zusammenstellen, die in Wirklichkeit nicht gleichzeitig blühen.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="en">This painting of a colourful bouquet of thirty types of flowers is a masterly work by Ambrosius Bosschaert. He depicted the flowers meticulously, so that each one is easily recognisable. This painting provides an overview of the most beautiful flowers known to Bosschaert, including the tulip, which was still a rarity in Holland at the time. Bosschaert based his bouquet on separate sketches he had made throughout the year. This allowed him to compose a bouquet of flowers that in real life do not bloom at the same time.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Cette peinture d’un bouquet coloré, composé de trente types de fleurs différentes, est une œuvre magistrale d’Ambrosius Bosschaert. Il a peint méticuleusement les fleurs, pour que chacune soit aisément reconnaissable. Ce tableau donne un aperçu des plus belles fleurs qu’il connaissait, dont la tulipe, qui était encore une rareté en Hollande, à l’époque. Pour peindre son bouquet, Bosschaert s’est appuyé sur différents croquis réalisés au cours de l’année. C’est ce qui lui a permis de rassembler des espèces qui, dans la réalité, ne fleurissent pas au même moment.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 46 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 64 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Ambrosius Bosschaert the Elder</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Этот красочный букет, в котором представлено тридцать разных видов цветов, принадлежит кисти Амброзиуса Босхарта. Он пишет цветы точно и тщательно, чтобы каждый из них можно было легко узнать. Босхарт помещает на этом натюрморте самые красивые цветы, которые он знал, включая тюльпан - тогда он все еще был в Голландии редкостью. Босхарт создал свой букет на основе отдельных набросков, которые делал в течение года. Таким образом он смог соединить все эти цветы в одной композиции, хотя цветут они в разное время года.</dc:description><dc:date>1618</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">安布罗修斯·博斯查尔特在他的这幅杰作里包含了大约三十种不同的花卉。他非常细致地画这些花，这样每一朵都清晰可辨。这幅画展现了博斯查尔特所知晓的所有最美丽的花，包括在当时的荷兰还很少见的郁金香。 博斯查尔特是将他在整年中所素描的单个的花朵合在一起才形成了这个花束。这使得他可以画一束在现实中有着不同花期的花卉。</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Esta representación de un colorido ramo con treinta tipos distintos de flores es una obra maestra de Ambrosius Bosschaert. Pintó las flores con gran minuciosidad, por lo que todas son fácilmente reconocibles. La obra nos permite saber cuáles fueron las flores más bellas que habría conocido Bosschaert, incluyendo el tulipán, que en aquella época todavía era una rareza en Holanda. Para pintar este ramo, Bosschaert se basó en una serie de bocetos individuales que había realizado a lo largo del año. Esto le permitió componer un ramo de flores que en la vida real no florecen en la misma época.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 64 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">30種類もの色鮮やかな花をまとめたこの花束の絵は、アンブロシウス・ボスハールトの最高傑作です。花はきわめて正確に描かれており、それぞれ品種を確認することもできます。ボスハールトが知っていた最も美しい花々の概観とみなせるようなこの絵の中に、当時まだ稀少価値であったチューリップも含まれていることは注目に値します。 ボスハールトは一年にわたって、異なる花をスケッチしました。その別々のスケッチをこの絵の中で再構成したため、同じ季節には咲かない花の花束を描くことができました。</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Vaas met bloemen in een venster</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 46 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Ambrosius Bosschaert de Oude</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Questo dipinto di un bouquet multicolore, costituito da trenta tipi di fiori diversi, è un’opera eseguita con maestria da Ambrosius Bosschaert. L’artista ritrasse i fiori meticolosamente, in modo da poter riconoscere con facilità ognuno di essi. Il dipinto offre una panoramica dei fiori più belli di cui Bosschaert era a conoscenza, come il tulipano, che in Olanda, all’epoca, costituiva ancora una rarità. Bosschaert basò il suo bouquet su bozzetti individuali da lui realizzati nel corso dell’anno. Ciò gli permise di comporre un mazzo di fiori diversi che, in realtà, non fioriscono tutti nello stesso periodo.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit schilderij met een bont boeket van dertig soorten bloemen is een topstuk van Ambrosius Bosschaert. Hij bracht de bloemen nauwkeurig in beeld, zodat ze stuk voor stuk goed te herkennen zijn. Daarmee biedt dit schilderij een overzicht van de mooiste bloemen die Bosschaert kende, waaronder de tulp die destijds in Holland nog zeldzaam was. Bosschaert baseerde zijn boeket op losse studies die hij gedurende het jaar maakte. Zo kon hij een boeket samenstellen van bloemen die in werkelijkheid niet tegelijkertijd bloeien.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Esta é a pintura de um buquê colorido com trinta tipos de flores, em um trabalho de maestria de Ambrosius Bosschaert. Ele ilustrava as flores meticulosamente e, assim, cada uma é facilmente identificável. O quadro oferece uma visão geral das mais belas flores conhecidas por Bosschaert, incluindo a tulipa, que ainda era uma raridade na Holanda naquela época.</dc:description><edm:isRelatedTo>https://collectienederland.nl/page/aggregation/mauritshuis/1208</edm:isRelatedTo></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/679"><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0679_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0679_repro/1000</edm:object><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/679"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>