<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/785"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 71 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">这幅画展现的荷兰的一个典型现象：在冰上玩耍。人们在滑雪、玩雪橇、玩一个叫“考尔夫”的游戏，这是冰上曲棍球的一种。左边，一群人从冰上掉下去了，但有人已经跑过来救他们。在桥的正前面，有个女人摔倒了，而且摔得很尴尬，露出了裸露的屁股。 阿维坎普是北荷兰第一个专注于冬季景观的画家。他一生中大部分时间住在坎彭市，是个聋哑人，因此也被成为“坎彭的哑巴”。</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Diese Szene ist typisch holländisch: Vergnügen auf dem Eis. Man läuft Schlittschuh, fährt Schlitten und spielt ‘Kolf’ – eine Art Eishockey. Links ist eine Gruppe im Eis eingebrochen, Hilfe naht. Und vor der Brücke ist eine Frau kopfüber gestürzt, dass man ihr bloßes Hinterteil sieht. Avercamp war der erste Maler in den niederländischen Nordprovinzen, der sich auf Winterlandschaften spezialisierte. Fast sein Leben lang arbeitete er in seiner Heimatstadt Kampen. Er war taubstumm – daher sein Beiname „Der Stumme aus Kampen“.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Ce tableau montre une coutume typiquement hollandaise : s’amuser sur la glace. Les gens font du patin à glace, de la luge et jouent à un jeu appelé le « kolf », une sorte de hockey sur glace. Sur la gauche, un groupe de gens sont tombés à travers la glace, mais d’autres viennent déjà à leur aide. Juste devant le pont, une femme est tombée à la renverse, dévoilant ses fesses nues. Avercamp fut le premier peintre du Nord des Pays-Bas à se spécialiser dans les paysages d’hiver. Il a vécu la plus grande partie de sa vie dans la ville de Kampen. Comme il était sourd et muet, on l’a surnommé 'Le Muet de Kampen'.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">この絵に描かれているのは、氷の上の遊びというオランダ特有の風習です。氷の上で、人々はスケートをしたり、橇に乗ったり、「コルフ」と呼ばれるアイスホッケーに似たゲームに興じています。左手には、氷の中に落ちてしまった人たちがいますが、すでに救援がそちらに向かっています。また、橋の手前には、ひっくり返ってスカートの中が丸見えの女性もいます。 アーフェルカンプは、オランダで初めて冬景色を専門に描いた画家です。彼は人生のほとんどをカンペンという町で過ごしました。また耳が不自由であったため、「カンペンの静かな人」と呼ばれました。</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">IJsvermaak</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">This painting shows a typically Dutch phenomenon: having fun on the ice. People are skating, sledging and playing a game called ‘kolf’, a sort of ice hockey. On the left, a group of people have fallen through the ice, but help is on the way. And just in front of the bridge, a woman has fallen over, revealing her bare bottom. Avercamp was the first painter in the Northern Netherlands to specialise in winter landscapes. He lived most of his life in Kampen and was deaf and dumb, which is why he was nicknamed ‘The Mute of Kampen’.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1610</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:date>1610</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit schilderij toont een typisch Hollands fenomeen: ijspret. De mensen vermaken zich met schaatsen, sleeën en het kolfspel, een soort ijshockey. Links is een groepje door het ijs gezakt, maar er komt al hulp aan. Vlak voor de brug is een vrouw voorover gevallen waardoor je haar blote billen ziet. Avercamp was de eerste schilder in de Noordelijke Nederlanden die zich specialiseerde in winterlandschappen. Hij woonde het grootste deel van zijn leven in Kampen en was doofstom – vandaar zijn bijnaam ‘De stomme van Kampen’.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">На е этой картине запечатлено типичное голландское развлечение: забавы на льду. Люди катаются на коньках и на санках и играют в игру под названием "кольф" - предшественник нынешнего хоккея на льду. Слева несколько человек провалились сквозь лед, но кто-то уже спешит им на помощь. А женщина перед мостом неудачно поскользнулась, так что оголились ягодицы. Аверкамп был первым художником в Северных Нидерландах, который стал специализироваться на зимних пейзажах. Глухонемой от рождения, он провел основную часть своей жизни в Кампене, за что и был прозван "Немым из Кампена".</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 36 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Esta pintura mostra um fenômeno tipicamente holandês: a diversão no gêlo. As pessoas estão patinando, passeando de trenó e brincando de um jogo chamado ‘kolf’, um tipo de hóquei em patins. À esquerda, um grupo de pessoas caiu através do gêlo, mas a ajuda já está a caminho. E bem defronte da ponte uma mulher caiu, exibindo o seu traseiro. Avercamp foi o primeiro pintor do norte dos Países Baixos a se especializar em paisagens invernais. Ele viveu a maior parte de sua vida na cidade de Kampen e era surdo-mudo, daí seu apelido ‘O mudo de Kampen’.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Questo dipinto mostra un fenomeno tipicamente olandese: il divertimento sul ghiaccio. La gente pattina, va in slitta e si diletta in un gioco chiamato ‘kolf’, una sorta di hockey su ghiaccio. A sinistra, un gruppo di persone sono cadute in una buca nel ghiaccio, ma qualcuno sta già correndo in loro aiuto. E proprio di fronte al ponte, una donna è caduta, rivelando le natiche nude. Avercamp fu il primo pittore nell’Olanda del Nord a specializzarsi in paesaggi invernali. L’artista visse la maggior parte della sua vita nella città di Kampen, era sordomuto e per questo fu soprannominato ‘Il Muto di Kampen’.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 71 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Hendrick Avercamp</dc:creator><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 36 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>785</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Esta obra muestra un fenómeno típicamente holandés: diversión sobre el hielo. Vemos a gente patinando, yendo en trineo y jugando a un juego denominado ‘kolf’, una especie de hockey sobre hielo. A la izquierda, el hielo se ha resquebrajado y algunas personas han caído al agua, pero ya hay quien acude a socorrerlas. Y justo delante del puente, una mujer se ha caído, dejando su trasero al descubierto. Avercamp fue el primer pintor del norte de los Países Bajos que se especializó en paisajes invernales. Vivió la mayor parte de su vida en la ciudad de Kampen y era sordomudo, por lo que se le conocía como “el mudo de Kampen”.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/785"><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/785"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>