<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1043"><dc:description xml:lang="en">This blue landscape provides the backdrop for a Bible story from the Book of Revelation: the vision of John, in which he sees Mary and her child appear in heaven. But here it is the imaginary landscape that dominates with its turbulent sea, fairy-tale mountains and bustling harbour. And an endless sense of depth. This painting is one of the earliest large-format landscapes. The Flemish painter Hans Bol painted this imaginary landscape using watercolour on linen. Paintings like this are particularly fragile, and few have withstood the ravages of time.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 85.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 50.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 50.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit blauwe landschap vormt de setting voor een verhaal uit het Bijbelboek Openbaring. Het is het visioen van Johannes, die ziet hoe Maria en kind aan de hemel verschijnen. Maar het fantasielandschap voert hier de boventoon, met de onrustige zee, de sprookjesachtige bergen en de rijke havenstad. En met die eindeloze verte. Het schilderij is een van de vroegste landschappen op een groot formaat. De Vlaamse schilder Hans Bol schilderde dit fantasielandschap met waterverf op linnen. Zulke schilderijen zijn bijzonder kwetsbaar – maar weinige doorstonden de tand des tijds.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Fantasielandschap met Johannes de Evangelist op Patmos</dc:title><dcterms:created>1564</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:identifier>1043</dc:identifier><dc:date>1564</dc:date><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Hans Bol</dc:creator><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 85.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/1043"><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1043"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>