<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/266"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/266"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0266_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0266_repro/1000</edm:object></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/266"><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1630</dc:date><dc:creator>Willem van Haecht</dc:creator><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 104.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">室内を隅から隅まで飾っているのは、すべてフランドル、ドイツ、そしてイタリアの実在する絵画です。彫刻も、有名な古代ギリシャ・ローマ時代の作品です。この「コレクターの展示室」を描いたのは、ヴィレム・ファン・ハーフトです。この主題は、特にアントワープで人気がありました。 画面の左側手前には、古代ギリシャ神話の一場面、画家アペレスが、アレキサンダー大王の寵姫カンパスペの肖像を制作しているところが描かれています。肖像画があまりに美しかったので、アレキサンダーは絵で十分満足できると考え、カンパスペをアペレスに譲りました。大王は、自然よりも芸術を選んだのです。</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 104.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Questa sala è ricca di dipinti, vere opere d’arte fiamminghe, tedesche e italiane. Anche le statue sono opere classiche ben note. Questa ‘kunstkamer’, o sala dell’arte, fu dipinta da Willem van Haecht. Si tratta di un soggetto molto popolare, specie ad Anversa. In primo piano, a sinistra, Van Haecht ha dipinto una storia tratta dall’antichità classica. Apelle è intento a ritrarre Campaspe, l’amante di Alessandro Magno. Costui ritenne il ritratto talmente bello da essere in grado di prendere il posto della stessa Campaspe, per cui donò la sua amante ad Apelle. Alessandro pose l’arte al di sopra della natura.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Esta sala está repleta de obras de arte flamengas, alemãs e italianas. Também as estátuas são clássicos muito conhecidos. Esta ‘kunstkamer’, ou sala de artes, foi pintada por Willem van Haecht. Este era um tema popular, principalmente em Antuérpia. Em primeiro plano, Van Haecht descreve uma estória da antiguidade clássica. Ela mostra Apeles pintando o retrato de Campaspe, a amante de Alexandre o Grande. Seu patrocinador acreditava que esta pintura era tão bela que poderia substituir Campaspe, e ele a presenteou a Apeles. Alexandre colocou a arte acima da natureza.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">这个房间内的都是现存的佛兰德、德国和意大利的艺术作品。这些雕塑也是著名的经典。这幅《画室》是由威廉·范·赫克特创作的。这是一个流行的主题，尤其是在安特卫普。 在左边，范·赫克特描绘的是一个古老的故事: 阿佩利斯正在画坎巴丝帕的肖像，她是亚历山大大帝的情人。他的买家觉得这幅肖像如此漂亮，可以取代坎巴丝帕。于是他把他的情人作为礼物送给了阿佩利斯。亚历山大为了艺术放弃了自然。</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Apelles schildert Campaspe</dc:title><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 148.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">In diesem Saal sind tatsächlich existierende flämische, deutsche und italienische Kunstwerke dargestellt, dazu allgemein bekannte klassische Statuen. Willem van Haecht hielt eine sogenannte „Kunstkammer“ im Bild fest. Das Motiv war in Antwerpen ausgesprochen beliebt. Im Vordergrund links malte van Haecht eine Legende aus dem klassischen Altertum. Zu sehen ist Apelles, wie er Campaspe porträtiert, die Geliebte Alexander des Großen. Dieser fand das Ergebnis so gelungen, dass er es gegen die echte Campaspe eintauschte. Die leibhaftige Geliebte gab er Apelles zum Geschenk. Womit Alexander die Kunst über die Natur erhob.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 148.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1630</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">This room is filled with paintings that are all existing Flemish, German and Italian works of art. The statues, too, are well-known classics. This ‘kunstkamer’, or art room, was painted by Willem van Haecht. It was a popular subject, particularly in Antwerp. In the left foreground, Van Haecht depicted a story from classical antiquity. It shows Apelles painting the portrait of Campaspe, the lover of Alexander the Great. His patron thought the portrait was so beautiful that it could take Campaspe’s place, and he presented his lover to Apelles as a gift. Alexander chose art above nature.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Cette pièce est remplie de tableaux qui sont tous des œuvres existant réellement - flamandes, allemandes et italiennes. Les statues, elles aussi, sont des œuvres célèbres. Cette « Kunstkammer » ou cabinet d’amateur, a été réalisée par Willem van Haecht. C’était un sujet populaire, en particulier à Anvers. Au premier plan à gauche, Van Haecht dépeint une histoire tirée de l’Antiquité. Il montre Apelle, en train de peindre le portrait de Campaspe, la maîtresse d’Alexandre le Grand. Celui-ci trouva que le portrait était si beau, qu’il pouvait remplacer Campaspe. Et il offrit sa maîtresse en cadeau à Apelle. Par ce choix, Alexandre plaçait l’art au-dessus de la nature.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Deze zaal hangt vol schilderijen die stuk voor stuk bestaande Vlaamse, Duitse en Italiaanse kunstwerken zijn. Ook de beelden zijn bekende klassiekers. Deze kunstkamer is geschilderd door Willem van Haecht. Het is een onderwerp dat vooral in Antwerpen geliefd was. Linksvoor schilderde Van Haecht een verhaal uit de klassieke oudheid. Daar is te zien hoe Apelles het portret van Campaspe schildert, de minnares van Alexander de Grote. Die vindt het resultaat zó mooi, dat hij genoegen neemt met het portret en de minnares aan Apelles schenkt. Alexander verkiest de kunst boven de natuur.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">La sala que vemos aquí está llena de cuadros que son obras reales de pintores flamencos, alemanes e italianos. Las estatuas también son obras clásicas claramente reconocibles. Esta ‘kunstkamer’, o sala de arte, fue pintada por Willem van Haecht. Fue un tema popular de la época, especialmente en Amberes. En primer plano a la izquierda, Van Haecht representa una historia de la antigüedad clásica: Apelles pintando el retrato de Campaspe, la amante de Alejandro Magno. Una vez terminado, Alejando pensó que el retrato era tan hermoso que podía sustituir a la joven, y ofreció a Campaspe como regalo al pintor. Alejandro eligió el arte por encima de la naturaleza.</dc:description><dc:identifier>266</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Картины на стенах этой комнаты - реальные произведения фламандских, немецких и итальянских мастеров. Античные скульптуры также хорошо известны. Это - "кунсткамера" или "зал искусств" кисти Виллема ван Хахта. Тема кунсткамеры была очень популярна, особенно в Антверпене.  В левой части композиции ван Хахт рассказывает нам историю из классической античности. Мы видим художника Апеллеса, который пишет портрет Кампаспы - любовницы Александра Македонского. Александр решил, что портрет вышел таким красивым, что вполне мог заменить оригинал, и преподнес Кампаспу в дар Апеллесу. Так он предпочел искусство самой жизни.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>