<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/92"><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Questo è il più famoso paesaggio urbano del Seicento olandese. L’interazione tra luci e ombre, l’imponente cielo nuvoloso e i delicati riflessi sull’acqua rendono quest’opera un capolavoro assoluto. Stiamo osservando Delft dal sud. C’è appena un alito di vento e la città è invasa da un’atmosfera tranquilla, rappresentata da Vermeer attraverso tre strisce orizzontali: acqua, città e cielo. L’artista ritrasse, inoltre, gli edifici facendoli apparire più curati di quanto non fossero in realtà.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Esta é a paisagem mais famosa do século dezessete. A interação de luz e sombra, o impressionante céu nublado e os sutis reflexos na água fazem desta pintura uma verdadeira obra de arte. Estamos olhando para Delft desde o sul. Quase não há vento e a cidade tem um ar de tranquilidade. Vermeer refletiu sua tranquilidade nesta composição ao criar três faixas horizontais: a água, a cidade e o céu. Ele pintou as edificações com linhas mais limpas do que realmente tinham.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit is het beroemdste stadsgezicht uit de Hollandse 17de eeuw. Het spel tussen licht en schaduw, de indrukwekkende wolkenlucht en de subtiele weerspiegelingen op het water maken dit schilderij tot een absoluut meesterwerk. We zien Delft vanuit het zuiden. Het is vrijwel windstil, de stad ademt rust uit. Vermeer bracht die rust ook in zijn compositie door drie horizontale banen te maken: water, stad en lucht. En door de bebouwing wat minder rommelig te schilderen dan zij in werkelijkheid was.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1660 - 1661 </dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">This is the most famous cityscape of the Dutch seventeenth century. The interplay of light and shade, the impressive cloudy sky and the subtle reflections in the water make this painting an absolute masterpiece. We are looking at Delft from the south. There is hardly a breath of wind and the city has an air of tranquillity. Vermeer reflected this tranquillity in his composition, by making three horizontal strips: water, city and sky. He also painted the buildings a bit neater than they actually were.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 115.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 115.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">オランダ絵画黄金時代の作品で、最も有名な都市風景画です。光と影のたわむれ、印象的な雲が浮かぶ空、そして水面に映る微妙な建物の影には、この作品が確かな傑作である所以が認められます。 私たちは、デルフトの街を南から眺めています。風はほとんどなく、街には静けさが漂っています。この穏やかな様子は、水、街、空、という水平な三層の画面構成からももたらされています。街の建築物も実際より整えて描かれました。</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 96.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Éste es el paisaje urbano más famoso del siglo XVII holandés. La interacción de luz y sombra, el impresionante cielo nublado y los sutiles reflejos en el agua convierten este cuadro en toda una obra maestra. Vemos la ciudad de Delft desde el sur. Apenas hay un soplo de viento y la ciudad respira un aire de tranquilidad. Vermeer reflejó esta tranquilidad en su composición con la incorporación de tres bandas horizontales: el agua, la ciudad y el cielo. También pintó los edificios un poco más cerca de lo que estaban en realidad.</dc:description><dc:identifier>92</dc:identifier><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Gezicht op Delft</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Dies ist die berühmteste Stadtlandschaft des Holländischen siebzehnten Jahrhundert. Das Spiel zwischen Licht und Schatten, der eindrucksvolle Wolkenhimmel und die sachten Spiegelungen auf dem Wasser machen das Bild zu einem wahren Meisterwerk. Wir sehen Delft von Süden. Es ist fast windstill und die Stadt strahlt Ruhe aus. Vermeer brachte diese Ruhe auch in seine Komposition durch die drei horizontalen Bahnen: Wasser, Stadt und Luft. Außerdem malte er die Gebäude ein wenig geordneter als sie in Wirklichkeit waren.</dc:description><dc:date>1660 - 1661 </dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Это самый известный городской пейзаж Золотого века голландской живописи. Игра света и тени, выразительные облака на небе и неуловимые отражения на воде делают его непревзойденным шедевром. Мы смотрим на Дельфт с юга. Ветра почти нет, и город окутан атмосферой тишины и покоя. Вермеер переносит эту атмосферу на полотно, композиционно разделив его на три горизонтальных полосы: вода, город и небо. Кроме того, он изображает здания более стройными и аккуратными, чем они были на самом деле.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">这是荷兰黄金时代最著名的城市景观画。光影的相互作用，云层密布的天空以及水中的微弱倒影让这幅画成为了旷世杰作。 我们现在是从南边望向德尔福特。几乎没有一丝风，整个城市都充满了宁静的气息。维米尔用他的构图来表现这种宁静，他把整个画面分成了横的三块:水面、城市和天空。他还将建筑物画得比实际更加简洁。</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 96.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Johannes Vermeer</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Voici l’un des plus célèbres paysages urbains du 17ième siècle néerlandais. L’interaction de l’ombre et de la lumière, l’imposant ciel nuageux et la subtilité des reflets dans l’eau, font de ce tableau un chef-d’œuvre absolu. Nous regardons Delft depuis le sud. C’est à peine s’il y a un souffle de vent et la ville donne une impression de tranquillité que Vermeer traite dans sa composition par trois bandes horizontales : l‘eau, la ville et le ciel. Il a également représenté les bâtiments un peu plus nets qu’ils ne l’étaient en réalité.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/92"><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0092_repro/1000</edm:object><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0092_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/92"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>