<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/145"><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">José e Maria estão no templo para dedicar seu bebê recém-nascido Jesus a Deus, onde Simeão reconhece a criança como o tão esperado Messias. O velho homem toma o bebê em seus braços e irrompe em um canto de louvor. A luz divina, que inunda Simeão, parece vir da própria criança. Rembrandt tinha 25 anos quando pintou esta cena, e ainda vivia em Leiden. Mudou-se para Amsterdã no mesmo ano, onde começou a pintar quadros maiores e executou retratos pela primeira vez.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 47.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 60.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">ヨセフとマリアは神殿で、生まれたばかりのイエスを捧げています。老人シメオンは、子供が長く待ち望まれてきた救世主であることを、一瞬にして認めます。シメオンはイエスを腕に抱き取り、讃歌を歌います。シメオンを照らし出す神々しい光は、まるで幼子から発せられているように見えます。 この絵を描いた時、レンブラントは25歳で、まだライデンに住んでいました。しかし、同じ年に、彼はアムステルダムに移住しました。アムステルダムでは、より大きなサイズの絵を制作するようになり、初めて肖像画にも挑戦しました。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">约瑟夫和玛利亚正在寺庙中，打算将他们的新生儿耶稣献给上帝。西蒙在那里认出这孩子就是他等待已久的弥赛亚。这个老人将孩子抱入怀中，不禁唱起了赞美之歌。神圣的光洒在西蒙身上，而这光似乎就是从这孩子身上散发出来的。 当伦勃朗创作这个场景时，他才25岁，仍然住在莱顿。同一年，他搬往了阿姆斯特丹，在那里，他开始创作更大的绘画作品并首次开始了肖像画的创作。</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">Joseph and Mary are in the temple to dedicate their newborn baby Jesus to God, where the child is recognised by Simeon as the long-awaited Messiah. The old man takes him in his arms and bursts into a song of praise. The divine light that floods Simeon appears to be shining from the child himself. When Rembrandt painted this scene, he was twenty-five and still living in Leiden. He moved to Amsterdam in the same year, where he started to paint much larger works and made portraits for the first time.</dc:description><dc:identifier>145</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Joseph et Marie sont au temple pour présenter à Dieu Jésus, leur fils nouveau-né, en qui Siméon reconnaît le messie longtemps attendu. Le vieil homme tient le petit dans ses bras et entonne un chant de louange. La lumière divine qui enveloppe Siméon semble émaner de l’enfant même. Quand Rembrandt peint cette scène, il a 25 ans et vit encore à Leyde. Il part cette année-là pour Amsterdam où il commence à réaliser des formats beaucoup plus grands et, pour la première fois, des portraits.</dc:description><dc:creator>Rembrandt van Rijn</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Jozef en Maria zijn in de tempel om de pasgeboren Jezus op te dragen aan God. Daar wordt het kind door Simeon herkend als de langverwachte Messias. De oude man neemt hem in zijn armen en heft een loflied aan. Het goddelijke licht dat hem overspoelt, lijkt uit het kind zelf te komen. Rembrandt was 25 jaar en woonde nog in Leiden, toen hij deze voorstelling schilderde. In hetzelfde jaar verhuisde hij naar Amsterdam, waar hij veel groter ging werken en voor het eerst portretten maakte.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">José y María han ido al templo para presentar a Jesús recién nacido ante Dios. En el templo, Simeón reconoce en el niño al esperado Mesías. El anciano toma al pequeño en sus brazos y entona un canto de alabanza. La luz divina que baña a Simeón parece emanar del propio infante. Rembrandt pintó esta escena con veinticinco años, cuando aún vivía en Leiden. Ese mismo año se trasladaría a Ámsterdam, donde sus obras adoptaron dimensiones mucho más grandes y empezó a pintar retratos.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Het loflied van Simeon</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Giuseppe e Maria sono nel tempio per consacrare a Dio il loro primogenito, Gesù, e il bimbo è riconosciuto da Simeone come il tanto atteso Messia. Il vecchio lo prende tra le sue braccia e scoppia spontaneamente in un cantico. La luce divina che si riversa su Simeone sembra essere davvero emanata da Gesù Bambino. Quando ritrasse questa scena, Rembrandt aveva 25 anni e viveva ancora a Leida. Quello stesso anno si trasferì ad Amsterdam, dove iniziò a dipingere opere molto più ampie e a realizzare ritratti.</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Maria und Josef sind im Tempel, um Gott das neugeborene Jesuskind zu weihen. Da wird es von Simeon als der langerwartete Messias erkannt. Der alte Mann schließt es in seine Arme und stimmt ein Loblied an. Das göttliche Licht, das beide einhüllt, scheint ganz vom Kind auszugehen. Rembrandt war fünfundzwanzig und wohnte noch in Leiden, als er diese Szene malte. Im gleichen Jahr zog er nach Amsterdam, wo er weitaus größere Werke in Angriff nahm und zum ersten Mal auch Porträts schuf.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1631</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 47.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 60.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><edm:isRelatedTo>https://collectienederland.nl/page/aggregation/mauritshuis/1226</edm:isRelatedTo><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Когда Иосиф и Мария пришли в Иерусалимский храм, чтобы посвятить Младенца Иисуса Богу, старец Симеон признал в ребенке долгожданного Мессию. Старик берет его на руки и запевает хвалебную песнь. Кажется, что окутывающий Симеона божественный свет исходит от самого младенца. Когда Рембрандт писал это произведение, ему было всего 25 лет, и он все еще жил в Лейдене. В том же году он перебрался в Амстердам, где стал создавать гораздо более масштабные полотна и впервые начал писать портреты.</dc:description><dc:date>1631</dc:date><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/145"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/145"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0145_repro_1/1000</edm:object><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0145_repro_1/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>