<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/253"><dc:creator>Jan Brueghel de Oude</dc:creator><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 114.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>253</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Questo dipinto è firmato da due famosi maestri fiamminghi: Rubens e Brueghel. I due artisti realizzarono diversi esempi di questo tipo di pittura, ideati come pezzi da esposizione che intendevano combinare il meglio del loro talento. Sebbene Brueghel fosse responsabile della composizione, a iniziare il dipinto fu Rubens. Molto sommariamente, e con colpi di pittura sottili, Rubens dipinse Adamo ed Eva, l’albero, il cavallo e il serpente. Poi Brueghel si dedicò alle piante e agli animali, che dipinse con precisione enciclopedica nelle finiture.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Het aardse paradijs met de zondeval van Adam en Eva</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">この絵は、フランドルを代表する二人の巨匠、ルーベンスとブリューゲルの合作です。ほかにもこの二人の共同制作による作品がありますが、このような合作の意図は、双方の画家がベストを尽くし合い、見世物のように見る人を楽しませることでした。 画面の構成したのはブリューゲルで、ルーベンスは直接描き始めました。ルーベンスが担当したアダムとイヴ、木、馬、蛇は、薄塗りで非常に素描的に仕上げられています。ブリューゲルは絵具を丹念に塗りながら、その他の動物と植物を百科事典から写したように細部まで正確に描いて完成させています。</dc:description><dc:creator>Peter Paul Rubens</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">This painting is by two famous Flemish masters: Rubens and Brueghel. They made several versions of this type of painting, which were intended as showpieces that combined the best of both artists. Although Brueghel was responsible for the composition, Rubens started the painting. Very sketchily, in thin paint, he painted Adam and Eve, the tree, the horse and the serpent. Then Brueghel took on the plants and animals, which he painted with encyclopaedic precision in finishing paint.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 74.3 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Dieses Gemälde stammt von zwei berühmten Flämischen Meistern: Rubens und Brueghel. Gemeinsam schufen sie mehrere solcher Bilder als Paradestücke, die das Beste beider Künstler demonstrieren sollten. Brueghel war für die Bildkomposition zuständig, doch Rubens begann mit der Ausführung. Skizzenhaft malte er mit dünner Farbe Adam und Eva, dazu den Baum, das Pferd und die Schlange. Danach übernahm Brueghel die Pflanzen und Tiere, die er minutiös in deckenden Farben ausarbeitete.</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Esta pintura foi executada por dois mestres flamengos: Rubens e Brueghel. Eles realizaram várias obras deste tipo, com a combinação da excepcionalidade de dois artistas. Embora Brueghel tenha sido o responsável pela composição, Rubens deu início ao trabalho. De uma forma quase de esboço, com finas camadas de tinta, pintou Adão e Eva, a árvore, o cavalo e a serpente. Brueghel, então, executou as plantas e os animais, que pintou com precisão enciclopédica.</dc:description><dc:creator>Jan Brueghel the Elder</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Ce tableau est l’œuvre de deux célèbres maîtres flamands : Rubens et Brueghel. Ils en ont ainsi réalisés plusieurs, destinés à être des pièces exceptionnelles, combinant le meilleur des deux artistes. Brueghel était responsable de la composition, mais c’est Rubens qui débuta le tableau. Comme une ébauche, il peignit d’une fine couche de peinture Adam et Ève, l’arbre, le cheval et le serpent. Brueghel prit la relève et réalisa les plantes et les animaux avec une précision encyclopédique, à l’aide d’une peinture de finition.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Esta obra fue realizada por dos famosos maestros flamencos: Rubens y Brueghel. Los dos artistas pintaron varios cuadros de este tipo con el objetivo principal de mostrar la combinación de ambos talentos en su máxima expresión. Aunque Brueghel es el autor de la composición, Rubens fue el que empezó a trabajar en el cuadro. Con trazos imprecisos y capas finas de pintura representó a Adán y Eva, el árbol, el caballo y la serpiente. A continuación Brueghel se ocupó de las plantas y los animales, los cuales pintó con precisión enciclopédica utilizando pintura de acabados.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1615</dcterms:created><dc:date>1615</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">这幅画是由两位著名的佛兰芒大师一起创作的：鲁本斯和勃鲁盖尔。他们创作了好几幅这种类型的绘画，结合了两人各自的特长，被作为合作的展示品。 尽管是勃鲁盖尔负责构图，但开始画的是鲁本斯。他用非常简略的笔触，稀薄的颜料画了亚当夏娃、树、马和蛇。勃鲁盖尔接着画植物和动物，他画得非常细致。</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit schilderij is van twee beroemde Vlaamse meesters: Rubens en Brueghel. Ze maakten meer van dit soort schilderijen, die bedoeld waren als spektakelstukken waarin het beste van beiden samen kwam. Brueghel was verantwoordelijk voor de compositie, maar Rubens begon met schilderen. Heel schetsmatig en met dunne verf schilderde hij Adam en Eva, de boom, het paard en de slang. Daarna nam Brueghel de planten en dieren voor zijn rekening, die hij met encyclopedische precisie in dekkende verf schilderde.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 74.3 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Перед вами - работа двух знаменитых фламандских мастеров, Рубенса и Брейгеля. Они написали несколько совместных картин – своего рода рекламные образцы, демонстрировавшие мастерство обоих художников потенциальным заказчикам. Хотя Брейгель отвечал за общую композицию, Рубенс первым принялся за работу. Не вдаваясь в детали, тонким слоем краски он пишет Адама и Еву, дерево, лошадь и змея-искусителя. Брейгель взял на себя изображение растений и животных, и передает их на холсте с академической точностью.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 114.7 cm, cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/253"><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0253/1000</edm:object><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/253"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0253/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>