<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1150"><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 62.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 62.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">老女はロウソクに手をかざし、まぶしい光から目を守りながらじっと前を見据えています。その後ろから、少年が老女の肩越しに自分のロウソクに火をつけようとしています。ルーベンスは、イタリアで見たカラヴァッジオの様式に倣ってこの板絵を描いています。カラヴァッジオの特徴は、強烈な光の効果と洗練されていないレアリスムです。 ルーベンスはこの絵を売るために制作したのではなく、自分の手元に残しました。おそらく、アトリエの弟子たちの教材として使ったのでしょう。</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">一个老妇女向前看着，好让眼睛避开闪烁的烛光。她身后的男孩手持蜡烛准备将其点亮。这幅画是卡拉瓦乔风格，鲁本斯曾在意大利看到过他的作品。这种风格的特点是其强烈的光效果和不加修饰的自然主义。 鲁本斯创作这幅作品并不是为了出售，他一直将其保留着。他很可能将其作为一个研究材料来给其工作室的学生学习。</dc:description><dc:identifier>1150</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">Una vecchia guarda dinanzi a sé, proteggendosi gli occhi dalla luce della candela, mentre il ragazzo dietro di essa regge la propria candela, pronta per essere accesa. Il pannello è dipinto nello stile di Caravaggio, le cui opere Rubens aveva visto in Italia. Il suo stile è caratterizzato da effetti di luce avvincenti e da un naturalismo non rifinito. Rubens non realizzò questo dipinto al fine di venderlo. L’opera rimase in suo possesso e l’artista forse se ne servì come materiale di riferimento per gli allievi che frequentavano il suo studio.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dcterms:created>1616 - 1617 </dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">An old woman gazes ahead, shielding her eyes from the candlelight, while the boy behind her holds his candle, ready to be lit. The panel is painted in the style of Caravaggio, whose work Rubens had seen in Italy. This style is characterised by its exciting effects of light and unpolished naturalism. Rubens did not make this painting to be sold; instead he retained possession of it. He probably used it as study material for the pupils in his studio.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Oude vrouw en jongen met kaarsen</dc:title><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 84 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 99 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Дряхлая старуха мечтательно глядит перед собой, прикрывая глаза от мерцающего света свечи, а мальчик позади нее готовится зажечь свою свечу. Эта работа написана в стиле Караваджо, произведения которого Рубенс видел в Италии. Для этого стиля характерны световые эффекты и удивительный натурализм изображения. Рубенс писал эту работу не для продажи и хранил у себя. Возможно, он использовал ее в качестве учебного материала для учеников в своей мастерской.</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 84 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">Eine alte Frau blickt vor sich hin und schützt dabei ihre Augen vor dem Kerzenlicht, während der Junge hinter ihr seine Kerze zum Anstecken hinhält. Das Tafelbild ist im Stil Caravaggios gemalt, dessen Werk Rubens in Italien gesehen hatte. Typisch sind die spannungsreichen Lichteffekte und der ungekünstelte Naturalismus. Rubens malte dieses Bild nicht für den Verkauf, sondern behielt es sein Leben lang. Wahrscheinlich benutzte er es als Anschauungsmaterial für seine Schüler.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 99 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">Una anciana mira hacia adelante, protegiéndose los ojos de la luz de la vela, mientras tras ella un niño sujeta otra vela con la intención de encenderla. El panel evoca el estilo de Caravaggio, cuya obra Rubens había visto en Italia. Este estilo se caracteriza por sus extraordinarios efectos de luz y por un tosco naturalismo. Rubens no pintó este cuadro para venderlo sino para su propio uso. Probablemente lo utilizó como material de estudio para los aprendices que tenía en su taller.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 77 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Une vieille femme regarde devant elle et protège ses yeux de la lumière d’une bougie, tandis que le garçon derrière elle tient sa bougie, prête à être allumée. Le panneau est peint dans le style de Caravage, dont Rubens avait vu le travail en Italie. Ce style se caractérise par ses effets de lumière et son naturalisme brut. Rubens n’a pas réalisé ce tableau pour le vendre. Au contraire, il l’a gardé pour lui. Il s’en servait sans doute comme matériau d’étude pour les élèves de son atelier.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 77 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Uma velha senhora olha para frente, protegendo seus olhos do brilho da chama, enquanto que o menino, que está atrás, segura sua vela pronto para acendê-la. O painel foi pintado no estilo de Caravaggio, cujos trabalhos Rubens conheceu na Itália. Este estilo é caracterizado por instigantes efeitos de luz e um rude naturalismo. Rubens não pintou este quadro com intenção de vendê-lo; ele o manteve para si. Provavelmente o usou como material de estudo para seus discípulos no estúdio.</dc:description><dc:creator>Peter Paul Rubens</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>1616 - 1617 </dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Een oude vrouw staart voor zich uit en tempert met haar hand het kaarslicht, terwijl de jongen achter haar zijn kaars bijhoudt om hem aan te steken. Het paneel is geschilderd in de stijl van Caravaggio, wiens werk Rubens in Italië had leren kennen. Kenmerkend daarvoor zijn de spannende lichteffecten en het ongepolijste realisme. Rubens maakte dit schilderij niet voor de verkoop en hield het altijd bij zich. Waarschijnlijk gebruikte hij het als studiemateriaal voor de leerlingen in zijn atelier.</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/1150"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1150"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>