<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/955"><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/955"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/955"><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 31.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>955</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 31.9 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:date>1638</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">Huygh Voskuyl looks out at us with a frown, as if we have interrupted him at work. But in fact this is simply what the artist saw reflected in the mirror when he painted his self-portrait. His straggly hair, unshaven cheeks and unkempt moustache lend this self-portrait an air of informality unusual for portraits of the Dutch seventeenth century. Equally unusual is the wooden wall in the background, which looks especially real with its fine grain. On it, Voskuyl has inscribed his signature and age: forty-six. Only a few paintings by this artist are known, making this self-portrait all the more exceptional.</dc:description><dc:creator>Huygh Pietersz Voskuyl</dc:creator><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 42.2 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Zelfportret</dc:title><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 42.2 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dcterms:created>1638</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Huygh Voskuyl kijkt ons fronsend aan, alsof we hem onderbreken in zijn bezigheden. Maar in feite is dit de weergave van wat Voskuyl in zijn spiegel zag toen hij dit zelfportret maakte. Zijn piekende haren, ongeschoren kaken en flodderige snor geven dit zelfportret een informele uitstraling die uitzonderlijk is voor portretten uit de 17de eeuw. Bijzonder is ook de houten wand op de achtergrond, die met zijn fijne nerven net echt lijkt. Daarop plaatste Voskuyl zijn signatuur en leeftijd: 46 jaar oud. Er zijn maar een paar schilderijen van zijn hand bekend, wat dit zelfportret nog bijzonderder maakt.</dc:description><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>