<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/736"><dc:description xml:lang="en">A woman is drunkenly held upright as she leans over to vomit. She is still holding onto a wine jug, and her breasts are hanging out of her blouse. The bystanders are laughing at her as she is led towards the pigpen on the right. After all, a pig belongs in the sty. Where she can sleep it off. Jan Steen rarely painted the loss of dignity as unkindly as he did here. The inebriated woman is the butt of all the ridicule. But Steen the joker also mocked the bystanders by depicting them as caricatures. As if half the village is blind drunk.</dc:description><dc:creator>Jan Steen</dc:creator><dc:identifier>736</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 72.1 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:title xml:lang="nl">‘Wie een varken is, moet in het kot’</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:date>1673 - 1675 </dc:date><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 72.1 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Laveloos wordt een vrouw overeind gehouden, terwijl ze moet spugen. Ze heeft de wijnkan nog in haar hand, haar borsten hangen uit haar bloesje. De omstanders lachen haar uit en voeren haar naar het varkenshok rechts. Want wie een varken is, moet maar in het kot. Om haar roes uit te slapen. Zelden schilderde Jan Steen het verlies van waardigheid zo genadeloos als hier. De dronken vrouw is het mikpunt van alle spot. Maar grappenmaker Steen nam ook de omstanders op de hak door hen heel karikaturaal af te beelden. Alsof het halve dorp ladderzat is.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 85.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 85.8 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1673 - 1675 </dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/736"><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/736"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>