<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1217"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">pastel</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 45 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Portret van Jacob van Kretschmar (1721-1792)</dc:title><dc:creator>Jean-Baptiste Perronneau</dc:creator><dc:date>1754</dc:date><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 45 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">paper</dcterms:medium><dc:type xml:lang="en">pastel</dc:type><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 60 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">papier</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit is Jacob van Kretschmar, 33 jaar oud. Van Kretschmar was van adel en maakte carrière in het leger. Hij draagt hier een modieuze blauwe jas met goudborduursel. Dat borduursel is heel losjes weergegeven, net als het witte kant van zijn ‘jabot’. Jacobs gezicht is echter heel gedetailleerd. Van Kretschmar liet zich portretteren door Perronneau, een Franse kunstenaar. Die maakte dit portret met krijt, een populaire techniek in de 18de eeuw. Mede door Perronneau werden pastelportretten geliefd in Nederland. Pastel is heel kwetsbaar, maar omdat dit portret altijd in familiebezit bleef, is het in perfecte staat.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1754</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 60 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">This is Jacob van Kretschmar, aged 33. Van Kretschmar belonged to the Dutch aristocracy and made his career in the army. In this portrait he wears a chic blue jacket with gold embroidery. The embroidery has been very loosely rendered, as has the white lace of his ‘jabot’. Jacob’s face, by contrast, has been recorded in meticulous detail. Van Kretschmar had his portrait painted by Perronneau, a French artist. It is executed in pastels, a popular technique in the 18th century. It was partly thanks to Perronneau that pastel portraits became fashionable in the Netherlands. Pastels are extremely delicate, but because this portrait had always stayed in the family, it is in perfect condition.</dc:description><dc:identifier>1217</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/1217"><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1217"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>