<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1212"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Ludger tom Ring the Younger</dc:creator><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Narcissen, maagdenpalm en viooltjes in een kan</dc:title><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 15.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 15.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1562</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:date>1562</dc:date><dc:creator>Ludger tom Ring de Jonge</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit 16de-eeuwse boeketje is uitzonderlijk zeldzaam, want vóór 1600 werden bloemstillevens nauwelijks geschilderd. Bloemen werden pas in de 17de eeuw een geliefd onderwerp voor schilderijen in Holland en Vlaanderen. Het bloemstilleven van Ludger tom Ring loopt op die ontwikkeling vooruit. In een hoge schenkkan staat een tuiltje bloemen met narcissen, viooltjes en maagdenpalm. Op tafel liggen nog wat losse bloemen en een takje wijnruit. Oorspronkelijk was de maagdenpalm blauwpaars, maar het blauwe pigment verloor in de loop der eeuwen zijn kleur. Daardoor zien we nu de oranjebruine onderlaag. Ludger tom Ring was de jongste telg van een kunstenaarsfamilie uit Münster. Hij leerde het vak van zijn vader en verbleef enige tijd in Holland, Vlaanderen en Engeland. In 1569 vestigde hij zich in Braunschweig waar hij overleed. Hij maakte vooral portretten en enkele bloemstillevens.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 35 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 35 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:medium xml:lang="nl">paneel</dcterms:medium><dc:identifier>1212</dc:identifier><dcterms:medium xml:lang="en">panel</dcterms:medium><dc:description xml:lang="en">This sixteenth-century bouquet is all the more exceptional since flower pieces were rarely painted before 1600. It was only in the seventeenth century that flowers became a popular subject in Dutch and Flemish painting. Ludger tom Ring’s still life anticipates this development. A tall ewer holds a posy of narcissi, violets and periwinkle flowers. Some individual blooms and a sprig of rue lie on the table. The periwinkle flowers would originally have been a purple-blue colour, but the blue pigment has faded over the centuries leaving only the orange-brown undercoat visible. Ludger tom Ring was the youngest member of a family of painters working in Münster. He trained with his father and spent time in Holland, Flanders and England. In 1569 he settled in Braunschweig, where he would live until his death. He primarily painted portraits, as well as a number of flower pieces.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/1212"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/1212"/><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>