<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rda="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/155"><dc:description xml:lang="ja-jp">ファン・ライスダールは、この絵の中でオランダの風景の本質をとらえています。砂丘の上から、遠くに見えるハールレムの街に続く平坦な大地が見下ろすように描かれています。その上には広大な空が広がり、積雲が浮かんでいます。 ファン・ライスダールは、雲の間から日が差し、光と影が互い違いになる様子を描写しています。私たちの目は、日の当たる場所をたどりながら、白い布がさらされている野原から、遠くに見える聖バフォ教会まで画面の奥深くへと導かれてゆきます。</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 62 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 81 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this painting, Van Ruisdael captured the essence of the Dutch landscape. From a high dune, we look out over the flat land in the direction of Haarlem, the city in the distance. Above the city stretches an immense sky with clouds drifting by. Van Ruisdael paints the sun shining between the clouds, alternating light and shade. He directs our gaze deep into the painting along the patches of sunshine, from the fields where linen is spread out to bleach to Saint Bavo’s Church in the distance.</dc:description><dc:date>1670 - 1675 </dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">painting</dc:type><dc:identifier>155</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">schilderij</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="ru-ru">Эта работа Якоба ван Рейсдала воплощает в себе саму суть − само воплощение голландского пейзажа. Мы смотрим на плоскую равнину с высокого песчаного холма. На горизонте виднеются очертания Харлема. Над ним - бескрайнее небо с плывущими облаками. Лучи солнца пронизывают облака, создавая резкий контраст между светом и тенью. Ван Рейсдал направляет наш взгляд от пятен яркого света на зеленых полях, где отбеливаются широкие полосы льняного полотна, к церкви Святого Бавона, виднеющейся вдали.</dc:description><dc:title xml:lang="nl">Gezicht op Haarlem met bleekvelden</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="zh-cn">在这幅画中，凡·罗伊斯达尔捕捉住了荷兰风景的精华。我们可以从这个高耸的山丘通过平坦的土地看向这个远方的城市—哈勒姆所在的方向。城市的尽头是广阔的天空，朵朵白云飘浮其上。 凡·罗伊斯达尔通过光和阴影的转变画出了云朵之间的阳光。他将我们的视线引到斑驳的阳光上，然后从晒满亚麻的田地到远处的圣巴夫教堂。</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">width, breedte 81 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 55.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In dit schilderij legde Van Ruisdael de essentie van het Hollandse landschap vast. Vanaf een hoog duin kijken we over het vlakke land in de richting van Haarlem, de stad in de verte. Daarboven strekt zich een onmetelijke lucht uit waarin stapelwolken voorbijglijden. Van Ruisdael liet de zon door de wolken schijnen, waardoor licht en schaduw elkaar afwisselen. Via de zonnige plekken leidt hij onze blik de diepte in, van de velden waar linnen ligt te bleken, naar de Haarlemse Bavokerk in de verte.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en-gb">height, hoogte 73 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="pt-pt">Nesta pintura, Van Ruisdael capturou a essência da paisagem holandesa. Desde o topo de uma duna vislumbramos as terras planas em direção a Haarlem, a cidade ao longe. Um imenso céu se estende sobre a cidade, com nuvens à deriva. Van Ruisdael pinta o Sol brilhando entre as nuvens, alternando luz e sombra. Ele direciona nosso olhar para as profundezas da pintura através dos trechos banhados pelo Sol, dos campos com e até a Igreja de São Bavo, à distância.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 55.5 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">width, breedte 62 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="es-es">En esta obra, Van Ruisdael captura la esencia del paisaje holandés. Desde una duna elevada, nuestra vista planea sobre el terreno llano de los campos en dirección a Harlem, la ciudad que se vislumbra en la distancia. Un cielo inmenso y poblado de nubes se extiende sobre la ciudad. Van Ruisdael pinta el resplandor del sol entre las nubes, alternando luz y sombra. A través de los parches iluminados de paisaje, guía nuestra mirada hacia la lejanía, desde los campos con hileras de ropa blanca secándose al sol hasta la iglesia de San Bavón que se perfila en el horizonte.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="it-it">In questo dipinto, Van Ruisdael riuscì a cogliere l’essenza del paesaggio olandese. Da un’alta duna, il nostro sguardo si dirige oltre una pianura in direzione di Haarlem, la città visibile in lontananza. Sopra la città si estende un cielo immenso con nuvole alla deriva. Van Ruisdael dipinge il sole risplendente tra le nuvole, alternando luci e ombre. Dirige poi il nostro sguardo verso la profondità del dipinto, lungo aree di luce, dai campi in cui il lino è stato steso per farlo scolorire, fino al San Bavone, che sorge in lontananza.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="fr-fr">Dans ce tableau, Van Ruisdael a capté l’essence du paysage néerlandais. Depuis la hauteur d’une dune, on regarde au-delà de l’étendue plate, en direction de Haarlem, la ville que l’on aperçoit au loin. Au-dessus de cette ville, s’étire un ciel immense avec des nuages à la dérive. Van Ruisdael peint le soleil qui brille entre les nuages, en faisant alterner la lumière et l’ombre. Il dirige notre regard le long des zones ensoleillées, vers la profondeur du tableau, depuis les champs où le linge est étalé à blanchir jusqu’à l’église Saint-Bavon au loin.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1670 - 1675 </dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="de-de">In diesem Gemälde fing van Ruisdael das Wesen der holländischen Landschaft ein. Von einem hohen Punkt in den Dünen schauen wir über das flache Land auf eine in der Ferne liegende Stadt, Haarlem. Darüber dehnt sich ein weiter Himmel mit vorbeiziehenden Wolkenbergen. Van Ruisdael hielt auch die Sonnenstrahlen fest, die durch die Wolken dringen und abwechselnd Licht und Schatten erzeugen. Über die hellen Partien lenkt er unseren Blick ins Bildinnere, über die Felder, wo Leinen zum Bleichen ausgebreitet liegt, bis hin zur fernen St. Bavo Kirche.</dc:description><dcterms:extent xml:lang="nl-nl">height, hoogte 73 cm, cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Jacob van Ruisdael</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/mauritshuis/155"><edm:isShownBy>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0155_repro/1000</edm:isShownBy><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Mauritshuis</edm:dataProvider><edm:object>https://media.delving.org/thumbnail/dcn/mauritshuis/0155_repro/1000</edm:object><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/mauritshuis/155"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>