<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2832"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1968</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">"Touch Cinema" is the video registration of a performance by VALIE EXPORT at Karlplatz (Stachus) in Munich. On her chest, the artist is wearing a polystyrene box, the front of which has an opening draped with curtains, and designed to resemble a cinema. Peter Weibel, from the inner circle of the Vienna-based group Wiener Aktionismus, assists by shouting into a megaphone, inviting the audience to touch the artist’s breasts for 33 seconds. The performance was considered transgressive at the time because of its erotic and sexual nature. The artist uses this act to point out and criticize the ways in which women’s bodies are objectified in the film industry. 'VALIE EXPORT is an Austrian feminist artist and activist. She was close to Vienna Actionism artists such as Herman Nitsch and Günter Brus, although she considered her work to be distinct from the movement. She worked in the film industry from 1965 to 1968. In 1967 she changed her name to VALIE EXPORT (written in capitals) as both an act of self-determination and as an act of rebellion against the patriarchal system. '"Touch Cinema" relates to other films that the artist made in the 1960s and 1970s. VALIE EXPORT defines these films as "Expanded Cinema", which aims to challenge the traditional medium, presenting avant-garde ideas on rethinking cinematic aesthetics and settings (for instance in the street or on stage). '-2019</dc:description><dc:creator>VALIE EXPORT</dc:creator><dc:title>Touch Cinema</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">16 mm film overgezet op video (PAL, zwart-wit, geluid)</dc:type><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:01:08</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">‘Touch Cinema’ is de videoregistratie van een performance van VALIE EXPORT op het Karlplatz (Stachus) in München. Op haar borst draagt de kunstenaar een piepschuim doos, die aan de voorzijde open is. Er hangt een gordijntje voor, zodat het lijkt op een bioscooptheater. Peter Weibel, uit de gelederen van het Wiener Aktionismus, helpt door in een megafoon te schreeuwen en het publiek uit te nodigen de borsten van de kunstenaar 33 seconden aan te raken. De performance werd destijds, vanwege het erotische en seksuele karakter als grensoverschrijdend beschouwd. De kunstenaar wil met de performance de manieren waarop vrouwenlichamen in de filmindustrie worden geobjectiveerd ter discussie stellen. 'VALIE EXPORT is een Oostenrijkse feministische kunstenaar en activist. Ze stond dichtbij Weense actionisten als Herman Nitsch en Günter Brus, maar heeft zich nooit echt met die beweging vereenzelvigd. Van 1965 tot 1968 werkte ze in de filmindustrie. In 1967 veranderde ze haar naam in VALIE EXPORT (in hoofdletters) als daad van zelfbeschikking en van rebellie tegen het patriarchale systeem. '‘Touch Cinema’ verwijst naar andere films die de kunstenaar in de jaren ’60 en ’70 maakte. VALIE EXPORT definieert deze films als ‘expanded cinema’ die tegen de traditionele cinema ingaan en avantgardistische ideeën bieden die aanleiding kunnen zijn om opnieuw na te denken over de esthetiek en de locaties (bijvoorbeeld de straat of het toneel) van films. '-2019</dc:description><dc:date>1968</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">16 mm film transferred to video (PAL, black-and-white, sound), duration 1:08 min.</dc:type><dc:identifier>2832</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2832"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C5689"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2832"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2832.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2832.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>