<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2831"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2831"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2831.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C5688"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2831.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2831"><dc:description xml:lang="en">"Cutting" is the video registration of a performance that took place at Underground Explosion in Munich. A large sheet of paper onto which we can see the projected image of a building façade appears on the screen. VALIE EXPORT places herself behind the sheet of paper and carefully cuts out the following message: "The content of writing is speech". In the second part of the video, the artist cuts the clothes and body hair of an immobile man. The artist uses these two acts to pay homage to media theorist Marshall McLuhan and to Bazooka Joe, a famous comic strip character. The title echoes the act of cutting in its literal sense, i.e. using sharp objects, and refers as well to its more metaphorical meaning: the act of editing or montage in the filmmaking process. 'VALIE EXPORT is an Austrian feminist artist and activist. She was close to Vienna Actionism artists such as Herman Nitsch and Günter Brus, although she considered her work to be distinct from the movement. She worked in the film industry from 1965 to 1968. In 1967 she changed her name to VALIE EXPORT (written in capitals) as both an act of self-determination and as an act of rebellion against the patriarchal system. '"Cutting" relates to other films that the artist made in the 1960s and 1970s. VALIE EXPORT defines these films as "Expanded Cinema", which aims to challenge the traditional medium, presenting avant-garde ideas on rethinking cinematic aesthetics and settings (for instance in the street or on stage). '-2019</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (PAL, zwart-wit, geluid)</dc:type><dc:creator>VALIE EXPORT</dc:creator><dc:identifier>2831</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:01:41</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Cutting</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="nl">‘Cutting’ is de videoregistratie van een performance die plaatsvond in Underground Explosion in München. Op het scherm verschijnt een grootstuk papier waarop de façade van een gebouw wordt geprojecteerd. VALIE EXPORT neemt plaats achter het vel papier en begint langzaam te knippen om de volgende boodschap te vormen: ‘De inhoud van het schrijven is het spreken.’ In het tweede deel van de video knipt de kunstenaar de kleren en het haar van een man. Deze twee acties zijn een eerbetoon van de kunstenaar aan de media-theoreticus/filosoof Marshall McLuhan en aan Bazooka Joe, een bekende stripfiguur. De titel is een echo van het knippen in letterlijke zin, met scherpe voorwerpen, maar verwijst ook naar een meer metaforische betekenis: de handeling van het knippen in filmmateriaal, de montage als onderdeel van het filmproces. 'VALIE EXPORT is een Oostenrijkse feministische kunstenaar en activist. Ze stond dichtbij Weense actionisten als Herman Nitsch en Günter Brus, maar heeft zich nooit echt met die beweging vereenzelvigd. Van 1965 tot 1968 werkte ze in de filmindustrie. In 1967 veranderde ze haar naam in VALIE EXPORT (in hoofdletters) als daad van zelfbeschikking en van rebellie tegen het patriarchale systeem. '‘Cutting’ verwijst naar andere films die de kunstenaar in de jaren ’60 en ’70 maakte. VALIE EXPORT definieert deze films als ‘expanded cinema’ die tegen de traditionele cinema ingaan en avantgardistische ideeën bieden die aanleiding kunnen zijn om opnieuw na te denken over de esthetiek en de locaties (bijvoorbeeld de straat of het toneel) van films. '-2019</dc:description><dcterms:created>1967-1968</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1967-1968</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (PAL, black-and-white, sound), duration 1:41 min.</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>