<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3105"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3105"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3105-03.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C9696"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3105-03.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3105"><dc:title>Model 'Ship of Tolerance'</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>2006</dc:date><dcterms:created>2006</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>3105</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">bamboo, hotmelt, rope, textile</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">This is a scale model of the 'Ship of Tolerance', an international art project by the acclaimed artist couple Ilya and Emilia Kabakov. This widely praised project helps children with different backgrounds and nationalities to become acquainted with other cultures and identities. ' The children are invited to attend a workshop hosted by local artists to broaden their cultural and creative horizon. They discuss other cultures and ideas about tolerance and hope. In conclusion they each make a painting on a piece of sail canvas. All the pieces are then stitched together into a giant sail. ' The school children will meet young carpentry students from Manchester and watch how they build a copy of an ancient Egyptian sailing ship. In conclusion, the gigantic sail will be hoisted and the ship will be launched. ' Previous interpretations of this ongoing project have taken place in Siwa, Venice, San Moritz, Sharjah, Miami, Havana, New York, Moscow, Zug, Capalbio, Rome, Rostock, Palermo and London.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">bamboe, hotmelt, touw, textiel</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit is een modelformaat van 'Ship of Tolerance', een internationaal kunstproject van het kunstenaarsduo Ilya en Emilia Kabakov. In dit gevierde project maken kinderen met uiteenlopende achtergronden en nationaliteiten op een levendige manier kennis met verschillende culturen en identiteiten. ' De kinderen krijgen een workshop van lokale kunstenaars om hun culturele, creatieve horizon te verbreden. Ze voeren gesprekken over andere culturen en ideeën, over tolerantie en hoop. Uiteindelijk maken ze allen een schildering op een stuk zeildoek, dat tot een groot zeil aan elkaar gestikt wordt. ' De schoolkinderen ontmoeten jonge timmerleerlingen uit Manchester en kunnen aanschouwen hoe deze een oud Egyptisch zeilschip nabouwen. Uiteindelijk wordt het gigantische zeil gehesen en de boot ter water gelaten. ' Dit on-going project heeft reeds plaatsgevonden in Siwa, Venetië, San Moritz, Sharjah, Miami, Havana, New York, Moscow, Zug, Capalbio, Rome, Rostock, Palermo en London.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>115 x 186 x 52 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Ilya &amp; Emilia Kabakov</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>