<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2573"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2573.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2573.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2573"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2874"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2573"><dc:creator>John Baldessari</dc:creator><dc:date>1971</dc:date><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:32:40</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (PAL, black-and-white, sound), duration 32:40 min.</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1971</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this exercise in associative meaning and word/image conjoinment, Baldessari pins a sequence of photographs to a wall below the ‘headline’ Art Disaster, which has been torn from a newspaper. While some of the photos are clear, others are illegible. The viewer reads the images in relation to the headline, struggling to derive meaning from each arbitrary juxtaposition. An absurd montage, a kind of disjointed narrative, emerges from the incongruities: a photograph of an empty bench precedes a photograph of a palm tree; a self-portrait of Cézanne is juxtaposed with a photograph of a butter pat in a dish. Exploiting the linguistic principles of metaphor and metonymy, Baldessari allows the viewer to interpret along two lines: vertically, from Art Disaster to picture below, or horizontally, from picture to picture. As demonstrated by the wonderfully surrealist narrative sequences that result, Baldessari encourages unconscious associations and subliminal meanings to emerge from the juxtaposition of found objects.</dc:description><dc:title>Art Disaster</dc:title><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>2573</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (PAL, zwart-wit, geluid)</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In deze oefening in associatieve betekenis en koppeling van woord en beeld prikt Baldessari een reeks foto's op een wand onder de uit een krant gescheurde ‘kop’ Art Disaster. Sommige van de foto's zijn duidelijk, andere zijn niet te ontcijferen. De toeschouwer leest de foto's in relatie tot de kop en doet moeite om de betekenis te achterhalen van alle willekeurige combinaties. Vanuit de ongerijmdheden ontstaat een absurde montage, een soort onsamenhangend verhaal: op een foto van een lege bank volgt een foto van een palmboom; een zelfportret van Cézanne wordt geplaatst naast een foto van een klontje boter op een schaal. Met gebruikmaking van de taalkundige principes metafoor en metonymie stelt Baldessari de toeschouwer in staat de combinaties op twee manieren te interpreteren: verticaal van Art Disaster naar de foto eronder of horizontaal van foto naar foto. Zoals duidelijk wordt uit de surrealistische narratieve sequenties die daaruit voortvloeien, stimuleert Baldessari met deze combinatie van gevonden voorwerpen de vorming van onbewuste associaties en onderbewuste betekenissen.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>