<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2348"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2348"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2348.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2498"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2348.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2348"><dc:date>1996</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="nl">hout, diverse voorwerpen, geluid</dc:type><dc:title>Hok II</dc:title><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Suchan Kinoshita</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1996</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Shed II' by Suchan Kinoshita consists of two interlinked spaces. In the first space, which does not give a view of what there is in the second, there is an hourglass. A number of collections are exhibited in the second space. There is a display case with spiders in formaldehyde. In another display case there are matchboxes with rolls of paper with writing rolled round a match inside them. In this display case there are photographs of people, not showing the head. There are socks and gloves hanging on hooks on a sheet of softboard and no two are alike. There are large slides of heads with their mouths open so wide that the throat is visible, hanging on a line and there are sheets of paper hanging on the wall, noting the time. There is also a cupboard with a speaker projecting the sounds of people sleeping, and there is a telephone hanging up which produces the sounds of eating when you pick up the phone. 'This installation by Kinoshita was largely based on autobiographical elements. The sounds of sleeping and eating were made by her children. The photographs of the people are of herself and of her husband taken by her daughter. The slides of the throats are part of the inheritance of her father, who was a professional voice coach. The single socks and gloves are remainders of Kinoshita’s household. The rolls of paper contain diary notes which she wrote and the sheets of paper with the times are notes of the time at which the light went on or off in the premises that she looked out onto when she lived in Luik. 'Kinoshita’s intention was to provide the visitor with an intense experience. She achieved this by appealing to the different senses, inviting the visitor to participate actively, for example, by answering the telephone or by the fact that only a few people can enter the intimate space at the same time. The first virtually empty space arouses curiosity, but the second is a sort of cabinet of rarities that also has a slightly domestic atmosphere. Kinoshita appeals to feelings of expectation and recognition. By looking at all sorts of personal fascinations, she wanted to put her public onto the track of a conscious experience of the environment in which both futile everyday matters, as well as very specialized activities, can be observed.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">wooden, various objects, sound</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Hok II' van Suchan Kinoshita bestaat uit twee onderling verbonden ruimtes. In de eerste ruimte, die geen zicht biedt op wat er zich in de tweede bevindt, staat een zandloper. In de tweede ruimte wordt een aantal verzamelingen getoond. Er staat een vitrine met spinnen op sterk water. In een andere liggen luciferdoosjes met daarin beschreven rolletjes papier, gedraaid om een lucifer. Op deze vitrine staan foto's van personen waarvan het hoofd buiten beeld valt. Aan een zachtboardplaat met haakjes hangen sokken en handschoenen waarvan er geen twee gelijk zijn. Aan een lijntje hangen grootbeelddia's van hoofden met de mond zo wijd opengesperd dat de keelholte zichtbaar is. Er hangen vellen papier aan een wand waarop tijdstippen zijn genoteerd. Verder is er een kastje met een speaker waaruit slaapgeluiden klinken, en hangt er een telefoon die eetgeluiden laat horen wanneer je hem opneemt. 'Deze installatie van Kinoshita is grotendeels gebaseerd op autobiografische elementen. De slaap- en eetgeluiden komen van haar kinderen. De foto's van personen betreffen haarzelf en haar man, gemaakt door haar dochtertje. De dia's van keelholtes komen uit de nalatenschap van haar vader, die zich beroepsmatig bezig hield met de vorming van de stem. De sokken en handschoenen zijn overgebleven eenlingen uit Kinoshita's huishouden. De rolletjes papier bevatten door haar geschreven dagboekachtige notities. De vellen papier met tijdstippen zijn noteringen van het moment waarop het licht aan of uit ging in het pand waarop zij uitkeek toen ze in Luik woonde. 'Het is Kinoshita's bedoeling de bezoeker een intense ervaring te laten ondergaan. Dit bewerkstelligt zij door een beroep te doen op verschillende zintuigen. Ze nodigt uit tot actieve deelname door bijvoorbeeld het opnemen van de telefoonhoorn en door het feit dat slechts enkele personen tegelijk de intieme ruimte kunnen betreden. Het eerste vrijwel lege hok wekt nieuwsgierigheid. Het tweede is een soort rariteitenkabinet dat tevens iets huiselijks heeft. Kinoshita appelleert aan gevoelens van verwachting en herkenning. Via een blik op allerlei persoonlijke fascinaties wil zij haar publiek op het spoor zetten van een bewuste ervaring van de leefomgeving, waarin zowel alledaagse futiele zaken als zeer gespecialiseerde waar te nemen zijn.</dc:description><dc:identifier>2348</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>