<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2945"><dc:description xml:lang="en">Working on a liveable and sustainable city. 'The photo prints show the barrier islands and the wetlands. For New Orleans they form important natural defenses against storms and floods. But this territory is sinking. Marjetica Potrč researched grassroots initiatives in New Orleans following the devastating hurricane Katrina in 2005, and she notes: “Citizens are the ones who make the city.” In the drawings, Potrč maps community strategies used to manage the living space and the water. Key words are sustainability and the return to traditional housing (the shotgun house). By rainwater harvesting, the strain on the soil and on the sewage system is relieved. The rainwater can be recycled in the housekeeping. Potrč argues that, after the collapse of 20th century modernism’s version of “progress”, there will be more room for new initiatives based on local traditions.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">inkjet print op papier, inkttekening op papier</dc:type><dc:identifier>2945</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>65,7 x 85,7 x 3,8 cm (incl. lijst / frame) 66,3 x 85,6 x 3,8 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>2007</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:title>New Orleans: Settlement and Return to Archetypes</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Werken aan een leefbare en duurzame stad. ' De fotoprints tonen de barrière-eilanden en wetlands. Voor New Orleans vormen zij belangrijke natuurlijke beschermingslinies tegen storm en vloedgolven. Maar dit gebied is zinkende. Marjetica Potrč deed onderzoek naar burgerinitiatieven in New Orleans na de verwoestende orkaan Katrina in 2005 en constateert: “Stadbewoners zijn degenen die de stad maken.” In de tekeningen brengt Potrč lokale strategieën om de leefruimte en het water te beheren in kaart. Sleutelwoorden zijn duurzaamheid en de terugkeer naar traditionele huizenbouw (de shotgun house). Door regenwater op te vangen worden de grond en het riool minder belast. Het regenwater kan hergebruikt worden in het huishouden. Potrč stelt, dat na de ineenstorting van het 20e-eeuwse moderne idee van ‘vooruitgang’, er ruimte komt voor nieuwe initiatieven gebaseerd op lokale tradities.</dc:description><dc:creator>Marjetica Potrc</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">ink, inkjet print on paper</dc:type><dc:date>2007</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2945"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2945"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2945-1-1.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C8085"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2945-1-1.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>