<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2580"><dcterms:created>1972</dcterms:created><dc:creator>John Baldessari</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (PAL, zwart-wit, geluid)</dc:type><dc:identifier>2580</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">In a sly twist on the methodology of the 18th-century "philosophes" who classified the laws and history of the world in massive encyclopedias, Baldessari devises and then subverts his own system for cataloguing the world. In a matter-of-fact tone, he states that he is going to present a precise, methodical inventory of objects, progressing from small to large in size. Drawing on his own collection of found objects, he exhibits and describes a seemingly arbitrary series of over thirty disparate items: a small glass bead, a nut, a dried orange peel, an artificial flower, a cigarette pack, toy money, a utility belt, a shoe tree. Stripped of any frame of reference — color, scale — the objects are virtually unidentifiable as the things Baldessari says they are. Without visual perception or cognition, the viewer relies on Baldessari's voiceover description to supply the objects' meaning. Therein, he suggests, lies the critical paradox: By undermining the viewer's empirical perception, video ultimately is proven to be a flawed medium for the indexing and classification of the world.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:23:50</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In een ironische variant op de methodiek van de 18de-eeuwse ‘philosophes’ die de wetten en geschiedenis van de wereld rubriceerden in omvangrijke encyclopedieën, bedenkt en ondergraaft Baldessari zijn eigen systeem voor het catalogiseren van de wereld. Op zakelijke toon meldt hij dat hij een nauwkeurige, methodische inventarisatie van objecten gaat geven, van klein naar groot. Hij toont en beschrijft een schijnbaar willekeurige reeks van meer dan dertig uiteenlopende objecten, waarbij hij put uit zijn eigen verzameling van gevonden voorwerpen: een kleine glazen kraal, een noot, een gedroogde sinaasappelschil, een kunstbloem, een pakje sigaretten, speelgoedgeld, een gereedschapsgordel, een schoenspanner etc. Zonder enig referentiekader – kleur, schaal – zijn de objecten vrijwel niet herkenbaar als de dingen die Baldessari beweert dat ze zijn. Zonder visuele waarneming of begripsvorming gaat de toeschouwer af op de beschrijving van Baldessari's voice-over om de betekenis van de objecten te achterhalen. Daarin zit, zo suggereert de kunstenaar, een cruciale paradox besloten: door de empirische waarneming van de toeschouwer te ondermijnen wordt volgens hem aangetoond dat video een gebrekkig medium is voor het indexeren en classificeren van de wereld.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Inventory</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (PAL, black-and-white, sound), duration 23:50 min.</dc:type><dc:date>1972</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2580"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2580"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2881"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2580-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2580-01.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>