<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3058"><dcterms:extent>(558x) 26 x 18 cm (81x) 31 x 138,5 x 3 cm (incl lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="en">Sara Sejin Chang (Sara van der Heide) started her series of cabinets on 14 October 2010, the day of the installation of the government of Prime Minister Mark Rutte, a combination of VVD, CDA supported by the populist right-wing Freedom Party (PVV). Everyday, she makes a drawing of another ‘Hollands Kabinet’. Hollands Kabinet is a colloquial term for the Dutch government, but also the name for a traditional Dutch storage cabinet. The collection of cabinets grew daily and became more varied with every day and every drawing. With the fall of the Rutte government on April 23, 2012, the work has reached its final form and the 558th Cabinet was added that day. 'The pluriform nature of the Dutch history is shown through the history of these examples of the Dutch cabinet. The wood cabinet has its origin in Asia and, via the influence of Moorish culture in Spain, found its way to Holland around 1600. Most of these cabinets were fabricated in Holland using Dutch oak, but there are also many examples of cabinets produced with ‘exotic’ wood. Additionally, and during Dutch colonial times, cabinets were also made in former colonies, for example in the Cape of Good Hope (currently South Africa); Ceylon (currently India); Batavia (currently Indonesia and Sri Lanka), Curacao and New York. These silent witnesses of the personal and national history of the Netherlands have been present for centuries in many Dutch households and were (and sometimes still are) passed on from generation to generation. '[exhibition text 2012]</dc:description><dc:identifier>3058</dc:identifier><dc:title>Hollands Kabinet</dc:title><dc:date>2010-2012</dc:date><dc:creator>Sara Sejin Chang (Sara van der Heide)</dc:creator><dcterms:created>2010-2012</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">watercolour on paper</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het seriële werk 'Hollands Kabinet' begon op 14 oktober 2010 – de dag dat het minderheidskabinet Rutte met gedoogsteun van de PVV werd geïnstalleerd. Vanaf die dag maakte Sara Sejin Chang (Sara van der Heide) elke dag een tekening van een Hollands kabinet. Hollands kabinet is een oudhollands bergmeubel, maar wordt ook gebruikt om de Nederlandse regering mee aan te duiden. De verzameling kabinetten groeide dagelijks en werd met elke dag en elke tekening gevarieerder. Met de val van het kabinet op 23 april 2012 heeft het werk zijn definitieve vorm bereikt, Kabinet 558 is die dag toegevoegd. 'Het pluriforme van de Nederlandse geschiedenis kan men terug vinden in de geschiedenis van het Hollands kabinet. De oorsprong van het meubelstuk ligt in Azië en het is via de Moorse cultuur in Spanje omstreeks 1600 in Nederland terecht gekomen. De meeste Hollandse kabinetten zijn van eikenhout vervaardigd, later kwamen daar kabinetten gemaakt met exotische houtsoorten bij. In de serie tekeningen is ook een heel aantal kabinetten opgenomen die in de voormalige koloniën zijn geproduceerd, zoals in Kaap de Goede Hoop (Zuid-Afrika); Ceylon (tegenwoordig Sri Lanka en India), Curacao en New York. Deze stille getuigen van de persoonlijke en nationale geschiedenis van Nederland zijn al eeuwenlang een belangrijk meubelstuk in de Nederlandse huishoudens en zijn of worden soms nog steeds van generatie op generatie doorgegeven. '[tentoonstellingstekst 2012]</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">aquarel op papier</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3058"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C9388"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3058-001.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3058"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3058-001.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>