<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2601"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2601"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2601.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2601.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2982"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2601"><dc:title>Provisional floor plan 'Self-portrait as a building'</dc:title><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>46,5 x 66,7 cm 56,7 x 73,8 x 3 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Mark Manders</dc:creator><dc:identifier>2601</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">pencil, felt-tip pen on paper</dc:type><dcterms:created>1996</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Toen Mark Manders achttien was begon hij aan zijn project ‘Self-Portrait as a Building’. Deze plattegrond is een van de vele onderdelen die samen het zelfportret vormen. Hij wilde zich eerst uiten in woorden maar “Ik hou niet van het idee om geschreven zinnen te gebruiken om het publiek te dicteren wat ze precies moeten denken.” Om het niet te persoonlijk te maken wil Manders het abstract houden. Aan de hand van de plattegrond kan iedereen eigen gedachten construeren. Het resultaat is een zelfportret dat afhangt van zowel de maker als de toeschouwer.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">potlood, viltstift op papier</dc:type><dc:date>1996</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">When Mark Manders was eighteen years old, he started his project ‘Self-Portrait as a Building’. This floor plan was one of the many elements that as a whole comprise a self-portrait. Manders wanted to express himself in words first, but says he ‘did not like the idea of using written sentences to dictate to the audience exactly what they should think’. In order to keep the work from becoming too personal, Manders keeps it abstract. On the basis of the floor plan anyone can construct their own thoughts. The result is a self-portrait that depends on both the creator and the spectator.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>