<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3135"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C10081"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3135-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3135-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3135"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3135"><dcterms:created>1988</dcterms:created><dc:title>My Conscience Tormenting Me</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">Solakov donated this painting in 2013 and wrote the following notes to accompany the work: "Before 1989, the year when the so-called ‘changes’ began, I made two paintings which addressed metaphorically the subject of my work ‘Top Secret’ . One was ‘Repentance’, 1987, that belongs to the National Art Gallery in Sofia. The other is the work in front of you ‘My Conscience Tormenting Me’. At that time it was unthinkable to openly say, draw or paint about the fact that I used to have contact with the Bulgarian Secret Service. I would have been sent to jail. 'This painting is very precious to me and my family, but I knew that the best place for this work was with ‘Top Secret’ and the accompanying video. That is why I have decided to donate the painting to Van Abbemuseum. Of course, my conscience is still tormenting me on other, more democratic subjects." 'See also the work 'Top Secret' by Solakov on our website.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil, graphite on canvas</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf en grafiet op doek</dc:type><dcterms:extent>72,9 x 92 x 3 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Nedko Solakov</dc:creator><dc:date>1988</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Solakov schonk dit schilderij in 2013 en schreef de volgende toelichting bij het werk: “Vóór 1989, het jaar waarin de zogenaamde ‘veranderingen’ begonnen, heb ik twee schilderijen gemaakt die het onderwerp van mijn werk ‘Top Secret’ symboliseerden. Het ene was ‘Repentance’, uit 1987, dat in bezit is van de National Art Gallery in Sofia. Het andere is het werk dat u hier ziet: ‘My Conscience Tormenting Me’. Het was in die tijd ondenkbaar om openlijk iets te zeggen, te tekenen of te schilderen over mijn vroegere contacten met de Bulgaarse Geheime Dienst. Dan was ik zeker naar de gevangenis gestuurd. Dit schilderij is mij en mijn familie zeer dierbaar, maar ik wist dat het beter tot zijn recht zou komen naast ‘Top Secret’ en de bijbehorende video. Daarom heb ik ervoor gekozen om het schilderij aan het Van Abbemuseum te schenken. Overigens knaagt mijn geweten nog steeds, maar nu gaat het over andere, meer democratische onderwerpen.” 'Bekijk ook het werk 'Top Secret' van Solakov op onze website.</dc:description><dc:identifier>3135</dc:identifier><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>