<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3157"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3157-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C10158"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3157"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3157-01.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3157"><dc:creator>René Daniëls</dc:creator><dc:date>2007</dc:date><dcterms:created>2007</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">This drawing depicts various motifs that often recur in René Daniëls’s post-2006 work. The vertical black mark on the right that resembles a person also appears in "Z.T.", 2006. The stand holding several microphones can be traced back to paintings from 1987. Daniëls has been putting words around these since 2006. The words ‘naakt’ (naked), ‘24 uur’ (24 hours) and ‘twee ling' (twins/Gemini) are frequently repeated. Daniëls’s star sign is Gemini. He adds his birthday, 23 May, to this drawing. The oval shape at the top of the picture has also appeared in several of his works since 2006. A small circle is connected by lines to a larger circle, on which the word ‘aarde’ (Earth) is written. The black figure seems to be connected by lines to the large globe in this drawing. However, at the same time he is standing on the outside. The question arises as to whether in this picture Daniëls is reflecting on his own position in relation to the world. Since he suffered his 1987 brain haemorrhage, which resulted in aphasia, it has been difficult to communicate with him. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>z.t.</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf, viltstift op doek</dc:type><dcterms:extent>30 x 40,5 x 2 cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Op deze tekening zijn diverse motieven te zien die vaak terugkeren in het werk van René Daniëls na 2006. De verticale, zwarte vlek rechts in beeld lijkt op een persoon en komt ook voor in 'Z.T.', 2006. De standaard met een aantal microfoons is terug te voeren op schilderijen uit 1987. Vanaf 2006 zet Daniëls er woorden omheen. De woorden ‘naakt’, ‘24 uur’ en ‘twee ling’ komen vaak voor. Daniëls’ sterrenbeeld is tweelingen. In deze tekening zet hij zijn geboortedag, 23 mei, erbij. Ook de ovale vorm bovenin het beeld is in veel werk vanaf 2006 aanwezig. Een kleine cirkel is via lijnen verbonden met een grotere cirkel, die voorzien is van het woord ‘aarde’. De zwarte figuur lijkt via lijnen verbonden te zijn met de grote wereldbol in deze tekening. Maar hij staat er tegelijkertijd buiten. De vraag dient zich aan of Daniëls hier reflecteert op zijn eigen positie ten opzichte van de wereld. Sinds hij getroffen werd door een hersenbloeding in 1987, met afasie als gevolg, is het moeilijk om met hem te communiceren. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil &amp; felt marker on canvas</dc:type><dc:identifier>3157</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>