<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3158"><dc:date>2007</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">At the end of 1987, René Daniëls suffered a brain haemorrhage from which he would never fully recover. He lost the use of his right hand, the one he used to draw and paint with, and suffered from aphasia, so he was no longer able to talk. He learned to communicate through gestures and nods and complemented this by drawing or writing down a few words with his left hand. He also sketched and made notes for himself every day. He started painting again in 2006. In his previous series of works from 1987, under the heading "Lentebloezem" (Spring Blossom), Daniels painted titles of his earlier paintings as blossom on branching lines. They form a kind of inventory of his oeuvre. It is here that he picks up from where he left off. Around the tree in the middle of the work shown here he writes the words E'ven and A'dam, which he had used previously on an invitation card and in paintings. These abbreviations for the cities of Eindhoven and Amsterdam, also sound like Eve and Adam, or even in A’dam. The caption ‘The Most Contemporary Picture Show’ is the title of a painting from 1983. In the top left and bottom left corners, we can see two shapes each with a half shaded black. They allude to previously painted motifs by Daniëls: the film camera and the bow tie/room motif (see various other works by Daniëls). In the bottom right corner, we can see the silhouette of a figure looking at all this. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:title>z.t.</dc:title><dcterms:created>2007</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">felt marker on canvas</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">viltstift op doek</dc:type><dc:creator>René Daniëls</dc:creator><dc:identifier>3158</dc:identifier><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>40,3 x 40,2 x 2 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Eind 1987 wordt René Daniëls getroffen door een hersenbloeding, waarvan hij niet volledig herstelt. Hij kan zijn rechterhand, waarmee hij tekende en schilderde, niet meer gebruiken en kampt met afasie. Spreken is niet meer mogelijk voor hem. Hij communiceert via gebaren en knikken en als aanvulling hierop maakt hij met zijn linkerhand tekeningen of schrijft enkele woorden op. Ook voor zichzelf maakt hij dagelijks tekeningen en notities. Vanaf 2006 gaat hij weer schilderen. In zijn laatste serie werken uit 1987, onder de noemer 'Lentebloesem', schildert Daniëls titels van eerder werk als bloesems aan vertakkende lijnen. Ze vormen een soort inventarisatie van zijn oeuvre. Hier pakt hij deze draad weer op. Rond de boom in het midden van het hier getoonde werk schrijft hij de woorden E’ven en A’dam, die hij eerder gebruikte op een uitnodigingskaart en in schilderijen. Deze afkortingen voor de steden Eindhoven en Amsterdam, klinken ook als Eva en Adam, of even in A’dam. De tekst ‘The Most Contemporary Picture Show’ is de titel van een schilderij uit 1983. Linksboven en -onder vallen twee vormen op die half zwart zijn. Ze verwijzen naar eerder geschilderde motieven van Daniëls: de filmcamera en het vlinderstrik/zaalmotief (zie diverse andere werken van Daniëls). Rechts onder is het silhouet van een persoon te zien die naar dit alles kijkt. '[2020]</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3158"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3158-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3158"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C10159"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3158-01.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>