<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3196"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3196-04.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C9722"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3196"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3196-04.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3196"><dc:creator>Sheela Gowda</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>3196</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">Sheela Gowda became fascinated by the interaction of the formerly nomadic Hakki Pikki people with city dwellers. In order to survive in the Indian metropolis of Bangalore (India), they make use of their so-called ‘tribal’ identity. Protesting against the demolition of their houses, they present themselves consciously as generic ‘tribal’ people in order to attract attention. In fact, these former huntergatherers are now merchants and skilled forgers of hunting trophies, such as the cow-horn chain hanging from the wall print that is sold to city dwellers as tiger claw. Gowda presents the Hakki Pikki in the smaller image in the way a tourist or an urbanite might see them: as cliché versions of various native peoples from America, Africa, and New Zealand. This exaggerated yet banal image of indigenous peoples then throws our gaze back to the bigger image of real people using those same clichés to try to prevent the loss of their homes.</dc:description><dc:date>2011</dc:date><dcterms:created>2011</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">inkjet print on paper, watercolour on print, horn, fur</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Sheela Gowda raakte gefascineerd door de interactie tussen de voormalig nomadische stam de Hakki Pikki en stedelingen. Om te overleven in de metropool Bangalore (India) benutten zij hun zogenoemde ‘tribale’ identiteit. Voor het protest tegen de sloop van hun woningen presenteren zij zich bewust als ‘tribaal’ volk om aandacht te vragen. Deze voormalige jager-verzamelaars zijn nu handelaren en kundige vervalsers van jachttrofeeën. De koehoornketting die aan de wandprint hangt, wordt aan stedelingen verkocht als zijnde tijgerklauwen. Gowda presenteert in het kleinere toegevoegde beeld de Hakki Pikki zoals de toerist hen mogelijk ziet: als cliché-versies van verscheidene inheemse volkeren van Amerika, Afrika en Nieuw Zeeland. Dit overdreven doch banale beeld van oorspronkelijke volkeren brengt onze blik terug naar het grotere beeld van echte mensen die dezelfde clichés gebruiken om het verlies van hun woningen te voorkomen.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">inkjet print op papier, aquarel op print, hoorn, bont</dc:type><dc:title>Protest, my son</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>