<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2626"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2626-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C3023"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2626-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2626"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2626"><dc:title>Balcony</dc:title><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">ijzer, verf</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:date>1991</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Balcony' by the Spanish artist Juan Muñoz is a small iron balcony attached high up on the wall. It is often combined with another work by Muñoz, 'Listening figure'. This is a rocking bronze character who is listening with his ear against the wall. The character behaves like a person, although you can see immediately that it is not an “ordinary” person. He is smaller and his legs are replaced by a hemisphere. 'Muñoz usually creates works consisting of different elements in which the space around and between these elements plays an important role. Initially he often paints the floor of the gallery where he places his objects so that it becomes part of the work. In 'Listening figure with Balcony', the wall has the same sort of function, even though it is not painted. Through this wall, the whole exhibition gallery is involved in the work. In a sense, a visitor who enters this space also becomes part of it. However, at the same time, he remains at a distance, not literally, but metaphorically. Muñoz’s figures do not actually communicate with the viewer; they are engrossed in their own affairs. Muñoz’s figures seem to record a moment in a particular event. The viewer does not know what has happened or what is going to happen, but it is clear that something is going on. 'Muñoz aims to bring about a feeling of tension and uncertainty in the viewer, confronting him with a recognizable but not quite realistic scene. He plays around with the concepts of presence and absence, proximity and distance. The figure that is physically present in Listening figure does not face the viewer. Someone could appear on the empty balcony. The visitor is present at the scene, but cannot participate in what is happening; he can only guess at it. In this way, Muñoz gives the viewer the opportunity to interpret the work in his own way.</dc:description><dc:creator>Juan Muñoz</dc:creator><dc:identifier>2626</dc:identifier><dcterms:created>1991</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">iron, paint</dc:type><dcterms:extent>85 x 71 x 44,5 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Balcony' van de Spaanse kunstenaar Juan Muñoz is een ijzeren balkonnetje dat hoog aan de wand bevestigd is. Het wordt vaak gecombineerd met een ander werk van Muñoz, 'Listening figure'. Dit is een bronzen tuimelaar die zijn oor te luisteren legt tegen dezelfde wand. De tuimelaar gedraagt zich als mens, hoewel je meteen ziet dat het niet om een 'gewoon' mens gaat: hij is kleiner van gestalte en zijn benen zijn vervangen door een halve bol. 'Muñoz maakt meestal werken die uit verschillende elementen bestaan en waarin de ruimte rondom en tussen die elementen een belangrijke rol speelt. Aanvankelijk beschildert Muñoz dikwijls de vloer van de zaal waarin hij zijn objecten plaatst. Zo wordt deze onderdeel van het werk. In 'Listening figure with Balcony' vervult de wand een zelfde soort functie, al is hij niet beschilderd. Via de wand wordt de hele expositieruimte betrokken bij het werk. De bezoeker die de ruimte betreedt, wordt er in zekere zin ook onderdeel van. Tegelijkertijd blijft de bezoeker echter op afstand; niet letterlijk maar figuurlijk. Muñoz' figuren communiceren namelijk niet met de toeschouwer; ze zijn verdiept in hun eigen zaken. Muñoz' beelden lijken momentopnamen uit een gebeurtenis. De kijker weet niet precies wat er gebeurd is of wat er komen gaat, maar dat er iets gaande is, lijkt evident. 'Muñoz wil bij de beschouwer een gevoel van spanning en onzekerheid teweeg brengen. Hij confronteert hem met een herkenbaar maar net niet realistisch gegeven. Hij speelt met de begrippen aanwezigheid en afwezigheid, nabijheid en afstand. De fysiek aanwezige figuur in 'Listening figure' is niet op de kijker gericht. Op het het lege balkon zou iemand kunnen verschijnen. De bezoeker is ter plekke aanwezig, maar kan niet deelnemen aan wat er gaande is. Hij kan er slechts naar raden. Zo geeft Muñoz de kijker de mogelijkheid het werk op een eigen manier te interpreteren.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>