<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/22"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C365"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0022.JPG"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0022.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/22"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/22"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:identifier>22</dc:identifier><dc:date>1952</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">This work by the French painter Jean Bazaine consists of planes of colour. He used bright red, purple and blue colours, as well as an ochre, alternating with black. There is a broad band of white running diagonally across the middle of the canvas. This painting is an abstract representation of thunder. The diagonal band of white, which is interrupted, can be seen as a flash of lightning which casts a bright light over a garden of flowers and plants. The red, purple, blue and yellow colours in the painting refer to flowers and the large amount of black represents the darkness during the thunderstorm. The smaller areas of colour, sometimes collected in clusters, support the movement of the head. To the left and right, the image is separate from the edge of the painting. At the top and the bottom it appears to be cut off as though it is a fragment from a much larger work. 'Bazaine’s paintings and drawings are based on nature. However, he does not represent his themes in a naturalist manner. He evokes the theme in an abstract way with the use of colour, rhythm and movement. Bazaine believed that a painting should embody the essence of the universe. He did not wish to represent specific details, but rather wanted to paint the essence of natural phenomena such as the blowing of the wind or the flow of water. Although his paintings are abstract, he continued to make drawings and watercolours based on visual reality. In that way he wanted to prevent himself from working too systematically; in fact, he wished to remain open to nature so that he could constantly discover new aspects. 'In 1941 Bazaine organized an exhibition in Paris entitled 'Jeunes Peintres de Tradition Française'. This was intended to be a protest against the cultural policy of the German occupiers. The title indicated that the participating artists wished to continue the French tradition, but in a new way. After the Second World War, this group, which compromised Bissière, Poliakoff and Manessier, as well as Bazaine, was known as the École de Paris.</dc:description><dc:title>L'orage au jardin</dc:title><dcterms:created>1952</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit werk van de Franse schilder Jean Bazaine is opgebouwd uit kleurvlekken. Er zijn heldere rode, paarse en blauwe kleuren gebruikt en een okergeel, afgewisseld met zwart. In het midden van het doek loopt in diagonale richting een brede witte baan. Dit schilderij biedt een abstract beeld van onweer. De witte diagonale baan, die onderbroken wordt, kan gezien worden als een bliksemflits die een helder licht werpt over een tuin met bloemen en planten. De rode, paarse, blauwe en gele kleuren in het schilderij verwijzen naar bloemen. Het vele zwart representeert het duister tijdens het onweer. De kleinere kleurvlekken, soms in clusters bij elkaar gezet, ondersteunen de hoofdbeweging. Links en rechts staat het beeld los van de rand. Boven en onder lijkt het afgesneden, alsof het een fragment is uit een groter geheel. 'De schilderijen en tekeningen van Bazaine vinden hun oorsprong in de natuur. Hij geeft zijn thema's echter niet op een naturalistische wijze weer. Hij roept het thema op een abstracte manier op, door gebruik te maken van kleur, ritme en beweging. Bazaine vindt dat een schilderij het wezen van het universum moet belichamen. Hij wil geen specifieke details afbeelden, maar de essentie van natuurverschijnselen als het waaien van wind of het stromen van water schilderen. Hoewel zijn schilderijen abstract zijn, blijft hij tekenen en aquarelleren naar de zichtbare werkelijkheid. Hiermee wil hij voorkomen dat hij vervalt in een systematiek. Hij wil open blijven staan voor de natuur om daarin telkens nieuwe dingen te kunnen ontdekken. 'Bazaine organiseert in 1941 een tentoonstelling in Parijs met de titel 'Jeunes Peintres de Tradition Française'. Het is bedoeld als protest tegen de cultuurpolitiek van de Duitse bezetters. De titel geeft aan dat de deelnemende kunstenaars aansluiting zoeken bij de Franse traditie, maar daar een nieuwe vorm aan willen geven. Na de Tweede Wereldoorlog wordt deze groep - waartoe naast Bazaine o.m. Bissière, Poliakoff en Manessier behoren - aangeduid met de term École de Paris.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dcterms:extent>101,3 x 81,8 x 5 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Jean Bazaine</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>