<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1145"><dc:type xml:lang="en">pencil, ball-point pen ink on paper on canvas</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">This work by the Italian artist Alighiero e Boetti consists of four parts, which show the same image in each case but in a different colour. Each part comprises a sheet of paper glued onto canvas with small vertical dashes drawn in horizontal lines,. The artist used the colours blue black, red and green, and part of the paper was left white. The white part is in the form of a rectangular sheet of paper which is torn off at the bottom edge and has a small fold in the top right-hand corner. A rectangular gateway is drawn in the middle of this form with dashes. The work is entitled 'I quattro moli', the four piers and sometimes the words “Pier Piet” are added to this. 'From the late 1960s Alighiero e Boetti presented very stylistically diverse work and was classified as a member of the Arte Povera, a movement which often worked with materials not commonly used in art, varying from objects taken from nature, such as branches, to everyday manufactured products, such as neon tubes or pieces of graph paper. Boetti used the latter to make the work 'Cimento dell'armonia e dell'invenzione' in 1969, in which he traced the horizontal and vertical lines on the paper. Boetti said: “Therefore I had to measure myself with a very small thing which, despite everything, guaranteed me an exceptional individual freedom to act and an enormous opportunity for research and analysis.” In fact Boetti determined for himself which lines and how many of them he would trace. The use of rules or systems and the individual way in which they were adopted formed the basis of his work. 'For the work 'Ordine e disordine' Boetti instructed Afghan women to embroider the sixteen letters of the title, leaving them free to choose their own colours and consequently there was an enormous variety of work carried out, despite a rigidly defined starting point. Boetti often has his ideas carried out by others. The fact that he considered it unimportant to include the artists’ signature is also shown in his choice to sign Alighiero e Boetti as though they are two people. The parts of I quattro moli were also made by different people. With the suffix (Pier Piet), Boetti probably referred to Piet Mondrian's series of works called 'Pier and Ocean'. These works consists of horizontal and vertical stripes which cross over each other, the only directions permitted according to Mondrian’s rules. In his attempt to achieve universal art, Mondrian used his strict rules intuitively, just like the people who executed Boetti’s work. .</dc:description><dc:date>1982</dc:date><dcterms:extent>(4x) 75,2 x 71,6 x 2,7 cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit werk van de Italiaanse kunstenaar Alighiero e Boetti bestaat uit vier delen, die telkens hetzelfde beeld tonen in een andere kleur. Elk deel omvat een op doek geplakt vel papier, waarop kleine verticale streepjes in horizontale rijen zijn getekend. De kleuren blauw, zwart, rood of groen zijn gebruikt. Een deel van het papier blijft wit. Het witte deel heeft de vorm van een rechthoekig blad papier dat aan de onderrand is afgescheurd en in de rechter bovenhoek een klein vouwtje heeft. Middenin deze vorm is met streepjes een rechthoekige poort getekend. Het werk heeft de titel 'I quattro moli', de vier pieren. Soms wordt daar '(Pier Piet)' aan toegevoegd. 'Alighiero e Boetti presenteert sinds eind jaren '60 stilistisch heel divers werk. Het wordt tot de arte povera gerekend. Daarin wordt vaak gewerkt met in de kunst ongebruikelijke materialen, variërend van aan de natuur ontleende objecten, zoals takken, tot alledaagse, industrieel vervaardigde producten als neonbuizen of een stuk ruitjespapier. Met dit laatste maakt Boetti in 1969 het werk 'Cimento dell'armonia e dell'invenzione', dat bestaat uit het overtrekken van de horizontale en verticale lijntjes op het papier. Boetti zegt hierover: "Ik moest me dus meten met een heel klein ding dat mij, ondanks alles, een buitengewone, individuele vrijheid tot handelen waarborgde, een enorme mogelijkheid tot onderzoek en analyse." Boetti bepaalt namelijk zelf, welke lijntjes, en hoeveel hij er overtrekt. Het gebruik van regels of systemen, en de individuele hantering hiervan, vormen de basis van zijn werk. 'Voor het werk 'Ordine e disordine' geeft Boetti Afghaanse vrouwen de opdracht de 16 letters van deze titel te borduren. Ze zijn daarbij vrij in hun kleurkeuzen. Zo ontstaat er, ondanks een strak gedefinieerd uitgangspunt, een enorme variëteit aan uitvoeringen. Boetti laat zijn ideeën dikwijls door anderen uitvoeren. Dat hij het handschrift van de kunstenaar onbelangrijk vindt, spreekt mede uit zijn keuze te signeren met Alighiero e Boetti, alsof het om twee mensen gaat. Ook de delen van 'I quattro moli' zijn door verschillende personen gemaakt. Met het achtervoegsel (Pier Piet) verwijst Boetti naar de serie 'Pier en Oceaan' van Piet Mondriaan. Deze werken bestaan uit elkaar kruisende horizontale en verticale streepjes, de enige richtingen die volgens Mondriaans regels toegestaan zijn. In zijn streven naar een universele kunst, hanteert Mondriaan zijn stricte regels intuïtief, net als de uitvoerders van een werk van Boetti.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">potlood, balpen inkt op papier op doek</dc:type><dc:identifier>1145</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Alighiero e Boetti</dc:creator><dc:title>I quattro moli</dc:title><dcterms:created>1982</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1145"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1145.JPG"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1145.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1410"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1145"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>