<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/218"><dc:date>1917-1918</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">In this bronze statue by Jacques Lipchitz various angular and semi-circular volumes have been combined to form a work of protruding forms which slide and fit together. Most of the elements cannot be immediately recognized as shapes from reality, though some of the eye-catching details are recognizable. A small, round indentation at the top of the sculpture can be recognized as an eye; a protruding, slightly oval form refers to an ear. The theme of diagonal lines which recur one below the other in three places refers to the strings of a guitar, certainly in connection with the title. This figure has been made as a freestanding sculpture, i.e., it can be viewed from any direction. However, there is clearly one main aspect from which the theme is most recognizable. 'By focusing on the recognizable details, the other shapes also become meaningful, even if they cannot be identified exactly. In some cases they have a double role, such as the shape extending to the front and running down from approximately halfway up. About this, Lipchitz said: “The knee has been drawn up as though he was leaping into space. At the same time, the shape of the knee corresponds to the shape of the guitar.” According to Lipchitz, the horizontal lines fairly high up in the sculpture refer to the stripy shirt of a sailor. At the same time, they work as independent elements serving as a counterpart to the guitar strings. The way in which this sculpture is composed follows the principles of Cubism. The forms of a figurative starting point are analyzed, become independent and are then recombined as a new whole in which the theme which was the starting point can still be recognized. 'Although the Cubist principles were mainly developed in painting, artists such as Lipchitz and Zadkine also used them in sculpture. The first version of 'Marin et guitare' dating from 1914 was much more realistic than the version shown here. However, Lipchitz turned the theme of “the young Spanish sailor who was dancing gaily around the girls while he is playing a guitar” into a lively figure here because of the rhythmic connection of differing forms, angular next to rounded, protruding and indented. The dynamic character of the sculpture is also reinforced by the diagonal lines which can be seen, amongst other things, in the strings.</dc:description><dc:identifier>218</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>91,5 x 37,6 x 36,4 cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1917-1918</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">brons</dc:type><dc:creator>Jacques Lipchitz</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In dit bronzen beeld van Jacques Lipchitz zijn diverse hoekige en halfronde volumes samengevoegd tot een geheel van verspringende, verschuivende en in elkaar grijpende vormen. De meeste onderdelen zijn niet direct te herkennen als vormen uit de werkelijkheid; enkele in het oog springende details echter wel. Een kleine ronde uitsparing bovenin de sculptuur is herkenbaar als oog; een uitstekende enigszins ovale vorm verwijst naar een oor. Het motief van schuine strepen dat op drie plaatsen schuin onder elkaar terugkeert, verwijst, zeker in samenhang met de titel, naar de snaren van een gitaar. Dit beeld is als vrijstaande sculptuur gemaakt, d.w.z. bedoeld om van alle kanten bekeken te worden. Het heeft echter duidelijk één hoofdaanzicht van waaruit het thema het meest herkenbaar is. 'Door de herkenbare details in het beeld krijgen ook de overige vormen betekenis, al zijn ze niet exact te duiden. Soms vervullen ze een dubbele functie, zoals de sterk naar voren komende vorm die van ongeveer het midden van het beeld naar beneden loopt. Lipchitz zegt hierover: "De knie is opgetrokken alsof hij de ruimte in sprong. Tegelijkertijd correspondeert de vorm van de knie met de vorm van de guitaar. The knee is pulled up as though he was leaping in space. At the same time it reiterates the shape of the guitar body." De horizontale strepen, tamelijk bovenin het beeld, verwijzen volgens Lipchitz naar het gestreepte shirt van een matroos. Ze werken tegelijkertijd als zelfstandige elementen, die een tegenhanger vormen van de snaren. 'De manier waarop dit beeld is opgebouwd, komt overeen met de principes van het kubisme. De vormen van een figuratief uitgangspunt worden geanalyseerd, verzelfstandigd en weer bijeengevoegd tot een nieuw geheel, waarbij het uitgangsmotief herkenbaar blijft. Hoewel de kubistische principes vooral vanuit de schilderkunst ontwikkeld zijn, hebben kunstenaars als Lipchitz en Zadkine ze ook in de beeldhouwkunst toegepast. Een eerdere versie van 'Marin et guitare' uit 1914 is veel realistischer dan de hier getoonde. Het motief van "die jonge Spaanse matroos, die vrolijk rond de meisjes danst terwijl hij gitaar speelt" weet Lipchitz hier echter levendig gestalte te geven door de ritmische aaneenvoeging van afwisselende vormen: hoekig naast rond, inspringend tegenover uitstekend. Het dynamische karakter van het beeld wordt nog versterkt door de diagonale lijnen die onder meer waarneembaar zijn in de snaren.</dc:description><dc:title>Marin et guitare</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">bronze</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/218"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C559"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0218.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0218.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/218"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>