<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2912"><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 'Summer Camp', Yael Bartana shows the engagement of the Israeli Committee Against House Demolitions (ICAHD) in reconstructing houses in Palestine. Its members, from all corners of the globe, resist Israel’s support for the destruction of Palestinian houses in the Occupied Territories. ' The involvement of Israelis in this resistance shows the dividedness of the people. The motto of Israeli propaganda films is: ‘We came to Israel to build and to be built.’ Using the visual language of these films in Summer Camp, Bartana shows the ideological and visual similarities between the ICAHD’s construction activities and the construction of the state of Israel.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">video (PAL, kleur, geluid)</dc:type><dc:creator>Yael Bartana</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>tijdsduur / duration 00:12:00</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>2912</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">video (PAL, colour, sound), duration 12 min.</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 'Summer Camp' is te zien hoe de ICAHD (Israeli Committee Against House Demolitions) bezig is met de wederopbouw van huizen in Palestina. De leden komen uit alle hoeken van de wereld. Ze verzetten zich tegen het Israëlische beleid dat verantwoordelijk is voor de vernielingen van de huizen van Palestijnen in de bezette gebieden. ' Dat ook Israëliërs betrokken zijn bij het verzet maakt de verdeeldheid van de bevolking zichtbaar. “We came to Israel to build and to be built” is de leuze in Israëlische propagandafilms. Bartana gebruikt voor 'Summer Camp' de beeldtaal van deze films, en laat zo de ideologische en visuele overeenkomsten zien tussen de bouwwerkzaamheden van de ICAHD en de opbouw van de staat Israël.</dc:description><dc:title>Summer Camp</dc:title><dc:date>2007</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>2007</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2912"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2912-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2912-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2912"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C6878"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>