<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/465"><dc:description xml:lang="en">The Delta works is a system of defence against disastrous floods such as that in 1953 in the Dutch coastal province of Zeeland. In the view of the scale of the planned dikes, special lifting vessels and pontoons were designed for the project. The Delta works are regarded as one of the seven modern wonders of 20th century engineering art by the American Society of Civil Engineers. 'As an expression of pride, the Dutch government commissioned various artists to record the on-going construction of the Delta works in different media from 1959 and 1970. The blueprints were donated in portfolios to museums and important foreign guests. '[exhibition text 2017]</dc:description><dcterms:extent>37,7 x 50 cm 55 x 66 x 2,8 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">ets op papier</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Ben Ikelaar</dc:creator><dcterms:created>1966</dcterms:created><dc:identifier>465</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">etching on paper</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De Deltawerken is een verdedigingssysteem tegen overstromingsrampen zoals in 1953 in Zeeland. Vanwege de schaal van de geplande waterkeringen werden er speciale hefschepen en zand zuigende pontons ontworpen. De Deltawerken wordt door de American Society of Civil Engineers beschouwd als één van de zeven moderne wereldwonderen van de 20e-eeuwse ingenieurskunst. 'Trots op haar waterstaatswerken gaf de regering tussen 1959 en 1970 aan verschillende kunstenaars de opdracht om de in uitvoering zijnde Deltawerken in verschillende media vast te leggen. De grafiekbladen werden in een portfolio aan musea en belangrijke buitenlandse gasten geschonken. '[tentoonstellingstekst 2017]</dc:description><dc:title>Deltawerken Haringvliet</dc:title><dc:date>1966</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/465"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C805"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0465-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0465-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/465"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>