<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/388"><dc:identifier>388</dc:identifier><dcterms:created>1959</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Rauchzeichnung', by the German artist Otto Piene, consists of paper and soot. The work was made with the help of a metal plate in which there are holes in a pattern of concentric circles. Piene allowed the smoke of a candle or petroleum lamp to pass through the holes forming dots varying from deep black to light grey. Here and there were marks because the smoke penetrated under the plate. The pattern of slightly overlapping circles or fragments of circles produces a dynamic result in the image and the circles appear to be moving. 'Initially Otto Piene made monochrome paintings with grids of points in light relief. The points arose because Piene pressed oil paints onto the canvas through a metal plate. The image that we see is largely determined by the light falling on it and the material serves only to reveal the effect of the light. Piene shared his interest in light and light reflection with Heinz Mack and Günther Uecker, and together they formed the Zero group. In addition to light, movement also plays an important role in their work. At first, movement was only suggested, as in 'Rauchzeichnung', but later objects were created in which there was actual movement. 'Zero was founded in 1957 on the basis of the cooperation between Piene and Mack. They opposed the expressionist art forms such as Abstract Expressionism and Tachism, which dominated the western art world in the 1950s. In this movement, emotion and a personal signature play an important role, but the Zero artists rejected that. Their work is much more impersonal and distant than a painting in which the act of painting is clearly present. Light, space and energy were key concepts for the Zero artists. They represent a new attitude to reality. According to Piene, “Zero is the zone of silence and of pure possibilities for a new start. Just like the countdown when a rocket is fired – Zero is the immeasurable zone where the old situation turns into a new one.”</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>75 x 105 x 2,8 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Rauchzeichnung</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">roet op papier</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">soot on paper</dc:type><dc:date>1959</dc:date><dc:creator>Otto Piene</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Rauchzeichnung' van de Duitse kunstenaar Otto Piene bestaat uit papier en roet. Het werk is gemaakt met behulp van een metalen plaat, voorzien van gaatjes in een patroon van concentrische cirkels. Piene laat de rook van een kaars of een petroleumlamp door de gaatjes neerslaan. Zo worden puntjes gevormd variërend van diep zwart tot lichtgrijs. Hier en daar ontstaan vlekken doordat de rook onder de plaat doordringt. Het patroon van gedeeltelijk overlappende cirkels of cirkelfragmenten geeft het beeld dynamiek: de cirkels lijken in beweging. 'Otto Piene maakt aanvankelijk monochrome schilderijen met rasters van punten in licht reliëf. De punten ontstaan doordat Piene olieverf door een metalen plaat op het doek drukt. Het beeld dat we zien wordt voor een groot deel bepaald door het licht dat erop valt. Het materiaal dient slechts om de werking van het licht zichtbaar te maken. Zijn interesse in licht en lichtreflectie deelt Piene met de kunstenaars Heinz Mack en Günther Uecker. Samen vormen zij de groep Zero. Naast licht speelt beweging een belangrijke rol in hun werk. Eerst wordt er alleen beweging gesuggereerd zoals in 'Rauchzeichnung'; later ontstaan er objecten waarin sprake is van werkelijke beweging. 'Zero ontstaat vanuit een samenwerking tussen Piene en Mack in 1957. Ze zetten zich af tegen de expressionistische kunstvormen zoals het abstract-expressionisme en tachisme, die in de jaren vijftig in de westerse kunstwereld de boventoon voeren. Daarin spelen emotie en persoonlijk handschrift een belangrijke rol. De kunstenaars van Zero nemen hier afstand van. Hun werk is veel onpersoonlijker en afstandelijker dan een schilderij waarin het schildersgebaar sterk aanwezig is. Licht, ruimte en energie zijn sleutelbegrippen voor de Zerokunstenaars. Ze vertegenwoordigen een nieuwe houding ten aanzien van de werkelijkheid. "Zero is de zone van stilte en van pure mogelijkheden voor een nieuw begin, als bij het aftellen wanneer raketten afgeschoten worden - Zero is de onmeetbare zone waar de oude toestand in een nieuwe over gaat", aldus Piene.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/388"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/388"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0388-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0388-01.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C728"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>