<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/36"><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">Beckmann completed this 'Winter Scene' in October, well before the winter of 1930; he was not painting a real scene. This looks like a traditional starting point: a painting conceived as a window on the world. However, Beckmann was not interested in painting nature per se. He wanted to show what is hidden behind visual reality/the visual surface, and in this way penetrate further into reality. 'Beckmann’s image of the world changed as a result of the First World War, in which, working as a voluntary nurse, he came across situations where there was no respect for human dignity. He saw life as the existence of a slave and wanted to pass on a message to learn to take personal responsibility. Winter symbolises dying and petrified nature, and the absence of hope. Winter Scene contains symbols showing the possibilities of flight (an open window), nature restricted by human hands (drastically pruned trees), and the possibility of a transition to another area or another existence (a closed garden, a ladder, a park surrounded by residential buildings). '[exhibition text 2013]</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dcterms:created>1930</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>36</dc:identifier><dc:creator>Max Beckmann</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>87,3 x 78,9 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Winterlandschap</dc:title><dc:date>1930</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het schilderij 'Winterbild' voltooide Beckmann in oktober 1930, ruim voor de winter; hij schilderde geen reële situatie na. Het lijkt een traditioneel uitgangspunt: een schilderij opgevat als venster naar de wereld. Maar Beckmann was niet geïnteresseerd in het schilderen van de natuur ‘an sich’. Hij wilde datgene tonen wat achter de visuele werkelijkheid/het visuele oppervlak schuil gaat en daarmee dieper doordringen in de realiteit. 'De Eerste Wereldoorlog waar hij als vrijwillige ziekenbroeder mensonterende situaties tegenkwam, veranderde Beckmann’s wereldbeeld. Hij zag het leven als een slavenbestaan en wilde mensen de boodschap aanreiken zelf verantwoording te nemen. Winter symboliseert de stervende en verstarde natuur en het ontbreken van hoop. In Winterbild zijn symbolen van vluchtmogelijkheden (open raam), de door mensenhanden beknotte natuur (extreem gesnoeide bomen), en de mogelijkheid van een overgang naar een andere gebied of een ander bestaan (gesloten tuin, ladder, park omzoomt met woonblokken) te lezen. '[tentoonstellingstekst 2013]</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/36"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0036.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0036.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/36"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C379"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>