<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/892"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/892"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1198"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0892-01.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0892-01.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/892"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dcterms:created>1974</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Grau (no.365/2)' by the German artist Gerhard Richter is a completely grey painting. It is done in oils and has a grainy texture, probably as a result of using a paint roller. 'Gerhard Richter made several grey paintings. With broad or narrow palette knives, paintbrushes and paint rollers, he applied all sorts of coarse and fine-grained textures onto the canvas. In this series of paintings, he used only the colour grey because this was most neutral for him and was least like an illusion. They are paintings which do not tell stories and do not refer to anything other than themselves. In this series, Richter shows the painting as a surface, the skin of the painting. 'His work is very diverse and his themes vary from photo-realistic landscapes and portraits to enlarged colour samples from paint shops. His work is an examination of the different possibilities of painting. He is prepared to paint everything in every conceivable way as long as his work does not start to belong to one particular style. He does not follow any system, has no programme and does not have any personal preferences either. Richter considers that theorizing about art is pointless because every theory simply replaces another, and all the arguments are based on coincidence. He said: “I do not have a motif, only motivation.” He is a painter and wants to show what is possible with and in painting.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Grau (nr. 365/2)' van de Duitse kunstenaar Gerhard Richter is een volledig grijs schilderij. Het is gemaakt met olieverf en heeft een korrelige textuur. Deze is vermoedelijk ontstaan door het gebruik van een verfroller. 'Gerhard Richter heeft diverse grijze schilderijen gemaakt. Met brede of smalle plamuurmessen, verfkwasten en verfrollers heeft hij allerlei grofkorrelige en fijnmazige texturen op doek aangebracht. In deze serie schilderijen gebruikt hij alleen de kleur grijs omdat die voor hem het meest neutraal is en de minst illusionistische werking heeft. Het zijn schilderijen die geen verhalen vertellen, die naar niets anders verwijzen dan naar zichzelf. Richter toont in deze serie het schilderij als oppervlak, de huid van het schilderij. 'Richters werk is heel divers. Zijn thema's variëren van fotorealistische landschappen en portretten tot uitvergrote kleurstalen uit verfwinkels. Zijn werk is een onderzoek naar de diverse mogelijkheden van de schilderkunst. Hij is bereid alles te schilderen, op elke denkbare wijze zolang zijn werk maar niet tot een bepaalde stijl gaat behoren. Hij volgt geen systeem, kent geen programma en heeft evenmin een persoonlijke voorkeur. Richter vindt dat theoretiseren over kunst geen zin heeft omdat elke theorie alleen maar in de plaats komt van een andere, en alle argumenten op toeval berusten. Hij zegt: "Ik heb geen motief, alleen motivatie". Hij is schilder en wil laten zien wat er met en binnen de schilderkunst mogelijk is.</dc:description><dc:identifier>892</dc:identifier><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:creator>Gerhard Richter</dc:creator><dc:date>1974</dc:date><dcterms:extent>250,5 x 200,5 x 4,9 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Grau (nr. 365/1)</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>