<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3371"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3371"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C11546"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3371-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3371-01.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3371"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">inkjet print op papier</dc:type><dc:creator>Walid Raad</dc:creator><dc:title>Preface to the German Edition</dc:title><dc:date>2016</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">inkjet print on paper</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit werk maakt deel uit van de serie 'Scratching On Things I Could Disavow: A History of Art In The Arab World'. Daarin gebruikt Walid Raad fictieve personages en literaire titels om meerduidige verhalen te vertellen over de geschiedenis van de beeldende kunst in de Arabische wereld. Raad presenteert hier muren met verdwenen kunstobjecten. De schaduwpartijen van de lijsten verraden dat ze er ooit zijn geweest. ' Raad vertelt: “Dit project maakt deel uit van de geschiedenis van de beeldende kunst in Libanon en de versnelling in de ontwikkeling van een nieuwe infrastructuur voor de beeldende kunst in de Arabische wereld. Daarbij overdenk ik, hoe cultuur en traditie in de Arabische wereld, materieel en immaterieel, beïnvloed worden door de verschillende oorlogen die er door de inheemse en externe krachten zijn gevoerd.”</dc:description><dcterms:extent>(4x) 63,1 x 44,2 x 3,7 cm (incl.lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>3371</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">This work is part of the series 'Scratching On Things I Could Disavow: A History of Art In The Arab World'. Raad uses fictional characters and literary titles to tell polyvalent stories about the history of art in the Arab world. Here, the viewer sees walls from which art objects have disappeared, shadows cast by frames showing they were once there. Raad explains: ‘This project is part of the history of art in Lebanon and the accelerating development of a new infrastructure of visual art in the Arab world. I study how culture and tradition in the Arab world are influenced, materially and immaterially, by the various wars that have been fought by native and by external powers.’ ' As Raad says: ‘This project engages in the history of visual arts in Lebanon and the acceleration in the development of a new infrastructure for the visual arts in the Arab world. Moreover, I consider how culture and tradition in the Arab world are affected, materially and immaterially, by the various wars that have been waged there by native and external powers.’</dc:description><dcterms:created>2016</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>