<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/459"><dc:title>Bleu outremer</dc:title><dcterms:created>1958</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>459</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 'Bleu outremer' the Spanish artist Antonio Tàpies applied thick layers of sand mixed with paint to the canvas with a spatula. The top layer, in a dark blue mixed with black, evokes associations with a gateway or wall. The two rectangular shapes in the clear blue can be seen as doors or peepholes. The grey edge at the top of the canvas and the grey to the left and right of the dark blue shape have been applied with paint, leaving the structure of the canvas visible. There are occasional holes and scratches in the thicker layers. 'During the second half of the 1950s there were several artists in Europe who mixed their paint with materials such as sand, clay or straw. The work created in this way was sometimes described with the term “Material painting”. However, despite a comparable use of material, it was certainly not a group of artists with similar ideas who deliberately presented a joint front. In the mid-1940s Tàpies started to work with materials such as rope, twigs, textile and paper. Later on he started to mix his paint with sand or used mortar, a mixture of sand and chalk. He deliberately opted for ephemeral or elementary materials. Tàpies explained: “I use sand in my paintings because I have a preference for the “material” quality.” In addition, the “symbolism of the material with its many contradictions” played an important role. 'For Tàpies a good painting is a painting which reflects life itself in as many aspects as possible. He never painted in an illusionist way. He constructed shapes on a canvas which evoke associations with walls, windows, doors and gateways, as in 'Bleu outremer' or Double port beige. These are not representations of existing objects; rather they represent an archetype. Tàpies made scratches or nicks in them, just as real walls and doors show the traces of what has happened over time as a result of natural circumstances or human intervention. He assigned great value to the structure of the surface, the tears, holes and irregularities of his work. Like the materials sand and dust, his walls and gateways are symbols of change and the transience of life itself.</dc:description><dc:creator>Antoni Tàpies</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>164 x 132 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil, sand on canvas on panel</dc:type><dc:date>1958</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf, zand op doek op paneel</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 'Bleu outremer' heeft de Spaanse kunstenaar Antoni Tàpies met een spatel dikke lagen van met zand vermengde verf op het doek aangebracht. De bovenste laag, in een donker, met zwart gemengd blauw, roept associaties op met een poort of muur. De twee rechthoekige vormen in een helderder blauw kun je zien als doorkijk of als deuren. De grijze rand bovenaan het doek en het grijs links en rechts van de donkerblauwe vorm zijn alleen met verf opgezet en laten de structuur van het linnen zichtbaar. In de dikkere lagen zitten hier en daar gaatjes en krassen. 'In de tweede helft van de jaren vijftig zijn er diverse kunstenaars in Europa die hun verf mengen met materialen als zand, klei of stro. Het werk dat hiermee ontstaat wordt wel aangeduid met de term materieschilderkunst. Ondanks een vergelijkbaar materiaalgebruik is er echter geen sprake van een groep kunstenaars met verwante ideeën, die bewust, gezamenlijk, naar buiten treden. Halverwege de jaren veertig begint Tàpies werk te maken met materialen als touw, takjes, textiel en papier. Later gaat hij verf mengen met zand of gebruikt hij mortel, een mengsel van zand en kalk. Hij kiest bewust voor vergankelijke of elementaire materialen. Tàpies zegt: "Ik verwerk zand in mijn schilderijen omdat ik een voorkeur heb voor het 'stof-achtige'." Daarbij speelt "de symboliek van het stof, met zijn vele tegenstrijdigheden" een belangrijke rol. 'Een goed schilderij is voor Tàpies een schilderij dat het leven zelf reflecteert in zoveel mogelijk aspecten. Hij schildert nooit illusionistisch. Hij bouwt vormen op een doek, die associaties oproepen met muren, ramen, deuren en poorten, zoals in 'Bleu outremer' of 'Double porte beige'. Dit zijn geen afbeeldingen van bestaande objecten, maar eerder vertegenwoordigen zij een archetype. Tàpies voorziet ze van krassen of kerven, net zoals werkelijke muren en deuren sporen van aantasting dragen, veroorzaakt in de loop der tijd door natuurlijke omstandigheden of door menselijk handelen. Tàpies kent grote waarde toe aan de oppervlaktestructuur, de scheuren, gaten en oneffenheden van zijn werk. Zijn muren en poorten zijn net als de materialen zand en stof, symbolen voor de veranderlijkheid en vergankelijkheid van het leven zelf.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/459"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0459.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C799"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0459.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/459"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>