<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/52"><dc:creator>Georges Braque</dc:creator><dc:date>1918</dc:date><dcterms:extent>130 x 74,5 x 3,5 cm 135,1 x 79 x 3,7 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1918</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:title>Nature morte au guéridon</dc:title><dc:identifier>52</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 'Nature morte au guéridon', dating from 1918, the French painter Georges Braque depicted a number of identifiable objects: a table, a guitar, a pipe, a newspaper and a bowl of fruit. However, he did not paint them in accordance with the laws of central perspective. The table leg is seen from the side, while the guitar and the newspaper are represented from above and the bowl of fruit is shown in cross-section. The pipe is painted from the side, but the opening suggests a view from the top. 'The combination of various different views is one of the characteristics of Cubism, in which an object is seen from different sides, analysed in terms of facets and forged together to create a new entity. During the first stage of Cubism, little attention was devoted to materials and material qualities, but this did happen during the second stage. In1912 Braque used a piece of woodgrain paper in a painting for the first time and by using that sort of material he tried to achieve a new sort of realism. Braque also incorporated pieces of newspaper and scraps of paper in his paintings. This collage technique meant that sometimes the planes literally slide over and across each other. 'Nature morte au guéridon' is entirely painted, but the influence of the technique is clearly visible in the dotted and chequered planes which are reminiscent of decorative paper and in the letters which refer to a headline in a newspaper. 'Braque juxtaposed abstract and recognizable shapes. The shapes cut across each other or overlap while at the same time they continue in a different colour. This is characteristic of the second stage of Cubism, synthetic Cubism, in which the image is composed of separate elements and the object and interim shape are seen as being of equal value. The soft colours of pink, blue and yellow which Braque used signify an enrichment in terms of colour in comparison with his analytical Cubist works in which he deliberately restricted his palette to greys, browns and ochres.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 'Nature morte au guéridon' uit 1918 beeldt de Franse schilder Georges Braque een aantal herkenbare objecten af: een tafeltje, een gitaar, een pijp, een krant en een fruitschaal. Hij schildert ze echter niet overeenkomstig de wetten van het centraal perspectief. De tafelpoot is van opzij gezien, de gitaar en de krant zijn van bovenaf weergegeven en de fruitschaal is in doorsnede afgebeeld. De pijp is van opzij geschilderd, maar de opening suggereert een bovenaanzicht. 'Het combineren van diverse aanzichten is een kenmerk van het kubisme. Een object wordt van verschillende kanten bekeken, in facetten ontleed, en tot een nieuw geheel aaneen gesmeed. Er is in de eerste fase van het kubisme weinig aandacht voor materiaal en stoffelijkheid. In de tweede fase is dat juist wel het geval. In 1912 gebruikt Braque voor het eerst een stuk houtnerfpapier in een schilderij. Hij probeert door de toepassing van dergelijke materialen een nieuw soort realisme te bewerkstelligen. Braque verwerkt stukken krant en snippers papier in zijn schilderijen. Deze collagetechniek leidt ertoe dat er soms letterlijk vlakken over en in elkaar geschoven worden. 'Nature morte au guéridon' is helemaal geschilderd maar de invloed van deze techniek is duidelijk zichtbaar in de gestippelde en geruite vlakken, die doen denken aan decoratief papier, en in de letters die verwijzen naar een krantenkop. 'Braque zet abstracte en herkenbare vormen tegen en over elkaar. Vormen worden doorsneden of overlapt terwijl ze tegelijkertijd in een andere kleur verder gaan. Dit is kenmerkend voor de tweede fase van het kubisme, het synthetisch kubisme, waarbij het beeld wordt samengesteld uit losse elementen en object en tussenvorm gelijkwaardig worden behandeld. De zachte kleuren roze, blauw en geel die Braque gebruikt, betekenen een verrijking qua kleur ten opzichte van zijn analytisch kubistische werken. Daarin beperkt hij zijn palet bewust tot grijzen, bruinen en okers.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/52"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/52"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0052.JPG"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0052.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C395"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>