<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/458"><dc:title>Effingham I</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 'Effingham 1' Frank Stella joins a red and a yellow polygon together with a blue band. This band of colour borders part of the red polygon and then follows round the yellow field. Where the blue band meets itself again the different parts remain divided by a thin line of unpainted canvas, and a similar edge of white can be seen between the different colours. The blue band ends in a sharp corner at the bottom of the yellow field. The painting is in the shape of an irregular polygon. 'At the start of his career as a painter, Stella was influenced by Abstract Expressionism. However, he rejected the atmosphere which characterizes many abstract expressionist works, particularly because of the spatial quality this suggests. Stella wished to exclude every form of illusion. He looked for a way of making a painting look completely flat. For him the solution was to work with rigid shapes, and plain colours in such a way that there is no figure and background. Between 1958 and 1960 he achieved this by constructing symmetrical compositions with parallel bands with the same width. He painted these bands in a geometric pattern to fill the space. After 1960 he solved the question of the figure and the background by removing the remaining forms from the canvas, resulting in so-called shaped canvases. Stella’s work can be described by the term Post-painterly Abstraction. ''Effingham 1' is one of the “Irregular Polygon Series”, also known as the “Eccentric Polygon Series”. The eleven paintings in this series each have a different shape and each shape is executed in four different colour combinations. The titles are derived from the towns in the White Mountains of New Hampshire. In this series, Stella uses two or three different geometric forms as a starting point, which he wholly or partly edges with an 8-inch wide band of a contrasting colour. By edging the shapes in this way, he avoids the illusion of overlapping. The thin lines of unpainted canvas keep the colours separated and avoid the effect of retreating or advancing. The sharp corners and shapes which appear to have been cut off, prevent the viewer from seeing the fields as things. Because of the thickness of the frame and its special outline, the painting acquires the character of an object.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">acrylverf op doek</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 'Effingham I' verbindt Stella een rood en een geel meerhoekig vlak met elkaar via een blauwe baan. Deze baan begrenst een gedeelte van het rode vlak en loopt vervolgens om het gele vlak heen. Waar de blauwe baan zichzelf ontmoet, blijven de verschillende delen van elkaar gescheiden door een dunne lijn van onbeschilderd doek. Ook tussen de verschillenden kleuren is zo'n randje wit zichtbaar. De blauwe baan eindigt met een scherpe hoek onderaan het gele vlak. Het schilderij heeft de vorm van een onregelmatige veelhoek. 'Aan het begin van zijn loopbaan als schilder ondergaat Stella invloed van het abstract-expressionisme. Het atmosferische, waardoor veel abstract-expressionistisch werk gekenmerkt wordt, staat hem echter tegen, vooral vanwege de ruimtelijkheid die daarmee gesuggereerd wordt. Stella wil elke vorm van illusionisme uitbannen. Hij zoekt een manier om een schilderij volkomen vlak te laten lijken. De oplossing is voor hem zó te werken met strakke vormen en egale kleuren, dat er geen sprake is van figuur en achtergrond. Tussen 1958 en 60 bereikt hij dit door symmetrische composities op te bouwen uit parallelle banen van dezelfde breedte. Deze banen brengt hij vlakvullend aan in een geometrisch patroon. Na 1960 lost hij de figuur-achtergrond problematiek op door de restvormen uit het beeldvlak te halen. Zo ontstaan de zogeheten shaped canvases. Stella's werk valt onder de term post-painterly abstraction. ''Effingham I' behoort tot de 'Irregular Polygon Series', ook wel 'Eccentric Polygon Series' genoemd. De elf schilderijen van deze serie hebben elk een andere vorm. Elke vorm is in vier verschillende kleurstellingen uitgevoerd. De titels zijn ontleend aan steden in de Witte Bergen van New Hampshire. In deze serie neemt Stella twee of drie ongelijke geometrische vormen als uitgangspunt, die hij geheel of gedeeltelijk omrandt met een acht inch brede baan in een contrasterende kleur. Door de omranding van de vormen voorkomt hij de illusie van overlapping. De dunne lijnen van onbeschilderd doek houden de kleuren gescheiden en gaan een effect van wijken of naar voren komen tegen. De scherpe hoeken en ogenschijnlijk afgesneden vormen voorkomen dat je de vlakken als dingen gaat zien. Het schilderij krijgt door de dikte van het spieraam en door zijn bijzondere omtreksvorm een objectachtig karakter.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>327 x 335,5 x 10,1 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Frank Stella</dc:creator><dcterms:created>1967</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">acrylic on canvas</dc:type><dc:identifier>458</dc:identifier><dc:date>1967</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/458"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C798"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0458-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/458"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0458-01.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>