<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3016"><dc:title>Wood Circle</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">wood</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to make the work 'Wood Circle' by the English artist Richard Long, hundreds of branches are placed together in the shape of a circle with a diameter of seven metres. The branches are all of different sizes and they are randomly spread in different directions but in such a way that the distance between them is roughly the same everywhere. Following these directions results in an undulating pattern. 'Long makes different sorts of works but they are closely interrelated. In nature he makes simple geometric sculptures using stones and branches. These disappear again after a while as a result of the influence of natural conditions. He also makes "conceptual" sculptures. He follows a route determined in advance, for example, a walk in the form of a circle. Long documents his walks and interventions in nature with photographs, maps and descriptions and then exhibits these at a later stage. He also makes sculptures in exhibition rooms. In this case he arranges natural materials such as wood, stone or clay in geometric patterns. With regard to his preference for these forms, he said: "I use lines and circles because of their strength. These rigid forms contrast with the capricious character of the natural material with which they are composed." 'Long’s work is inconceivable without the developments of minimal art and conceptual art. He studied at Saint Martin’s School of Art in London from 1966 to 1968 where a number of artists including Gilbert &amp; George, Barry Flanagan and Hamish Fulton were thinking of ways to expand the concept of sculpture at the time. For them a sculpture was no longer by definition an unchanging spatial object made by an artist. Art could also be less tangible and focus more on an idea. A work of art could have a temporary character. Because of the fact that some of Long’s work is created directly in nature it is also classified as Land Art. '[MvG 2006/2007]</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">hout</dc:type><dc:identifier>3016</dc:identifier><dcterms:created>1977</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het werk Wood Circle van de Britse kunstenaar Richard Long bestaat uit 840 takken van verschillende afmetingen. De takken zijn in willekeurige volgorde, en volgens bepaalde richtlijnen, in een cirkel met een doorsnede van zeven meter, opgesteld. Ze dienen gelijk verdeeld te zijn en overal moeten ongeveer evenveel dikke, dunne, langere, en kortere takken voorkomen. De takken raken elkaar niet aan en vormen samen een golvend patroon. De voorschriften voor het opstellen van het werk zijn in 1976 door Long in een certificaat vastgelegd. 'Long werkt veel met natuurlijke materialen in geometrische patronen. Over zijn voorkeur voor deze vormen zegt hij: "Ik gebruik lijnen en cirkels omwille van hun kracht. Deze strakke vormen contrasteren met de grilligheid van het natuurlijke materiaal waaruit ze zijn opgebouwd". 'Een belangrijk element in het werk van Long is ‘de wandeling’. Tijdens zijn wandelingen maakt Long sculpturale werken van materialen die hij in het landschap vindt. De werken die hij in de buitenlucht maakt, verdwijnen soms weer door natuurlijke omstandigheden. Het maakproces en de documentatie hiervan maakt voor Long onderdeel uit van het kunstwerk. Het werk van Long wordt vaak tot de Land Art gerekend. Nadat Long met zijn werk bekendheid gekregen had, heeft hij zijn werk ook binnen musea en galerieën gepresenteerd. '[MvG 2006/2007]</dc:description><dcterms:extent>(geïnstalleerd kunstwerk) ø 700 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Richard Long</dc:creator><dc:date>1977</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3016"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3016-01.JPG"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3016-01.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3016"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1181"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>