<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/385"><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:created>1909</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">In 'Femme en vert' Pablo Picasso, who originated from Spain, used mainly grey, brown and ochre shades to paint the head and upper body of a woman against a background of the same colours. The green to the left and right of the neck and under the raised arm of the woman is very prominent and the face is composed of angular shapes. The body and arms contain less sharply defined shapes and Picasso placed whimsical fields of colour next to each other here. The background is divided into different fields with a number of horizontal and vertical lines and within these fields other colours have been juxtaposed. 'In 1909 Picasso and the French artist Georges Braque developed a new style known as Cubism. They used a given object in the real world, analysed it and divided it into facets, using these to construct a new composition. At the same time they made the shapes more abstract and combined different aspects within a painting so that there is nothing left of a central perspective. The canvas is seen as a flat surface on which colours and shapes are given a place as independent elements, and this Cubist vision was the first step in the development towards abstract art. The first stage of Cubism, which lasted up to 1912, was known as analytical Cubism. As the artists were still concentrating mainly on shape, the palette of colours they used was limited. 'In 'Femme en vert' Picasso painted his lover at the time, Fernande Olivier, concentrating on the details of her head, and he represented the various parts of her face and hair in stereometric forms. Together with the distribution of light and dark, these produce a spatial effect. The left side of the figure is clearly distinct from the background; on the right, the shapes cannot all be read in a spatial way. The green under the arm can be seen as a sofa or as a cushion, but the green mark above the arm cannot be defined. The light triangular shape to the left does not have a clear significance either and the shapes in the background cannot be identified as particular objects. This work remains something between a traditional portrait and an abstract painting.</dc:description><dc:identifier>385</dc:identifier><dc:date>1909</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Femme en vert</dc:title><dc:creator>Pablo Picasso</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>100,3 x 81,3 x 2,5 cm 124,4 x 105,3 x 4,1 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">In 'Femme en vert' schildert de uit Spanje afkomstige kunstenaar Pablo Picasso met voornamelijk grijze, bruine en oker tinten het hoofd en het bovenlichaam van een vrouw tegen een achtergrond in dezelfde kleuren. Het groen links en rechts van de hals en onder de opgetrokken arm van de vrouw springt eruit. Het gezicht is opgebouwd uit hoekige vormen. Het lichaam en de armen bevatten minder scherp afgebakende vormen. Picasso plaatst hier grillige kleurvlekken tegen elkaar. De achtergrond is met een aantal horizontale en verticale lijnen verdeeld in vlakken. Binnen deze vlakken zijn weer verschillende kleuren tegen elkaar gezet. 'In 1909 ontwikkelen Picasso en de Franse kunstenaar Georges Braque een nieuwe stijl: het kubisme. Ze gaan uit van een gegeven uit de werkelijkheid, analyseren dit, ontleden het in facetten en bouwen daaruit een nieuwe compositie op. Daarbij abstraheren zij de vormen en combineren zij verschillende aanzichten binnen een schilderij. Er is geen sprake meer van centraal perspectief. Het doek wordt beschouwd als een plat vlak waarop kleuren en vormen als zelfstandige elementen hun plaats krijgen. Deze kubistische visie vormt een eerste stap in de ontwikkeling naar de abstracte kunst. De eerste fase van het kubisme, die tot 1912 duurt, wordt het analytisch kubisme genoemd. Omdat de kunstenaars zich dan vooral op vorm concentreren, houden zij hun kleurenpalet beperkt. 'In 'Femme en vert' heeft Picasso zijn toenmalige vriendin Fernande Olivier, afgebeeld. Haar hoofd is het meest uitgewerkt. Picasso herleidt de verschillende onderdelen van haar gezicht en de haarpartij tot stereometrische vormen. Deze zorgen, mede door de verdeling van licht en donker, voor een ruimtelijk effect. De linkerkant van de figuur onderscheidt zich duidelijk van de achtergrond. Aan de rechterkant zijn de vormen niet allemaal meer ruimtelijk te lezen. Het groen onder de arm kun je zien als bank of als kussen, maar de groene vlek boven de arm is niet meer te definiëren. Ook de lichte driehoekige vorm links daarvan heeft geen eenduidige betekenis. De vormen op de achtergrond zijn evenmin als voorwerpen herkenbaar. Dit werk houdt het midden tussen een klassiek portret en een abstract schilderij.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/385"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/385"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0385-01.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0385-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C725"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>