<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3357"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3357-05.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3357"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C10855"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3357-05.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3357"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">styrene, MDF, plexiglas (maquette)</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>2015-2017</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">This architectural model, developed in close collaboration with architect Paul Kuipers, shows The People’s Parliament of Rojava. The circular design refers to the agora from ancient Greek democracy, but also to the informal circles in which Rojavan communes practice self-governance. The pillars around the circle mention key terms from the social contract of Rojava, the “constitution” of the autonomous region. The roof consists of fragments of different flags of organizations that play a key role in the revolution of Rojava and its daily self-governance. Around the parliament a public park is created, that strengthens Amina Osse’s idea of a “parliament as a public space.” The People’s Parliament of Rojava is a symbol, a sculpture and an architectural manifesto, as much as it is also a place of day to day political assembly. 'Roof Design 'This cross-section of the roof of the parliament comprises fragments of flags of different organizations that play key roles within the Rojava Revolution and the daily practice of self-governance in the region, developed in close collaboration with designer Remco van Bladel. The roof also forms an index that provides insight in the different character of each organization. Together these fragments of flags form a visual “democratic confederacy” in which the symbolic stars and suns form an “ideological planetarium,” beneath which the assemblies in the parliament will take place.</dc:description><dcterms:created>2015-2017</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent>31 x 101,5 x 101,5 cm (maquette incl. perspex kap / cover)</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">styreen, MDF, perspex</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit architectonische model, ontwikkeld in nauwe samenwerking met architect Paul Kuipers, toont het Volksparlement van Rojava. Het cirkelvormige ontwerp verwijst naar de agora uit de antieke Griekse democratie, maar ook naar de veelal informele cirkels waarin lokale Rojavaanse communes hun zelfbestuur in praktijk brengen. De pilaren rondom de cirkel vermelden kernbegrippen uit het sociale contract van Rojava, de ‘grondwet’ van de autonome regio. Het dak bestaat uit fragmenten van diverse vlaggen van organisaties die een kern rol spelen in de revolutie van Rojava en het dagelijkse zelfbestuur. Rondom het parlement wordt een publiek park aangelegd, dat Amina Osse’s idee van een ‘parlement als publieke ruimte’ versterkt. Het Volksparlement van Rojava is zowel een symbool, een sculptuur, een architectonisch manifest, als een plek van concrete politieke samenkomst. 'Ontwerp Overkapping 'De doorsnede van de overkapping van het parlement is opgebouwd uit fragmenten van vlaggen van verschillende organisaties die een sleutelrol spelen in de Revolutie van Rojava en het dagelijkse zelfbestuur in de regio, ontwikkeld in nauwe samenwerking met vormgever Remco van Bladel. De overkapping is tegelijkertijd een index die inzage geeft in het verschillende karakter van elke organisatie. Tezamen vormen de vlagfragmenten een visuele ‘democratische confederatie’ waarin de symbolische sterren en zonnen een ‘ideologisch planetarium’ vormen waaronder de samenkomsten in het parlement plaats zullen hebben.</dc:description><dc:creator>Jonas Staal</dc:creator><dc:title>New World Summit - Rojava</dc:title><dc:identifier>3357</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>