<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/336"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil, plaster, rope on canvas</dc:type><dc:title>Composition avec des cordes</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf, gips, touw op doek</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">The background of the painting 'Composition avec des cordes' by the Spanish artist Joan Miró consists of areas of colour applied in thin layers which partly merge together. Miró placed some sharply defined figures on top of this. These figures were partly left “open” and were partly coloured in with black or brightly coloured paint. In addition he attached pieces of rope to the canvas with large daubs of white glue. 'Miró divided his time between Paris and the area of his birth, Catalonia, from 1919, and was introduced to Surrealism in 1924. The Surrealists were very interested in the role of the subconscious in creating a work of art. Some worked with écriture automatique, while others expressed curious images from dreams in great detail. In Miró’s painting the shapes and colours of the background seem to fan out across the canvas in an uncontrolled way, but the carefully designed and precisely coloured figures come from a meticulously constructed imaginary world. The pieces of rope are similar to these figures in terms of their shape. The ragged ends correspond to the thin, shifting, radiating splurges of paint. 'Virtually all Miró’s work is populated by creatures who resembled humans or animals. In terms of the form they originate from objects in the Catalan landscape such as stones, shells, gourds, holes in rocks or weathered wood. Miró turned these organic but lifeless starting points into living creatures by adding eyes or feet. He explained: “My people are subject to the same simplification as my colours. Simplified as they are, they provide a more human and lively effect than if they had been represented in great detail. If they were detailed they would lack the imaginary life which makes everything larger.” After 1940, Miró started to experiment more with different materials, leaving the expressive strength of the material to dominate.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>123,5 x 103 x 10 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Joan Miró</dc:creator><dc:date>1950</dc:date><dcterms:created>1950</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:identifier>336</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De ondergrond van het schilderij 'Composition avec des cordes' van de Spaanse kunstenaar Joan Miró bestaat uit vlekken kleur, aangebracht in dunne lagen die gedeeltelijk in elkaar overvloeien. Daaroverheen heeft Miró scherpomlijnde figuurtjes gezet. Deze figuurtjes zijn gedeeltelijk 'open' gelaten en gedeeltelijk ingekleurd met zwarte of helder gekleurde verf. Daarnaast heeft hij stukjes touw met grote klodders witte lijm op het doek bevestigd. 'Miró, die vanaf 1919 afwisselend in Parijs en in zijn geboortestreek Catalonië verblijft, maakt in 1924 kennis met het surrealisme. De surrealisten hebben grote belangstelling voor de rol van het onderbewuste bij de totstandkoming van een kunstwerk. Sommigen werken met écriture automatique, anderen geven uiterst gedetailleerd merkwaardige droombeelden weer. Op Miró's schilderij lijken de vormen en kleuren van de ondergrond zonder controle over het doek uit te waaieren, maar de zorgvuldig vormgegeven en precies ingekleurde figuurtjes komen uit een geconstrueerde fantasiewereld. De stukjes touw hebben qua vorm overeenkomst met deze figuurtjes. De rafelige uiteinden sluiten aan bij de dunne, schiftende en uitwaaierende verfvlekken. 'Vrijwel al Miró's werk wordt bevolkt door op mensen of op dieren lijkende wezens. Wat vorm betreft vinden ze hun oorsprong in objecten uit het Catalaanse landschap, zoals stenen, schelpen, kalebassen, gaten in rotsen of verweerd hout. Van deze organische, maar levenloze uitgangpunten maakt Miró levende wezens door er ogen of voetjes aan toe te voegen. Hij zegt hierover: "Mijn mensen zijn onderworpen aan dezelfde vereenvoudiging als mijn kleuren. Vereenvoudigd als ze zijn, geven ze een menselijker en levendiger effect dan wanneer ze gedetailleerd weergegeven zouden zijn. Met alle details zouden ze dat denkbeeldige leven, dat alles groter maakt, missen." Na 1940 gaat Miró meer experimenteren met verschillende materialen. Daarbij staat de uitdrukkingskracht van het materiaal zelf voorop.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/336"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0336-02.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0336-02.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/336"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C676"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>