<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/781"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">This wall object by Sol LeWitt consists of a series of linked open squares made of white varnished aluminium. The work has a zigzag shape. At the bottom there are five squares linked together horizontally. From the square furthest to the right, a row goes up and the top of that row is once again the start of a row of five horizontal squares. The work is not very thick. 'LeWitt preferred to base his objects on a square. He viewed this as the most neutral basic shape with which it was possible to represent an idea as objectively as possible. On the basis of the same desire for objectivity he used the neutral colours white or black and smooth materials such as sanded and varnished wood or metal for his objects. LeWitt made several series of 'Wall Structures'. First, he painted them black. Later he opted for white because he considered that they meant that they were more part of the wall. This 'Wall Structure' consists of three times five squares. However, as the first and last square of the vertical row are also the beginning or end of the horizontal rows, there are therefore only thirteen squares that can be seen. The viewer’s gaze moves between thirteen and three times five. This work illustrates that even a simple structure provides different possibilities for arrangements and observation. 'Sol LeWitt considered himself a conceptual artist. The basis of a work of art was an idea which was determined in advance. The artist did not have to carry it out himself. The execution could also be of a temporary nature. LeWitt’s 'Wall Structures' also reveal characteristics of Minimal Art. One of the characteristics of Minimal Art is the use of a particular basic element which is repeated in accordance with a certain ordering principle. The interaction between the object and the space where it is presented is of crucial importance for this. The empty space around the object or between the elements is just as important for the experience of the image as the material that is present.</dc:description><dc:date>1972</dc:date><dcterms:created>1972</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit wandobject van Sol LeWitt bestaat uit een reeks aaneengeschakelde open vierkanten van wit gelakt aluminium. Het werk heeft een zigzagvorm. Onderaan zijn vijf vierkanten horizontaal geschakeld. Vanuit het meest rechtse vierkant gaat er een rij omhoog. Het bovenste daarvan is weer het begin van een rij van vijf horizontale vierkanten. Het werk heeft een geringe dikte. 'LeWitt baseert zijn objecten bij voorkeur op het vierkant. Hij beschouwt dit als de meest neutrale basisvorm, waarmee een idee zo objectief mogelijk kan worden vorm gegeven. Vanuit hetzelfde verlangen naar objectiviteit gebruikt hij voor zijn objecten de neutrale kleuren wit of zwart en gladde materialen zoals geschuurd en gelakt hout of metaal. LeWitt heeft diverse series 'Wall structures' gemaakt. Eerst schildert hij ze zwart. Later kiest hij voor wit, omdat hij vindt dat ze zo meer onderdeel uitmaken van de muur. Deze 'Wall structure' bestaat uit drie maal vijf vierkanten. Maar omdat het eerste en laatste vierkant van de verticale rij tevens het begin of einde vormen van de horizontale rijen, zijn er dus maar dertien vierkanten te zien. De blik van de waarnemer schommelt tussen dertien en drie maal vijf. Dit werk illustreert dat zelfs een eenvoudige structuur verschillende mogelijkheden tot ordening en waarneming biedt. 'Sol LeWitt beschouwt zichzelf als conceptueel kunstenaar. Aan de basis van een kunstwerk ligt het idee. Dit wordt vooraf bepaald. De kunstenaar hoeft het niet zelf uit te voeren. De uitvoering kan van tijdelijke aard zijn. LeWitts 'Wall structures' vertonen ook overeenkomst met de minimal art. Kenmerkend daarvoor is het gebruik van een bepaald basiselement, dat volgens een bepaald ordeningsprincipe herhaald wordt. De wisselwerking tussen het object en de ruimte waarin het gepresenteerd wordt, is daarbij van wezenlijke betekenis. De lege ruimte rondom het object, of tussen de elementen in, is even bepalend voor de ervaring van het beeld als de aanwezige materie.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>194,1 x 345,0 x 4,0 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">beschilderd aluminium</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">painted aluminum</dc:type><dc:identifier>781</dc:identifier><dc:title>Untitled (Wall Structure)</dc:title><dc:creator>Sol LeWitt</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/781"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/781"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1102"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0781.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0781.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>