<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3555"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">viltstift, Oost-Indische inkt, potlood, acrylverf, pyrografie, spuitverf, stoomgebogen eikenhouten latten, houtolie, impregneerlak</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">The history of "Woensel Supertoll! leads back to the summer of 2013. Artist Tijs Rooijakkers wanted to collaborate with the award-winning rapper Fresku (Roy Reymound, Eindhoven, 1986) in the semi-outdoor space of the Van Abbemuseum called Het Oog (The Eye). The theme of your own strength, finding your flow and creating a work with that flow is deeply rooted in the work of both artists. Fresku, which is Papiamento for 'cheeky', is a storyteller with sharp observations, humor and a reflective, critical eye. He wrote texts about personal motives and ambitions on the semi-circular wall of Het Oog, covered with wooden slats. These wooden slats were then steamed by Rooijakkers and bent into an enormous spinning top. A time-lapse by motion graphic studio OddOne was made of the work process and used in Fresku's video clip "WILSKR8" (willpower). 'Subsequently, the project moved to the area Woensel. Under the title "Woensel Supertoll!", Rooijakkers went here to organize master classes and workshops, together with Fresku, social design collective Tante Netty and local neighbourhood and welfare organizations. They invited local residents to formulate their own motives and ambitions on Rooijakkers' slats. With this he created large wooden clusters spread across the neighborhood. Ultimately, a permanent sculpture was erected in the middle of Woensel; a ‘supertol’ (super spinning top) covered in handwritten texts by both Fresku and local residents. 'With the project, Rooijakkers wanted to build a bridge between the museum and the city, between art and urban culture and between residents and their living environment. The artist explains: "The spinning-top is a symbol of the will, power and passion of mankind. Once a top is spinning, it supersedes gravity.’’ With the project in Woensel, he won the Eindhoven Culture Prize 2017. 'In 2019 the work returned to the Van Abbemuseum. Using slats from "Supertoll!" and "Woensel Supertoll!", Rooijakkers developed a theatrical installation in the 25-meter high tower of the Van Abbemuseum. A large part of this installation has been acquired by the museum with support of the Mondrian Fund. The cluster of slats and the spinning top can be presented separately in the future. 　 　 　</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">spray paint, felt-tip pen, acrylic paint, slats, impregnating varnish</dc:type><dc:date>2013-2019</dc:date><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Tijs Rooijakkers</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De geschiedenis van ‘Woensel Supertoll! leidt terug naar de zomer van 2013. Kunstenaar Tijs Rooijakkers wilde graag samenwerken met de bekroonde rapper Fresku (Roy Reymound, Eindhoven, 1986) in Het Oog; de semi-buitenruimte van het Van Abbemuseum. De thematiek van je eigen kracht, je flow vinden en vanuit die flow werk maken, zit diep in beider werk geworteld. Fresku, dat Papiaments is voor 'brutaal', is een verhalenverteller met scherpe observaties, humor en een reflecterende, kritische blik. Hij schreef teksten over persoonlijke drijfveren en ambities op de halfronde wand van Het Oog, bekleed met houten latten. Deze houten latten werden vervolgens door Rooijakkers gestoomd en gebogen tot een enorme tol. Van het werkproces werd door motion graphic studio OddOne een time-lapse gemaakt en deze werd gebruikt in de videoclip ‘WILSKR8’ van Fresku. 'Vervolgens verplaatste het project zich naar de Eindhovense wijk Woensel. Onder de noemer ‘Woensel Supertoll!’ ging Rooijakkers hier, samen met Fresku, sociaal ontwerpcollectief Tante Netty en lokale buurt- en welzijnsorganisaties masterclasses en workshops organiseren. Zij nodigden buurtbewoners uit om hun eigen drijfveren en ambities te formuleren op planken van Rooijakkers. Daarmee realiseerde hij grote houten zwermen op verschillende plekken in de wijk. Uiteindelijk werd middenin Woensel een permanent kunstwerk gerealiseerd; een ‘supertol’ met handgeschreven teksten van zowel Fresku als wijkbewoners. 'Met het project wilde Rooijakkers een brug slaan tussen het museum en de stad, tussen kunst en urban culture en tussen bewoners en hun leefomgeving. De kunstenaar vertelt: ‘’De tol staat symbool voor de wil, kracht en passie van de mens. Als een tol eenmaal draait, overstijgt hij de zwaartekracht.’’ Met het project in Woensel won hij de Eindhoven Cultuurprijs 2017. 'In 2019 keerde het werk terug in het Van Abbemuseum. Gebruikmakend van planken uit ‘Supertoll!’ en ‘Woensel Supertoll!’ ontwikkelde Rooijakkers een theatrale installatie in de ruim 25 meter hoge toren van het Van Abbemuseum. Een groot deel van het werk is verworven door het museum, met steun van het Mondriaan Fonds. De zwerm en de tol kunnen apart van elkaar worden gepresenteerd.</dc:description><dc:title>Woensel Supertoll!</dc:title><dcterms:created>2013-2019</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>3555</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3555"><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3555"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C12742"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>