<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3526"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3526.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3526"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C12315"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3526.jpg"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3526"><dc:description xml:lang="en">Jonas Staal produced the photo series Anatomy of a Revolution: Rojava (2015) during his first travel to Rojava in 2014. It documents the emergence of radical new institutions since the start of the Rojava Revolution. 'A classroom in the Women’s Academy in Rimêlan, which teaches “jineology,” or the “science of women,” connecting women’s struggles to those of minorities and stateless peoples. The slogan "sembola jinên soresger" translates as “symbols of women warriors.” The portraits above depict revolutionaries Fidan Dogan, Clara Zetkin, Sakine Cansız, Rosa Luxemburg, and Leyla Söylemez . Around are the portraits of martyrs Zilan (Zeynep Kınacı) and Serhildan (Sema Yüce).</dc:description><dc:creator>Jonas Staal</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Anatomy of a Revolution: Rojava</dc:title><dc:identifier>3526</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">diasec print</dc:type><dcterms:created>2015</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De fotoserie Anatomie van een Revolutie: Rojava (2015) realiseerde kunstenaar Jonas Staal tijdens zijn eerste reis naar Rojava in 2014. De serie documenteert het ontstaan van de radicale nieuwe instituties sinds de Revolutie van Rojava. 'Leslokaal in de Vrouwenacademie in Rimêlan, waar ‘jineologie’ wordt gedoceerd, oftewel ‘vrouwenkunde’, waarin de strijd van vrouwen wordt verbonden aan die van minderheden en stateloze volkeren. De slogan 'sembola jinên soresger' kan worden vertaald als ‘symbolen van vrouwenstrijdsters’, en de portretten erboven zijn die van de revolutionairen Fidan Dogan, Clara Zetkin, Sakine Cansız, Rosa Luxemburg en Leyla Söylemez. Rondom hangen de portretten van Rojavaanse martelaren Zilan (Zeynep Kınacı) en Serhildan (Sema Yüce).</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:date>2015</dc:date></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>