<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/84"><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dcterms:created>1913</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>L'équipe de Cardiff</dc:title><dc:creator>Robert Delaunay</dc:creator><dc:date>1913</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">The painting 'L'équipe de Cardiff' by the French artist Robert Delaunay shows fragments of a big wheel, the Eiffel Tower, a biplane and a rugby team. Next to these, the viewer can read legible texts on billboards. In painting all these elements Delaunay used colour and form very freely, leaving out the details. Shapes merge together and colours are sometimes in sharp contrast with each other, while in other cases they are placed side by side in different shades of a single colour. 'In terms of form, 'L'équipe de Cardiff' has some characteristics of Cubism. In a Cubist painting some recognizable outlined shapes can be seen separately as independent fragments. Furthermore, the theme is no longer represented in accordance with the laws of central perspective and different perspectives are combined at the same time to form a new overall picture. Delaunay did not base his work on a single main theme, but juxtaposed different themes to achieve a sense of movement. The French poet and art critic Guilluame Apollinaire used the term “Orphism” for Delaunay’s work to describe the lyrical and colourful variation of Cubism. Delaunay aimed to represent themes such as movement, space and light and to do this he used subjects which were characteristic of the dynamics of the modern era. 'The starting point for this painting was the photograph of a rugby team in a French newspaper. Delaunay combined this element with some of the high points of the technology of the time such as the Eiffel Tower, a biplane and the big wheel. The texts refer to advertisements on walls and billboards in fields. “Astra” is the name of an airplane factory. The words “Magic Paris” evoke the charms of the French capital city. Altogether, the subject has a very earthy and contemporary character: Paris as an exciting city full of novelties and amusement. Delaunay used bright colours to represent this theme. The composition of the painting shows upward movement: the rugby player jumps up and the semi-circular shape of the big wheel draws the viewer’s eyes upwards to the biplane. It is precisely because of the unusual contemporary subject and the new way of painting that Delaunay’s work encountered great resistance from the general public in 1913.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Op het schilderij 'L'équipe de Cardiff' van de Franse kunstenaar Robert Delaunay zijn fragmenten te zien van een reuzenrad, de Eiffeltoren, een dubbeldeks vliegtuigje en een rugbyteam. Daarnaast zijn er opschriften als van reclameborden leesbaar. Delaunay gaat bij het schilderen van al deze elementen vrij om met kleur en vorm. Details laat hij achterwege. Vormen vloeien in elkaar over. Kleuren zijn soms sterk contrasterend, dan weer als nuances van één toon naast elkaar geplaatst. 'Wat vorm betreft heeft 'L'équipe de Cardiff' kenmerken van het kubisme. In een kubistisch schilderij vallen herkenbare, afgebakende vormen uiteen in meer op zichzelf staande fragmenten. Bovendien wordt het motief niet meer weergegeven volgens de wetten van het centraal perspectief. Verschillende aanzichten worden gelijktijdig gecombineerd tot een nieuw geheel. Delaunay gaat niet uit van één hoofdmotief, maar schuift verschillende motieven in elkaar tot een beweeglijk geheel. De Franse dichter en kunstcriticus Guillaume Apollinaire bedenkt voor Delaunays werk de term orfisme, een lyrische, kleurrijke variant op het kubisme. Delaunay wil thema's als beweging, ruimte en licht verbeelden. Hij maakt daarbij gebruik van onderwerpen die typerend zijn voor de dynamiek van de moderne tijd. ' Uitgangspunt voor dit schilderij is een foto van een rugbyteam in een Franse krant. Delaunay combineert dit gegeven met hoogtepunten van techniek als de Eiffeltoren, een vliegtuig en een reuzenrad. Met zijn opschriften verwijst hij naar gevel- en veldreclame. 'Astra' is de naam van een vliegtuigfabriek. De tekst 'Magic Paris' roept de bekoringen van de Franse hoofdstad op. Alles bij elkaar is het onderwerp zeer aards en eigentijds: Parijs als bruisende stad vol nieuwigheden en amusement. Om dit thema te verbeelden gebruikt Delaunay felle kleuren. Het schilderij is in een opwaartse beweging gecomponeerd: de springende rugbyspeler en de halve cirkelvorm van het reuzenrad leiden de blik van de kijker omhoog naar het vliegtuig. Juist vanwege het ongebruikelijke, eigentijdse onderwerp en de nieuwe manier van schilderen roept Delaunays werk in 1913 bij het grote publiek weerstand op.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>198,8 x 135,2 x 7,8 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:identifier>84</dc:identifier></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/84"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0084-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0084-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/84"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C427"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>