<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/400"><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Mi-août', by the French artist Martial Raysse, reveals part of a person: the upper legs, the stomach, part of the right arm and a few fingers of the left hand. The fingers are placed on a newspaper or magazine, and next to it Raysse painted a bathroom slipper which has a foam plastic flower mounted on it. The attributes and the position of the figure reveal that it is a woman in a bathing costume who is lying down, reading. Raysse used an offset print of this as the basis for his work and painted bright unnatural colours over it. The woman’s legs are bright red and her arm is bright yellow. The background consists of different shades of blue and has been painted with short brushstrokes. The subject, the title 'Mi-août' (mid-August) and the bright colours combined with the cool blue, evoke an atmosphere of a sunny seaside holiday. 'Martial Raysse is a member of the group of artists known as “les nouveaux réalistes”, which was founded in Paris in 1960 by the art critic Pierre Restany. These artists used contemporary products from everyday life such as consumer articles and advertising materials as the starting point for their work. In this respect there are similarities with British and American Pop Art. In Pop Art, modern products are depicted, sometimes with the addition of actual objects. In nouveau réalisme, the objects themselves are used to create images. These objects are then processed in different ways by being stacked, pressed or wrapped up so thattheir identity is largely lost. Although Raysse represented himself as a nouveaux réaliste, his work reveals more similarities with Pop Art. 'He presented the viewer with a world full of fine appearances. He created paintings, assemblages, and installations for which he used ingredients from his surroundings: the French Côte d'Azur. Posters of beautiful women advertising suncreams or luxury holidays, beach accessories and cheap jewellery were used to create images which radiated artificiality. In themselves they are already products to make the world look more beautiful than it is, but Raysse added another dimension. He did not paint or construct a sunny scene as in the advertisement, but presented an illusion of this. He undermined the realistic content of his images by using unnatural clashing colours and sharply defined forms, which seemed had a flat effect rather than the character of illusion. The added accessories like the bathroom slippers, false eyelashes or neon tubes emphasise the lack of reality of the scene.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1962</dcterms:created><dc:date>1962</dc:date><dcterms:extent>185,5 x 134,5 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Mi-août' van de Franse kunstenaar Martial Raysse toont een gedeelte van een persoon: de bovenbenen, de buik, een stuk van de rechterarm en een paar vingers van de linkerhand. De vingers rusten op een krant of tijdschrift. Daarnaast is een badslipper geschilderd. Raysse heeft er een schuimplastic bloem op gemonteerd. De attributen en de houding van de figuur verraden dat het hier gaat om een vrouw in badpak die ligt te lezen. Raysse heeft een offsetprint hiervan gebruikt als basis voor zijn werk. Daar heeft hij felle, onnatuurlijke kleuren overheen geschilderd. De benen van de vrouw zijn helder rood, haar arm is fel geel. De achtergrond bestaat uit verschillende kleuren blauw, die met korte toetsen tegen elkaar gezet zijn. Het onderwerp, de titel 'Mi-août' (half augustus) en de felle kleuren in combinatie met het koele blauw, roepen de sfeer op van een zonnige vakantie aan zee. 'Martial Raysse behoort tot de kunstenaarsgroep 'les nouveaux réalistes', die in 1960 door de kunstcriticus Pierre Restany in Parijs wordt opgericht. Deze kunstenaars nemen eigentijdse producten uit het dagelijks leven, zoals consumptieartikelen en reclamemateriaal, als uitgangspunt voor hun werk. Hierin vertonen zij overeenkomst met de Britse en Amerikaanse pop art. Binnen de pop art worden de moderne producten afgebeeld, waarbij soms werkelijke voorwerpen worden toegevoegd. In het nouveau réalisme worden de voorwerpen zelf gebruikt om beelden mee te creëren. Deze objecten ondergaan dan een ingreep als stapelen, samenpersen of inpakken waardoor de identiteit ervan grotendeels verloren gaat. Hoewel Raysse naar buiten treedt als 'nouveau réalist', vertoont zijn werk meer overeenkomst met de pop art. 'Raysse schotelt de kijker een wereld vol schone schijn voor. Hij maakt schilderijen, assemblages en installaties waarvoor hij de ingrediënten ontleent aan zijn leefomgeving: de Franse Côte d'Azur. Posters met mooie vrouwen die reclame maken voor zonnecrème of luxe vakanties, strandaccessoires en goedkope sieraden worden gebruikt om beelden te maken waar de kunstmatigheid vanaf straalt. Het zijn van zichzelf al middelen om de wereld mooier te laten lijken dan zij is, maar Raysse doet er nog een schepje boven op. Hij schildert of bouwt geen zonnig tafereel, zoals in de reclame, maar presenteert de illusie daarvan. Hij ondermijnt het werkelijkheidsgehalte van zijn beelden door het gebruik van niet-natuurlijke, botsende kleuren en haarscherp afgebakende vormen die eerder vlak dan illusionistisch werken. De toegevoegde accessoires als badslippers, valse wimpers of neonbuizen benadrukken de onwerkelijkheid van de voorstelling.</dc:description><dc:creator>Martial Raysse</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">plastic, foam rubber, oil, offset on paper on wood</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">plastic, schuimrubber, olieverf, offset op papier op hout</dc:type><dc:identifier>400</dc:identifier><dc:title>Mi-août</dc:title></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/400"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/400"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0400.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C740"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0400.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>