<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/801"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">80 dia's</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">The work '16th century' by the American artist Robert Barry uses the English language as its subject. With the help of a slide projector, a series of forty words is projected onto the wall one by one. A black slide is projected between two words. Every slide is visible for about 8-10 seconds. The words are in the English language, using the same font and the same size and they are shown in purple. They are words which were used in the English language for the first time in the 16th century. 'Together with the work of Lawrence Weiner and Joseph Kosuth, the work of Robert Barry belongs to the first generation of Conceptual Art. Using the medium of language, these artists examined the function of art and the artist. Barry explored the territory between the visual arts, philosophy and poetry. In his oeuvre he went through a gradual development from a traditional working method to a dematerialized form of art: art in which the reduction of the visual imagery was constantly extended. Initially he made paintings. Then he started to make sculptures with transparent threads. Subsequently he experimented with gases, electromagnetic fields, radio frequencies and radiation. These works of art are imperceptible to our senses but they are certainly real and verifiable. In other words, Barry investigated phenomena such as telepathy and the subconscious. At this stage the material dismantling of his work had become complete. 'Immaterial subjects can only really be described with words. For this reason, language was the most important component in Barry’s work from 1969. He composed series of words on individual sheets or in the form of a book, projected words in series of slides or recorded them onto tape. The words in '16th century' evoke associations in the viewer. The meaning of every word is familiar but it never becomes completely clear what the artist means. It is impossible to determine the links which the artist makes between the different words; there are all sorts of possible interpretations. The viewer has to interpret and develop these concepts on the basis of his own imagination. Barry did not see himself as the creator of a perfect end product, but as a pioneer in a creative thinking process.</dc:description><dc:identifier>801</dc:identifier><dc:title>16th Century</dc:title><dc:creator>Robert Barry</dc:creator><dc:date>1974</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">80 slides</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het werk '16th Century' van de Amerikaanse kunstenaar Robert Barry heeft de Engelse taal als onderwerp. Met behulp van een dia-apparaat wordt een reeks van veertig woorden één voor één op de muur geprojecteerd. Tussen twee woorden wordt er een zwarte dia geprojecteerd. Elke dia is ongeveer acht tot tien seconden zichtbaar. De woorden zijn Engelstalig, hebben hetzelfde lettertype, dezelfde grootte en zijn paars. Het zijn woorden die in de 16e eeuw voor het eerst in de Engelse taal zijn gebruikt. 'Het werk van Robert Barry behoort samen met dat van Lawrence Weiner en Joseph Kosuth tot de eerste generatie conceptuele kunst. Deze kunstenaars onderzoeken met behulp van het medium taal de functie van de kunst en van de kunstenaar. Barry begeeft zich op het grensgebied tussen beeldende kunst, filosofie en poëzie. Hij heeft in zijn oeuvre een geleidelijke ontwikkeling doorgemaakt van een traditionele werkwijze naar een gedematerialiseerde vorm van kunst: een kunst waarbij de reductie van de beeldmiddelen steeds verder is doorgevoerd. Aanvankelijk maakt hij schilderijen. Daarna gaat hij sculpturen maken met doorzichtige draden. Vervolgens experimenteert hij met gassen, elektromagnetische velden, radiofrequenties en stralingen. Deze kunstwerken zijn onvatbaar voor onze zintuigen, maar wel degelijk reëel en verifieerbaar. In andere werken onderzoekt Barry fenomenen als telepathie en het onderbewustzijn. De materiële ontmanteling van zijn werk is dan compleet. 'Immateriële onderwerpen kunnen eigenlijk alleen maar door woorden beschreven worden. Daarom vormt de taal vanaf 1969 de belangrijkste component in Barry's werk. Hij stelt woordreeksen samen op losse bladen of in boekvorm, projecteert woorden in de vorm van een diareeks of spreekt ze in op een geluidsband. De woorden van '16th Century' roepen bij de beschouwer associaties op. De betekenis van ieder woord is bekend, maar nooit wordt precies duidelijk wat de kunstenaar bedoelt. Het verband dat de kunstenaar legt tussen de verschillende woorden is niet te achterhalen; allerlei interpretaties zijn denkbaar. De beschouwer moet zelf vanuit zijn eigen verbeelding deze begrippen nader invullen en uitbouwen. Barry beschouwt zichzelf niet als de maker van een volmaakt eindproduct, maar als gangmaker in een creatief denkproces.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1974</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/801"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1119"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0801-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/801"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0801-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>