<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/430"><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>107,5 x 131,5 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:date>1964</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Groot kwadratenreliëf' by the Dutch artist Jan Schoonhoven is made of papier-mâché. It consists of hundreds of small squares which are all slightly different because they have been made by hand. The relief has been attached to a piece of chipboard and painted white. The light which falls onto this emphasizes the irregularities in the composition, which has a very rigid structure. 'In 1960, the artists Schoonhoven, Armando, Henderikse and Peeters founded the Nul movement. The members of Nul thought that art should come from and be linked to everyday reality and they rejected everything that was personal and expressive which characterized art in the 1950s. They felt a relationship with the Zero artists in Germany, who were looking for an art that reflected reality in an objective way. Space, light and movement were important themes in the Zero movement. Schoonhoven explained: “We wanted an art which everyone could understand. No hierarchy, we opted for order, very objective, art as a product. The aim was to create the foundations of reality in an impersonal way as art.” 'In order to express his ideas Schoonhoven opted for repeated geometric forms, creating structures in which no single element is emphasized. For Schoonhoven it was essential to prevent any preferences, and for this reason he did not isolate any fragments of reality as Armando and Peeters did, but worked with geometric elements and therefore neutral elements which he made himself. He did not wish to present concrete material facts, but show “the essence” of reality. For him, reality was structure and he banned colour: “Combining colours creates a subjective illusion.” The Nul artists were actually aiming for objectivity. Despite the use of neutral forms, a neutral composition and neutral use of colour, Schoonhoven’s reliefs are not sterile. The small irregularities resulting from the fact that the work is made by hand, emphasized by the way light falls on it, gives the work vitality.</dc:description><dc:identifier>430</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Groot kwadratenreliëf' van de Nederlandse kunstenaar Jan Schoonhoven is gemaakt van papier-maché. Het bestaat uit honderden kleine vierkantjes die, doordat ze met de hand gemaakt zijn, allemaal iets van elkaar verschillen. Het reliëf is op een spaanplaat bevestigd en wit geverfd. Het licht dat erop valt, benadrukt de onregelmatigheden in de compositie, die in opzet strak is. 'In 1960 wordt door de kunstenaars Schoonhoven, Armando, Henderikse en Peeters de Nulbeweging opgericht. De leden van Nul vinden dat kunst moet voortkomen uit en aansluiten bij de dagelijkse werkelijkheid. Ze keren zich af van het persoonlijke en expressieve waardoor de kunst in de jaren vijftig gekenmerkt wordt. Ze voelen zich verwant met de kunstenaars van Zero in Duitsland, die zoeken naar een kunst die een objectieve afspiegeling van de werkelijkheid is. Ruimte, licht en beweging zijn belangrijke thema's binnen Zero. "We wilden een kunst die iedereen kon begrijpen. Geen hiërarchie, we kozen voor ordening, heel objectief. Kunst als product", zegt Schoonhoven. "Doel is op onpersoonlijke wijze de werkelijkheid te funderen als kunst ". 'Om zijn ideeën weer te geven kiest Schoonhoven voor geometrische vormen die herhaald worden. Zo ontstaan er structuren waarin geen enkel element de nadruk krijgt. Het vermijden van voorkeur is voor Schoonhoven van wezenlijk belang. Daarom isoleert hij ook geen fragmenten uit de werkelijkheid zoals Armando en Peeters, maar werkt hij met zelfgemaakte, geometrische, dus neutrale elementen. Hij wil geen concreet materieel gegeven tonen, maar de werkelijkheid "in essentie" weergeven. De werkelijkheid is voor hem structuur. Kleur bant hij uit. "Samenvoeging van kleuren schept subjectieve illusie". De kunstenaars van Nul streven juist naar objectiviteit. Ondanks het gebruik van neutrale vormen, een neutrale compositie en neutraal kleurgebruik zijn Schoonhovens reliëfs niet steriel. De kleine oneffenheden, ontstaan door het handwerk en benadrukt door de lichtval, maken het werk levendig.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1964</dcterms:created><dc:creator>Jan Schoonhoven</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">latex paint on papier-mâché on chipboard</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="nl">latexverf op papier-maché op spaanplaat</dc:type><dc:title>Groot kwadratenreliëf</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/430"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0430-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/430"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0430-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C770"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>