<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3367"><dc:description xml:lang="en">This is a portrait of Marcus Garvey, founder of UNIA-ACL (Universal Negro Improvement Association and African Communities League), a successful Black nationalist movement from the 1920s. Iris Kensmil: ‘For the history of Afro- American emancipation the Black nationalists have a significance of their own, which appeals to me and which is the reason I made various works about it. This fascination is perhaps most easily indicated by saying that equality by integration still connotes pursuing white privilege. The Black nationalists stand for a force and a respectability of their own.’</dc:description><dc:identifier>3367</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>140,2 x 110,6 x 3,1 cm</dcterms:extent><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:date>2015</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:title>Here the New Negro begins</dc:title><dc:creator>Iris Kensmil</dc:creator><dcterms:created>2015</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Op dit portret is Marcus Garvey afgebeeld. Hij was oprichter van UNIA-ACL (Universal Negro Improvement Association and African Communities League). Dit was een Black-nationalism-beweging in de jaren twintig van de vorige eeuw met veel aanhang. Kensmil: “Voor de geschiedenis van Afro-Amerikaanse emancipatie hebben de Black nationalists een eigen betekenis, die mij aanspreekt en waarom ik meerdere werken daarover gemaakt heb. Die fascinatie is wellicht het simpelste aan te duiden door te stellen dat gelijkheid door integratie, toch de bijbetekenis heeft van achter het witte privilege aangaan. De Black nationalists staan voor eigen kracht en respectabiliteit.”</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/3367"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3367.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/3367.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C11300"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/3367"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>