<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/767"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/767"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1089"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0767.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0767.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/767"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">synthetische verf op doek</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">This work by Sigmar Polke is a rectangular, vertical painting. The top right-hand corner has been painted an even black, while the rest of the canvas is a monochrome white. At the bottom of the canvas the following words are spelled out in typed letters “Höhere Wesen befahlen: rechte obere Ecke schwarz malen!" Irony and magic are the starting point for Polke’s work. His paintings take a look at existing ideas about the origin of artistic inspiration. Is it divine, is it part of the human psyche, or is it located in the chemistry of the human body? Polke believed that when he painted, there was a relationship between the forces on the canvas which he could not control himself and that the painting determined its own destiny. '“Höhere Wesen befahlen” is above all an ironic reference to the romantic German tradition in which “higher things” play an important role. With regard to this theme, Polke produced installations with texts, amongst other things. One of these read: “I was standing in front of the canvas and wanted to paint flowers. Suddenly I received an order from higher beings: no flowers! Paint flamingos! First, I wanted to paint on, but then I realized that they were being serious.” 'In “Höhere Wesen befahlen” Polke parodied the Hard Edge school of painting of artists such as Elsworth Kelly. Polke rejected Kelly’s geometric abstract paintings, because his works which consist of even fields of colour placed very precisely next to each other, refer to nothing other than themselves. According to Polke, this starting point is too limited. He was actually interested in questions such as how art and reality relate to each other and what the social significance is of art. What makes an artist an artist? The answers he came up with for these questions were different in every new work, resulting in a very varied oeuvre in which he used many different styles of painting all at once.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1969</dcterms:created><dc:title>Höhere Wesen befahlen: rechte obere Ecke schwarz malen!</dc:title><dcterms:extent>151,2 x 126,1 x 3 cm (incl.lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Sigmar Polke</dc:creator><dc:identifier>767</dc:identifier><dc:date>1969</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">synthetic paint on canvas</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit werk van Sigmar Polke is een rechthoekig, verticaal schilderij. De rechter bovenhoek is egaal zwart geschilderd en de rest van het doek is monochroom wit. Onder aan het doek zijn in typeletters de woorden "Höhere Wesen befahlen: rechte obere Ecke schwarz malen!" geschilderd. 'Ironie en magie vormen het uitgangspunt van het werk van Polke. Hij maakt schilderijen met een knipoog naar bestaande ideeën over de oorsprong van de artistieke inspiratie. Is deze goddelijk, ligt zij besloten in de menselijke psyche, of is ze gelegen in de chemie van het menselijk lichaam? Polke denkt dat wanneer hij schildert er op het doek een verhouding van krachten ontstaat waar hij zelf geen vat op heeft en dat het schilderij zijn eigen lot bepaalt. 'Höhere Wesen befahlen...' is vooral een ironische verwijzing naar de romantische Duitse traditie waarin het 'hogere' een belangrijke rol speelt. Rond dit thema heeft Polke onder meer installaties gemaakt met tekstborden. Op een daarvan was te lezen: "Ik stond voor het doek en wilde een bloemstuk schilderen. Toen kreeg ik van hogere wezens een bevel: geen bloemstuk! Flamingo's schilderen! Eerst wilde ik doorschilderen, maar toen begreep ik dat ze het serieus meenden." 'Polke parodieert in 'Höhere Wesen befahlen...' de hard edge schilderkunst van kunstenaars als Elsworth Kelly. Polke wijst de geometrisch abstracte schilderijen van Kelly af, omdat diens werken, bestaand uit haarscherp naast elkaar geplaatste egale kleurvlakken, naar niets anders verwijzen dan naar zichzelf. Volgens Polke is dat uitgangspunt te beperkt. Hij houdt zich juist bezig met vragen als: Hoe verhouden kunst en werkelijkheid zich tot elkaar? Wat heeft kunst maatschappelijk te betekenen? En wat maakt een kunstenaar tot kunstenaar? De antwoorden die hij bedenkt op deze vragen kunnen in elk nieuw werk weer anders zijn. Zo ontstaat er een zeer gevarieerd oeuvre waarin hij vele schilderstijlen door elkaar heen hanteert.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>