<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/944"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1242"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0944.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/944"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0944.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/944"><dc:identifier>944</dc:identifier><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Index 002 (Bxal)' by the group of artists Art and Language consists of 27 sheets of paper which each contains a number of staves and fragments of a text. The work is presented in three layers of nine sheets next to each other. The top layer is printed with black ink, the middle layer with red ink and the lower layer again with black ink. The text, which runs over the various sheets and should be read line by line, serves as a topic for discussion. Statements are made and questions are posed which invite the viewer to think about matters such as the need for language and the function and effect of exchanging thoughts. 'Art &amp; Language is the collective name of a group of artists who produce works in different combinations which consist mainly of critical and polemical texts. They raise issues about the conditions for art and the way in which art functions. By presenting the works as art, Art and Language removes the distinction between art and art criticism and between language and the visual arts. This work was first exhibited in 1973 in New York. In addition to the part described above, it also comprised forms at the time which could be completed by the public in accordance with instructions written by Art &amp; Language. These instructions contained various multiple choices. The additions of the public obtained in this way were seen as being part of the work. 'Art &amp; Language opposed art which removes itself from language, which is produced intuitively and does not ask for or provide any intellectual explanation. The art of Art &amp; Language was based on the ideas of the philosopher Wittgenstein, who was concerned with the truth of propositions. In addition, it was influenced by the thoughts of Karl Marx, particularly those where attention is devoted to the mechanisms in society which cause and maintain forms of incorrect beliefs. 'Between 1972 and 1976 Art &amp; Language made a number of works with the title “Index”. These works were created on the basis of the need to take a critical look at their own work. The viewer is assigned an active role and explicitly invited to think about what is raised for discussion in the work concerned. 'Index 002 (Bxal)' was created at a time that there were divisions within the Art &amp; Language group. Reference was made to this in the fragment of text: “Various groups are fighting bitterly amongst themselves.” In this way, Art &amp; Language also saw itself as a subject for discussion. Because the ideas and thoughts about art had a central place in this group, its work is classified as Conceptual Art.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Index 002 (Bxal)' van de kunstenaarsgroep Art &amp; Language bestaat uit 27 vellen papier die elk een aantal notenbalken bevatten en fragmenten van een tekst. Het werk wordt gepresenteerd in drie lagen van negen vellen naast elkaar. De bovenste laag is gedrukt met zwarte inkt, de middelste met rode, de onderste weer met zwarte inkt. De tekst, die doorloopt over de verschillende vellen en regel voor regel gelezen moet worden, dient als discussiestuk. Er worden stellingen in geponeerd en vragen gesteld die uitnodigen tot nadenken over zaken als de noodzaak van taal en de functie en werking van gedachtewisselingen. 'Art &amp; Language is de verzamelnaam van een groep kunstenaars die in wisselende samenstelling werken produceert. Deze werken bestaan voornamelijk uit tekst. De teksten zijn kritisch en polemisch. Ze werpen vraagstukken op over de voorwaarden vòòr en het functioneren van kunst. Door de werken te presenteren als kunst, heft Art &amp; Language het onderscheid tussen kunst en kunstkritiek, tussen taal en beeldende kunst op. Dit werk is voor het eerst tentoongesteld in 1973 in New York. Buiten het boven beschreven gedeelte, bevatte het toen ook formulieren die door het publiek ingevuld konden worden, volgens een door Art &amp; Language geschreven instructie. Deze instructie bevatte diverse keuzemogelijkheden. De zo verkregen aanvullingen van het publiek werden beschouwd als onderdeel van het werk. 'Art &amp; Language trekt ten strijde tegen kunst die zich onttrekt aan taal; die intuïtief tot stand komt en geen intellectuele uitleg vraagt of geeft. De kunst van Art &amp; Language is gebaseerd op de ideeën van de filosoof Wittgenstein, die zich bezig houdt met de waarheidswaarde van vooronderstellingen. Daarnaast zijn de denkbeelden van Karl Marx van invloed, met name die, waarin aandacht besteed wordt aan de mechanismen in de samenleving die vormen van foutief geloof veroorzaken en in stand houden. 'Tussen 1972 en 1976 maakt Art &amp; Language een aantal werken onder het motto index. Deze werken ontstaan vanuit de behoefte het eigen werk kritisch onder de loep te nemen. De toeschouwer krijgt een actieve rol toebedeeld en wordt expliciet uitgenodigd tot meedenken over datgene wat in het betreffende werk ter sprake komt. Index 002 (Bxal) ontstaat in een tijd dat binnen de groep Art &amp; Language verdeeldheid heerst. Hiernaar wordt verwezen via het tekstfragment "Various groups are fighting bitterly amongst themselves". Zo stelt Art &amp; Language ook zichzelf ter discussie. Omdat het idee en het denken over kunst centraal staan in het werk van deze groep, wordt hun werk gerekend tot de conceptuele kunst.</dc:description><dc:date>1973</dc:date><dcterms:extent>(geïnstalleerd kunstwerk) 144 x 625,5 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Index 002 (Bxal)</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">offset op papier</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">offset on paper</dc:type><dcterms:created>1973</dcterms:created><dc:creator>Art &amp; Language</dc:creator></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>