<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1124"><dc:date>1973-1974</dc:date><dc:creator>Bernd &amp; Hilla Becher</dc:creator><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:created>1973-1974</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">This work by the German artists Bernd &amp; Hilla Becher consists of 85 photographs subdivided into 19 groups which together systematically depict an entire coalmine. One group consists of ten photographs which survey the total complex and give an impression of where it is located in the landscape; the other groups each show part of the complex, such as the pithead, the coke oven and the cooling tower. The more complex the particular section, the more photographs are devoted to it. They are each taken from a different angle and provide a tour around the whole place at a specific distance. For example, the group devoted to the pithead consists of eight photographs. Four of these are taken from the front, so that one side is shown face on, and these alternate with four photographs taken diagonally showing two sides of the pithead in perspective. The photographs are presented in blocks. 'Bernd &amp; Hilla Becher recorded the “Zeche Hannibal” in 1973 and 1974 when the mine was shut but not yet demolished. From 1959 the Bechers photographed industrial architecture including water towers, gasworks, furnaces and mineshafts. They presented the objects as neutrally as possible and the photographs were always in black and white. The object is shown as far as possible in the centre of the image and the photographs are taken against a dull sky so that the weather conditions do not bring about any dramatic effects. The Bechers worked with a special technical camera which made it possible to correct strong distortions of perspective. They wanted their photographs to give as much clear information as possible about the objects that were shown. They usually adopted a position high up so that the viewer also gains information about the situation in the field. 'Bernd &amp; Hilla Becher were not concerned with taking photographs with any artistic or aesthetic merit; the photography served merely as a means to record and inventorise things. In this way, information was available about them even when the objects that were photographed no longer existed. Despite their aim for neutrality, the Bechers’ photographic series had a very personal atmosphere and that is why they are presented as art. Because of the fact that the Bechers’ work is a consistent investigation into a specific field with clear criteria as regards design, it can be related to the Conceptual Art and Minimal Art of artists such as LeWitt, Brouwn and Buren.</dc:description><dc:identifier>1124</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">zwart-wit fotografie</dc:type><dcterms:extent>(38x) 46,3 x 56.3 x 2,3 cm (incl lijst / frame) (47x) 56,3 x 46,3 x 2,3 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit werk van de Duitse kunstenaars Bernd en Hilla Becher bestaat uit 85 foto's die in 19 groepen zijn onderverdeeld. Samen brengen zij een gehele kolenmijn systematisch in beeld. Eén groep toont tien overzichtsfoto's die een indruk geven van het totale complex en hoe dat in het landschap ligt. De overige groepen geven telkens een onderdeel van het complex weer zoals de schachtbok, de cokesoven, de koeltoren. Hoe complexer het onderdeel is, des te meer foto's worden eraan gewijd. Ze zijn telkens vanuit een andere hoek genomen en geven, met een vaste afstand, een rondgang om het object weer. De groep gewijd aan de schachtbok bijvoorbeeld bestaat uit acht foto's. Vier zijn er frontaal genomen waardoor er één zijde van de bok recht in beeld staat. Deze worden afgewisseld met vier diagonaal genomen foto's die twee zijden van de bok in perspectief weergeven. De foto's worden in blokken gepresenteerd. 'Bernd en Hilla Becher maken de opnames van 'Zeche Hannibal' in 1973 en 1974. De mijn is dan gesloten maar nog niet gesloopt. De Bechers fotograferen sinds 1959 industriële architectuur, o.m. watertorens, gashouders, hoogovens en schachttorens. Ze geven de gekozen objecten zo neutraal mogelijk weer. De foto's zijn altijd zwart-wit. Het object wordt zoveel mogelijk midden in beeld gebracht. De foto's worden gemaakt bij een egaal bewolkte lucht, zodat de weersgesteldheid geen dramatische effecten teweeg brengt. De Bechers werken met een technische camera, die het mogelijk maakt sterke perspectivische vertekeningen te corrigeren. Ze willen via hun foto's zoveel en zo duidelijk mogelijke informatie geven over de in beeld gebrachte objecten. Ze kiezen meestal voor een hoog standpunt, waardoor je als beschouwer ook informatie krijgt over de ligging op het terrein. 'Het gaat Bernd en Hilla Becher niet om het maken van foto's met een artistieke of esthetische waarde. De fotografie dient puur als registratiemiddel; als middel waarmee dingen geïnventariseerd en gedocumenteerd kunnen worden. Zo kan er kennis van genomen worden, ook wanneer de gefotografeerde objecten niet meer bestaan. Ondanks hun streven naar neutraliteit, hebben de fotoseries van de Bechers een zeer eigen gezicht. Daarom worden ze als kunst gepresenteerd. Vanwege het feit dat het werk van de Bechers een consequent onderzoek is op een specifiek terrein met duidelijke criteria t.a.v. de vormgeving, kan het in verband gebracht worden met de conceptuele kunst en de minimal art van kunstenaars als LeWitt, Brouwn en Buren.</dc:description><dc:title>Steinkohlebergwerk - Zeche Hannibal - Bochum-Hofstede Ruhrgebiet</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">black-and-white photography</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1124"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1124"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1124-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1124-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1396"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>