<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1122"><dcterms:created>1976</dcterms:created><dc:title>Torquato Tasso</dc:title><dc:identifier>1122</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">The bottom half of this painting by the German artist A.R. Penck is largely taken up by the silhouette of a nude woman painted in green and blue paint. On her body a few simple signs and a head have been painted in black. From her feet, Penck painted a sort of chain of signs, also in black, which stretches from the bottom-left to the top-right corner of the painting. In addition, spread over the entire canvas there are strokes of yellow and red paint. The text “ROMA AETERNA ODER ERLEUCHTUNG des TORQUATO TASSO”, and the signature “RALF” can be seen at the bottom right. 'From 1961 Penck developed a sign language which was related both to prehistoric rock paintings and to contemporary pictograms. He considered art as a means of communication and aimed for an iconography which could be understood by a broad general public. He created images to draw the viewer’s attention to the truth and the reality he lived in. Up to 1980 Penck lived in the former East Germany, where the freedom of the individual was greatly restricted, both politically and artistically. He was already in contact then with the West German painters, Immendorf and Baselitz, and in 1980 he defected to the west. 'His work is sometimes classified as Neo-Expressionism. The painting 'Torquato Tasso' can be seen as a plea for freedom and liberty. Torquato Tasso was a 16th-century writer/poet and in his epic tale “Gerusalemme liberata” he wrote the history of the First Crusade. The German poet Goethe devoted a play to Tasso in which the protagonist is the artist who comes into conflict with society because of his own wilfulness. Penck’s fear was that the freedom of human existence was threatened by uncontrollable systems, and he combated this with images. His works are direct expressions of his thoughts and feelings. Sometimes the message can be understood directly, but sometimes more prior knowledge is required. A work such as 'Torquato Tasso' not only expresses the story behind it. The way in which it is painted – semi-figurative and semi-abstract – in bright colours and with strong movements, can be seen as a scream for freedom.</dc:description><dc:date>1976</dc:date><dc:type xml:lang="en">acrylic on canvas</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="nl">temperaverf op doek</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De onderste helft van dit schilderij van de Duitse kunstenaar A.R. Penck wordt grotendeels in beslag genomen door het silhouet van een naakte vrouw, geschilderd met groene en blauwe verf. Op haar lichaam zijn met zwarte verf enkele eenvoudige tekens en een kop geschilderd. Vanaf haar voeten heeft Penck, eveneens met zwart, een soort keten van tekens weergegeven die zich uitstrekt van linksonder naar de rechter bovenhoek van het schilderij. Verder zijn er, verspreid over het doek, vegen gele en rode verf aangebracht. Rechtsonder is de tekst 'ROMA AETERNA ODER DIE ERLEUCHTUNG des TORQUATO TASSO' te lezen, en de signatuur RALF. 'A.R. Penck ontwikkelt vanaf 1961 een tekentaal die zowel verwantschap heeft met prehistorische rotstekeningen als met eigentijdse pictogrammen. Hij beschouwt kunst als middel tot communicatie en streeft naar een beeldtaal die door een breed publiek begrepen kan worden. Hij maakt beelden om de kijker te attenderen op de waarheid, op de werkelijkheid waarin hij leeft. Tot 1980 woont Penck in het voormalige Oost-Duitsland. Daar is de vrijheid van het individu sterk beperkt, zowel in politiek als in artistiek opzicht. Penck heeft dan al contact met de Westduitse schilders Immendorf en Baselitz. In 1980 gaat hij naar het westen. Zijn werk wordt wel gerekend tot het neo-expressionisme. 'Het schilderij 'Torquato Tasso' kan gezien worden als een pleidooi voor bevrijding en vrijheid. Torquato Tasso was een zestiende-eeuwse Italiaanse schrijver/dichter. Hij schreef in zijn epos 'Gerusalemme liberata' de geschiedenis van de eerste kruistocht. De Duitse dichter Goethe wijdde een toneelstuk aan Tasso. Centraal daarin staat de kunstenaar die door zijn eigenzinnigheid in conflict raakt met de samenleving. Pencks angst is dat de vrijheid binnen het menselijk bestaan bedreigd wordt door oncontroleerbare systemen. Daartegen trekt hij met beelden ten strijde. Zijn werken zijn directe uitingen van zijn gedachten en gevoelens. Soms is de boodschap direct leesbaar, soms is er wat meer voorkennis vereist. Een doek als 'Torquato Tasso' spreekt niet alleen via het verhaal erachter. De manier waarop het geschilderd is, half figuratief, half abstrstract, in heldere kleuren en met een heftig gebaar, kun je beschouwen als een schreeuw om vrijheid.</dc:description><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>A. R. Penck</dc:creator><dcterms:extent>283,5 x 283 x 3,8 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1122"><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1395"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1122"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1122.JPG"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1122.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>