<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/94"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/94"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0094.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C437"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0094.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/94"><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:date>1922</dc:date><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:creator>Theo van Doesburg</dc:creator><dc:identifier>94</dc:identifier><dcterms:extent>45,5 x 43,3 cm 72,5 x 70,2 x 5,7 cm (incl. lijst)</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Compositie XXII</dc:title><dcterms:created>1922</dcterms:created><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Composition XXII' by Theo van Doesburg consists of nine rectangular planes: one red, one ochre, one blue, two white, two black and two grey planes. These planes are interrelated in a particular ratio. The painting is almost square, approximately 45 x 45 cm. 'Van Doesburg’s use of shape and colour in 'Composition XXII' is in accordance with the starting points of Neo-Plasticism. The followers of this movement endeavoured to expose universal values. They saw art which provided an insight, in which concepts such as harmony and balance have a central place as a model for a better society. In 1917 Van Doesburg founded the journal De Stijl. In this journal artists, architects and writers wrote articles looking for new art forms with a universal value. They used abstract shapes and restricted themselves to straight lines and right-angled corners. Their palette consisted of the primary colours, red, yellow and blue and the non-colours, white, grey and black and Van Doesburg applied these starting points rather freely. For example, the yellow plane in 'Composition XXII' is not a primary yellow, but an ochre yellow. 'In addition to being a painter, Van Doesburg was also an architect, typographer, designer and poet. His interest in architecture is tangible in 'Composition XXII'. The planes are not outlined as they are in Mondrian’s work and they are not set separately on a background as in Van der Leck’s, but are placed directly next to each other. The differences in colour and tone result in an interplay of the planes which recede or project in relation to each other. Van Doesburg aimed to achieve a spatial effect in the painting extending forward so that the viewer imagines he is in the painting.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Compositie XXII van Theo van Doesburg bestaat uit negen rechthoekige vlakken: een rood, een okergeel, een blauw, twee witte, twee zwarte en twee grijze. De vlakken staan in een bepaalde maatverhouding tot elkaar. Het schilderij is bijna vierkant, ongeveer 45x45cm. 'Van Doesburgs vorm- en kleurgebruik in Compositie XXII is in overeenstemming met de uitgangspunten van het neoplasticisme. De aanhangers van deze stroming streven naar het blootleggen van universele waarden. Inzichtelijke kunst, waarin begrippen als harmonie en evenwicht centraal staan, zien zij als model voor een betere samenleving. In 1917 richt Van Doesburg het tijdschrift De Stijl op. Hierin komen kunstenaars, architecten en schrijvers aan het woord die zoeken naar nieuwe kunstvormen met een universele waarde. Ze maken gebruik van abstracte vormen en beperken zich tot rechte lijnen en rechte hoeken. Hun palet bestaat uit de primaire kleuren rood, geel en blauw, en de niet-kleuren wit, grijs en zwart. Van Doesburg gaat enigszins vrij met deze uitgangspunten om. Het gele vlak in 'Compositie XXII' is niet primair geel, maar okergeel. 'Naast schilder is Van Doesburg ook architect, typograaf, vormgever en dichter. In Compositie XXII wordt zijn interesse in architectuur voelbaar. De vlakken worden niet begrensd door lijnen zoals bij Mondriaan; ze staan ook niet los op een ondergrond zoals bij van der Leck; ze worden direct tegen elkaar geplaatst. Door verschillen in kleur en toon ontstaat er een spel van vlakken die ten opzichte van elkaar wijken of naar voren komen. Van Doesburg streeft naar een ruimtelijke werking van het schilderij naar voren, waardoor de toeschouwer zich in het schilderij waant.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>