<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1519"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1519"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1519.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1519.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1740"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1519"><dc:date>1984-1985</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">When you look at the painting 'Emma de Los Angeles' by Eugène Leroy you see the image of a naked woman appearing out of a large amount of paint. The painting is composed of short strokes of oil paint, which have been applied evenly in many layers all over the canvas. Where the light colours converge, the body of the woman becomes visible. There are no sharp outlines. The image merges into the background, as does the face and her dark hair. There are no details visible either in the figure of the woman, or in the environment. 'For Leroy, the representation and the paint as a material are equally important. He explained: “My task is to conceal the anecdote in an interaction with the painting, an interaction that takes place little by little and needs time, but nearly always only produces the ash of a fire which mercifully glows through it or by good fortune…” Leroy based this on a picture, which he saw in reality and which moved him. However he did not reflect this directly and only allowed a trace of the original emotion to be reflected in his painting. In an almost endless process of revelation and concealment, of painting and painting over, the motif is almost completely concealed in the paint. 'Light plays an important role in Leroy’s work; the light that is suggested by applying light colours, but also the effect of light and shadow which is produced on the painted surface as a result of the thickness of the paint. Leroy explained: “I really wanted to make a painting which has its own inner light.” He liked to work with backlighting because this blurs the difference between what is illuminated and what is concealed, what is secret and what is clearly present. Leroy is unique in the history of art. He followed his own path without interruption, independently of contemporary styles or movements. The creative process has a central place in his paintings. It was difficult for him to determine when a painting was finished. It was the act of painting itself that he was concerned with. Like reality, this is never completed. It is a search for an ideal, which can only be realized very briefly (when a canvas is finished).</dc:description><dcterms:extent>194,9 x 130,1 x 8,5 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Eugène Leroy</dc:creator><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Wanneer je het schilderij 'Emma de Los Angeles' van Eugène Leroy bekijkt, zie je vanuit een grote hoeveelheid verf het beeld van een naakte vrouw opdoemen. Het schilderij is opgebouwd uit korte streken olieverf die, gelijkmatig verdeeld over het doek, in vele lagen over elkaar zijn aangebracht. Waar de lichte kleuren zich verdichten, wordt het lichaam van de vrouw zichtbaar. Het heeft geen scherpe contouren. Het gaat over in de achtergrond, evenals het gezicht en de donkere haarpartij. Er zijn geen details zichtbaar, noch in de gestalte van de vrouw, noch in de omgeving. 'Voor Leroy zijn de voorstelling en de verf als materie even belangrijk. Hij zegt: "Mijn taak is het de anekdote te verbergen, in een wisselwerking met het schilderij, een wisselwerking, die zich stukje bij beetje voltrekt, die tijd nodig heeft en die toch, bijna altijd, slechts de as oplevert van een vuur dat er, dankzij geluk of genade, doorheen gloeit...". Leroy gaat uit van een beeld dat hij in werkelijkheid gezien heeft, dat hem ontroert. Hij geeft dat echter niet op een directe manier weer, maar laat slechts een spoor van de oorspronkelijke emotie doorklinken in zijn schilderij. In een bijna eindeloos proces van tonen en verbergen, van schilderen en wegschilderen, raakt het motief bijna volledig in de verfmassa verscholen. 'In Leroy's werk speelt licht een belangrijke rol; het licht dat hij suggereert door lichte kleuren op te brengen, maar ook de licht- en schaduwwerking die op het geschilderde oppervlak ontstaat door de dikte van de verf. "Ik wilde werkelijk een schilderij maken dat zijn eigen innerlijke licht heeft", zegt Leroy. Hij werkt graag met tegenlicht, omdat juist daarbij het verschil tussen wat verlicht en wat verborgen is, wat heimelijk en wat duidelijk aanwezig is, vervaagt. Leroy is een eenling binnen de kunstgeschiedenis. Hij gaat onverstoorbaar de weg die hij vindt dat hij gaan moet, los van actuele stijlen of stromingen. In zijn schilderijen staat het maakproces centraal. Het is voor hem moeilijk te bepalen wanneer een schilderij af is. Het schilderen zelf is waar het om gaat. Dit is, evenals de werkelijkheid, nooit voltooid. Het is een zoektocht naar een ideaal dat hooguit kortstondig (wanneer een doek af is) verwezenlijkt wordt.</dc:description><dc:identifier>1519</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dc:title>Emma de los Angeles</dc:title><dcterms:created>1984-1985</dcterms:created></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>