<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1452"><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1682"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1452.JPG"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1452.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1452"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1452"><dc:date>1982</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">'La caduta di Icaro' by the Italian artist Giulio Paolini consists of nine perspex plinths supporting an antique chair which are arranged in three rows of three. There are eight chairs standing and one is turned over with its seat pointing down. Above this, there are white paintings hanging from the ceiling by a nylon thread and the symbol of one of the nine planets in our solar system is shown on the back of each canvas. The size and position of each canvas corresponds to the place occupied by the planet concerned in the solar system and only the canvas with the “earth” lies on the ground, with the jacket of an old Italian suit lying on it. The other parts of the suit are hanging spread out over the other canvases. 'The title of this work refers to the story of the mythological figure Icarus. With wings made of feathers and wax, Icarus flew too close to the sun, despite his father’s warning. The wax melted, the feathers came unstuck and Icarus plunged into the sea. Paolini provides a free version of this story. He said: “The protagonist (Icarus) who is performing in this “scena di conversazione” falls onto the canvas on the ground (the Earth) in his attempt to touch Venus.” In Paolini’s version it is therefore not the sun, but Venus, the goddess of love, who is the cause of Icarus’s fall. Paolini does not present Icarus as a person. The “falling” objects in combination with the title tell his story. 'Paolini places an existing story and existing objects in a new light. In this installation the arrangement and structure are important elements. They make the work comprehensible. However, they do not explain it. With 'La caduta di Icaro' Paolini raises questions about our art and culture. Is art too far removed from the everyday world we live in, just like Icarus? Is an artist who tries to achieve a higher ideal doomed to fall back to the earth? Paolini’s work is about art and tradition and about the relationship between art and reality. In this respect it corresponds with the work of other Italian artists who became known in the late 1960s by the name Arte Povera. They considered it their task to open the public’s eyes to processes taking place in reality.</dc:description><dc:creator>Giulio Paolini</dc:creator><dc:title>La caduta di Icaro</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="nl">9 plexiglazen sokkels, 9 stoelen, 9 opgespannen doeken, 1 rokkostuum</dc:type><dcterms:created>1982</dcterms:created><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:identifier>1452</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">9 plexiglass socles, 9 chairs, 9 stretched canvasses, 1 dinner jacket</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'La caduta di Icaro' van de Italiaanse kunstenaar Giulio Paolini bestaat uit negen perspex sokkels die een antieke stoel dragen. Ze staan opgesteld in drie rijen van drie. Acht stoelen staan rechtop; een ligt er met de zitting naar beneden. Boven dit geheel hangen witte schilderijen met een nylondraad aan het plafond. Op de achterzijde van elk doek staat het symbool van een van de negen planeten uit ons zonnestelsel. De grootte en positie van ieder doek komt overeen met de plek die de desbetreffende planeet in het zonnestelsel inneemt, alleen het doek 'aarde' ligt op de grond. Daarop ligt de jas van een oud Italiaans rokkostuum. De overige delen van het kostuum hangen verspreid over de andere doeken. 'De titel van dit werk verwijst naar het verhaal van de mythologische figuur Icarus. Met vleugels, gemaakt van veren en was vliegt Icarus ondanks de waarschuwing van zijn vader te dicht bij de zon. De was smelt, de veren laten los en Icarus stort in zee. Paolini geeft een vrije versie van dit verhaal. Hij zegt: "De hoofdfiguur (Icarus), die in deze 'scena di conversazione' optreedt, valt bij zijn poging Venus aan te raken, op het doek op de grond (de Aarde)". In Paolini's versie veroorzaakt dus niet de zon maar Venus, de godin van de liefde, de val van Icarus. Paolini brengt Icarus niet als persoon in beeld. De 'vallende' voorwerpen in combinatie met de titel vertellen zijn verhaal. 'Paolini plaatst een bestaand verhaal en bestaande voorwerpen in een nieuw licht. Ordening en structuur zijn binnen deze installatie belangrijke elementen. Ze maken het werk overzichtelijk. Ze verklaren het echter niet. Met 'La caduta di Icaro' roept Paolini vragen op over onze kunst en cultuur. Verwijdert de kunst zich, net als Icarus, te ver van onze dagelijkse leefwereld? Is de kunstenaar die een hoger ideaal probeert te bereiken, gedoemd terug te vallen op aarde? Paolini's werk gaat over kunst en traditie, en over de relatie tussen kunst en werkelijkheid. In dit opzicht sluit het aan bij het werk van andere Italiaanse kunstenaars die eind jaren zestig onder de noemer arte povera bekendheid krijgen. Zij zien het als hun taak via hun werk het publiek de ogen te openen voor processen in de werkelijkheid.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>