<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1960"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1960"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1960.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2136"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1960.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1960"><dc:creator>Rachel Whiteread</dc:creator><dc:title>Valley</dc:title><dc:date>1990</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Valley' by Rachel Whiteread is composed of six blocks of plaster which reveal the imprint of a bathtub when they are placed together. The outsides form a rectangular block. The hollow where the bathtub was originally is covered with a glass plate that fits exactly. Valley evokes associations with a grave because of the hollow shape and the covering with a glass plate, which also refers to the presence of something valuable. Because of the height of the work – Whiteread makes the sculpture higher than a normal bathtub – the visitor does not see immediately what has been covered. It is only when he is right at the edge that the empty space becomes visible. Dividing the sculpture into blocks also contributes to the sense that you are looking at something from the past, at valuable fragments of something that has been lost. 'Since 1988, Whiteread has been making sculptures consisting of casts of parts of an interior, or of large objects for human use, such as tables, bathtubs, mattresses or an entire living room. Normally a cast is made using a mould so that it has the exact shape of the original. However, she presents the mould as a sculpture. The materials she chooses include plaster, wax and rubber. Her sculptures are an immediate reminder of the original, but they are not copies of it, and in this way her objects transcend their function as everyday artefacts and become a sort of monument. She said: “My intention was to give certain spaces a weight they never had, but it is also to do with retaining a presence. In that sense it certainly is about maintaining something, and materials such as rubber and plaster have always been associated with this.” 'The objects she used as a starting point are never new. They reveal traces of use in the form of minor damage, patches of rust, or hairs left behind. These traces can be discovered in Whiteread’s sculptures, which means that you are not looking at the object, purely as a shape, but also at the use of that object, and therefore the memories of human activities. The human presence is still almost tangible. In this respect, Whiteread said: “I use furniture as a metaphor for people.” Because of their literal absence, the sculptures also evoke feelings of loss, desolation and even death. Whiteread’s sculptures mean that you can feel absence; they are monuments to memory.</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="en">plaster, glass</dc:type><dc:identifier>1960</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">gips, glas</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Valley' van Rachel Whiteread is opgebouwd uit zes blokken gips die, tegen elkaar gelegd, de afdruk van een badkuip laten zien. De buitenkanten vormen een rechthoekig blok. De holte waar de badkuip heeft gezeten, is afgedekt met een precies passende glasplaat. 'Valley' roept associaties op met een graf door de vorm van de holle ruimte en de afdekking daarvan met een glasplaat. De afdekking met glas refereert ook aan de aanwezigheid van iets kostbaars. Door de hoogte van het werk -Whiteread maakt de sculptuur hoger dan een badkuip gewoonlijk is- ziet de bezoeker niet onmiddellijk wat er afgedekt is. Pas wanneer hij vlak bij de rand is, wordt de lege ruimte zichtbaar. De verdeling van de sculptuur in blokken draagt bij aan het gevoel dat je naar iets uit het verleden kijkt, naar waardevolle fragmenten van iets dat verloren gegaan is. 'Whiteread maakt sinds 1988 sculpturen die bestaan uit afgietsels van interieurdelen of grote voorwerpen voor menselijk gebruik, zoals tafels, badkuipen matrassen, of een hele woonkamer. Gewoonlijk wordt een afgietsel gemaakt met behulp van een mal. Het afgietsel krijgt zo exact de vorm van het origineel. Whiteread presenteert echter de mal als sculptuur. Als materiaal kiest ze gips, was of rubber. Haar sculpturen roepen direct het origineel in herinnering, maar zijn geen kopie daarvan. Hierdoor overstijgen Whitereads objecten hun functie als dagelijks gebruiksvoorwerp en worden het een soort monumenten. Ze zegt: " Mijn intentie was bepaalde ruimtes een gewicht te verlenen dat ze nooit gehad hebben. Maar het heeft ook te maken met het bewaren van een aanwezigheid. In die zin gaat het wel degelijk over in stand houden, iets waarmee materialen als rubber en gips altijd al geassocieerd werden." 'De voorwerpen die Whiteread als uitgangspunt neemt, zijn nooit nieuw. Ze vertonen sporen van gebruik in de vorm van kleine beschadigingen, roestplekken of achtergebleven haren. Deze sporen zijn terug te vinden in Whitereads sculpturen. Je kijkt daardoor niet puur naar het object als vorm, maar ook naar het gebruik van dat object en daarmee naar de herinnering aan menselijk handelen. De menselijke aanwezigheid is nog bijna voelbaar. Whiteread zegt hierover: "Ik gebruik meubilair als metafoor voor mensen." Door de letterlijke afwezigheid daarvan roepen de sculpturen ook gevoelens op van verlatenheid, verlies of zelfs dood. Whitereads beelden maken afwezigheid voelbaar. Het zijn monumenten voor herinnering.</dc:description><dcterms:created>1990</dcterms:created><dcterms:extent>94,7 x 96,6 x 186 cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>