<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/1153"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1153.JPG"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C1412"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1153"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/1153.JPG"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/1153"><dc:date>1982</dc:date><dcterms:extent>200 x 652 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:title>Schüttbild</dc:title><dcterms:created>1982</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="nl">acrylverf op doek</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">Two canvases of two by three metres form this 'Schüttbild' by the Austrian artist Hermann Nitsch. They are displayed next to each other and are largely covered in blood-red paint. Looking at the way the paint is spattered, we can conclude that it was probably hurled at the canvas. In various places, someone then walked through the paint in their bare feet, as shown by the footprints on the canvas. 'From 1960 Hermann Nitsch was involved in “Aktionsmalerei”. He made paintings with rusty brown or blood-red paint and wax, which he sometimes applied with his hands and feet, and he often hurled thin paint directly at the canvas so that it dripped or spattered. In contrast with American action painting, in which the paint was seen only as paint, Nitsch’s canvases often provoke horror because of their similarity to fresh or clotted blood. Like Brus and Schwarzkogler, Nitsch was a member of the Wiener Aktionismus. These artists tried to break down taboos and push back the boundaries with their shocking actions and performances in order to increase the freedom of the individual. Photographs of Nitsch’s performances and remnants of these in the form of gory bandages, chalices and chasubles are presented in exhibitions so that the visitor can recreate them in his imagination. 'From 1963 Nitsch organized performances entitled “Orgien Mysterien Theater”, in which people performed naked or wrapped up in clothes and he used both living and dead animals. Men and animals were subjected to crucifixion rituals and the participants were smeared with blood and with the organs removed from the animals. The whole performance was accompanied by music made on location, and wine flowed freely. These performances could last several hours or even days. They were the preparation for Nitsch’s ultimate artworks: the six-day performance, which had a mystical and orgiastic character. The participants entered into a trance and, liberated from bourgeois conventions, they allowed their energy free rein. The performance served as a transfiguration of life. Nitsch’s “Orgien Mysterien Theater” is a combination of provocation and devotion. It is based strongly on Christian rituals, classical mythology and alchemical practices.</dc:description><dc:identifier>1153</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Twee doeken van twee bij drie meter vormen dit 'Schüttbild' van de Oostenrijkse kunstenaar Hermann Nitsch. Ze worden tegen elkaar aan gepresenteerd, en zijn grotendeels bedekt met bloedrode verf. De verf is er gezien de vele spatten waarschijnlijk met een heftig gebaar tegenaan gesmeten. Op diverse plaatsen is er vervolgens met blote voeten door de verf gelopen, getuige de voetafdrukken op het doek. 'Hermann Nitsch houdt zich vanaf 1960 bezig met 'Aktionsmalerei'. Hij maakt schilderijen met roestbruine of bloedrode verf en was, die hij soms met handen en voeten aanbrengt. Vaak ook gooit hij dunne verf direct tegen het doek. Deze druipt of spat dan uit. In tegenstelling tot de Amerikaanse action painting, waarin de verf zich uitsluitend als verf laat bekijken, wekken Nitsch' doeken veelal afschuw op door hun gelijkenis met vers of geronnen bloed. Nitsch behoort evenals Brus en Schwarzkogler tot het Wiener Aktionismus. Deze kunstenaars proberen via shockerende acties en performances taboes te doorbreken en grenzen te verleggen om daarmee de vrijheid van het individu te vergroten. Foto's van Nitsch' performances en overblijfselen daarvan in de vorm van besmeurde verbanden, kelken en kazuifels worden in tentoonstellingen gepresenteerd. Zo kan de bezoeker zich daar een voorstelling van maken. 'Sinds 1963 organiseert Nitsch performances onder de noemer Orgien Mysterien Theater. Hierin laat hij mensen naakt of in doeken gewikkeld optreden en gebruikt hij levende en dode dieren. Mens en dier worden onderworpen aan kruisigingrituelen. De deelnemers worden met bloed en met de uitgenomen organen van de dieren besmeurd. Het geheel wordt begeleid door ter plekke gemaakte muziek en er is rijkelijk wijn aanwezig. Deze optredens kunnen enkele uren tot enkele dagen duren. Het zijn voorbereidingen op Nitsch' ultieme kunstwerk: het zes-dagen-spel. Dit heeft een mystiek en orgiastisch karakter. De deelnemers raken in een roes en laten, bevrijd van burgerlijke conventies, hun energie de vrije loop. Het spel dient als verheerlijking van het leven. Nitsch' Orgien Mysterien Theater is een mengeling van provocatie en devotie. Het leunt sterk op christelijke rituelen, klassieke mythologie en alchemistische praktijken.</dc:description><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:creator>Hermann Nitsch</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">acrylic on canvas</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>