<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2064"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dcterms:extent>40,5 x 73 x 62,5 cm</dcterms:extent><dcterms:created>1993</dcterms:created><dc:creator>Karin Arink</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">paraffin wax, clay</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:description xml:lang="nl">De titel van dit werk geeft aanleiding deze sculptuur te zien als een gekromde menselijke torso. Maar als je de details bekijkt, komen er allerlei vragen op. Aan de binnenkant van de kromming zie je twee ronde vormen die op billen lijken. Aan de buitenkant, tussen wat stompen van armen kunnen zijn, is een ruggengraat waarneembaar. Het is moeilijk te bepalen of het een zich strekkende of juist in elkaar buigende figuur is. De gekrulde vorm doet ook denken aan een larve of engerling, het stadium waarin een insect zich voorbereidt op een nieuwe levensfase. 'Karin Arink is geïnteresseerd in dingen waarin tegengestelde krachten samenkomen. Dingen als metamorfosen en hermafrodieten, mechanismen of spelingen van de natuur die een merkwaardige vormverandering in zich dragen. Haar beelden gaan over kracht en kwetsbaarheid, over maakbaarheid en onvermogen, begrippen die tegengesteld lijken, maar zich hier verenigen. De incomplete en voor meerdere uitleg vatbare gedaante draagt de mogelijkheid van groei en verandering in zich. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:identifier>2064</dc:identifier><dc:date>1993</dc:date><dc:title>My neck, my back curve silently</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="en">The title of this work leads us to view this sculpture as a curved human torso, but when you examine the details, all kinds of questions arise. On the inside of the curve you can see two round shapes resembling buttocks. On the outside, between what may be stumps of arms, you can make out a spine. It is difficult to determine whether the figure is stretching or hunched up. The curled up shape is also reminiscent of a larva or a grub; the stage in which an insect prepares for a new phase in life. 'Karin Arink is interested in things where opposing forces come together. Things like metamorphoses and hermaphrodites, mechanisms or accidents of nature that entail a striking change of shape. Her images are about strength and vulnerability, about the ability to create and powerlessness; concepts that may seem opposite, but which come together here. The form, which is both incomplete and open to multiple interpretations, holds within itself the potential for growth and change. '[2020]</dc:description><dc:type xml:lang="nl">paraffine, klei</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2064"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2064.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2229"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2064"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2064.jpg"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>