<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2089"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2089-01.jpg"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2254"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2089-01.jpg"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2089"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2089"><dc:identifier>2089</dc:identifier><dc:description xml:lang="en">'My Hands Are My Heart' by the Mexican artist Gabriel Orozco consists of two photographs which hang one above the other. Both show the upper body and hands of a young man. In the top photograph the fingers hold a piece of clay at the level where the human heart is located. The fingers look like a ribcage, held horizontally and symmetrically, with the nails touching together. In the bottom photograph the hands are opened up and show the heart of clay that has just been kneaded, with the little fingers together and the thumbs pointing out. The thin lines of clay which have been pushed out by the fingerprints also look like ribs. 'Gabriel Orozco usually created staged photographs based on situations which he found in his own environment. He photographed an object, place or situation he found, after adding something small to it. For example, at the end of a market he left one orange on every deserted market stall. Another time he placed hand-formed balls of sand in the small hollows of an eroded rock. The objects placed in this way have a more or less self-evident relationship with their environment in these situations, but at the same time they are additions which are consciously placed. You often find sand near to rocks, but a pile of sand is never so perfectly round. Oranges are not left behind on every market stall. Orozco’s work is rooted in everyday life, but because of the artificial intervention, it acquires an unreal static atmosphere. 'In many cases the materials which Orozco uses for his interventions are fragile and transient, so that the interventions themselves are also fragile and temporary. Orozco captures these moments in his photographs and gives them a sort of eternal quality. Because of their alienating character, the photographs give the viewer the opportunity to reflect about what he is seeing. In 'My Hands Are My Heart', Orozco confronts the viewer with complex and fundamental ideas in a very simple and compact way. The hands creating this lump of clay and then showing it can be seen as a symbol for the artist. The image that he is creating is a print of himself, literally of his hands, but also of his heart and feelings. The heart he shows evokes the feeling of the kneading itself, kneading as a basic form of creation. For Orozco, the hands and the heart, material and form, art and life are inextricably linked.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>52,2 x 35,5 cm 69,1 x 53 cm (incl. passe-partout)</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">kleurenfoto</dc:type><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:created>1991</dcterms:created><dc:title>My Hands Are My Heart</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">colour photograph</dc:type><dc:creator>Gabriel Orozco</dc:creator><dc:date>1991</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'My Hands Are My Heart' van de Mexicaanse kunstenaar Gabriel Orozco bestaat uit twee foto's, die boven elkaar opgehangen worden. Beide tonen het bovenlichaam en de handen van een jongeman. Op de bovenste foto omklemmen de vingers, ter hoogte van de plaats van het menselijk hart, een stuk klei. Precies symmetrisch gehouden, horizontaal en met de nagels tegen elkaar, lijken de vingers op een ribbenkast. Op de onderste foto zijn de handen geopend. Met de pinken tegen elkaar en de duimen naar buiten tonen zij het juist geknede hart van klei. De dunne richels klei die door de vingerafdrukken naar buiten gestuwd zijn, lijken weer op ribben. 'Gabriel Orozco maakt meestal geënsceneerde foto's, gebaseerd op situaties die hij aantreft in zijn leefomgeving. Een gevonden voorwerp, plek of situatie wordt door hem gefotografeerd nadat hij iets kleins heeft toegevoegd. Hij plaatst bijvoorbeeld, na afloop van een markt, op elke verlaten kraam één sinaasappel. Een andere keer voorziet hij kleine holtes in een verweerde rots, van met de hand gevormde zandballen. De geplaatste voorwerpen hebben in deze situaties een min of meer vanzelfsprekende relatie met hun omgeving, maar tegelijkertijd zijn het bewust aangebrachte toevoegingen. Zand vind je vaak bij rotsen, maar een zandklomp is nooit zo mooi rond. Sinaasappels blijven niet op elke marktkraam achter. Orozco's werk is geworteld in het leven van alledag, maar door de kunstmatige ingreep krijgt het een verstilde, onwerkelijke sfeer. 'Vaak zijn de materialen die Orozco voor zijn ingrepen gebruikt, kwetsbaar en vergankelijk. Daardoor zijn ook de ingrepen zelf kwetsbaar en tijdelijk. Met zijn foto's fixeert Orozco deze momenten en geeft hij ze als het ware een eeuwigheidswaarde. Door hun vervreemdende karakter geven de foto's de kijker de gelegenheid zich te bezinnen op wat hij ziet. In 'My hands are my heart' confronteert Orozco de kijker op een eenvoudige en compacte manier met complexe en fundamentele gegevens. De handen die een vorm van klei maken en deze vervolgens tonen, kun je zien als symbool voor de kunstenaar. Het beeld dat hij schept is een afdruk van zichzelf; letterlijk van zijn handen, maar ook van zijn hart, van zijn gevoelens. Het hart dat hij toont, roept het gevoel van het kneden zelf op; kneden als een primaire manier van vormen. Voor Orozco zijn handen en hart, materie en vorm, kunst en leven een onlosmakelijk geheel.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>