<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2086"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2086.jpg"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2086.jpg"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2086"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2251"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2086"><dc:creator>Jean-Marc Bustamante</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Lumière no.1' by the French artist Bustamante is a black and white photograph screen printed onto perspex. The photograph, which is not completely in focus and has a coarse grain, shows a naked arm and hand, pulling the cord of a wall light. The light is on. You can see a part of the armrest of a sofa or the head of a bed diagonally across the image. 'Bustamante made a number of works which he called 'Lumières' between 1987 and 1993. The starting point for these were photographs from art and architectural books and magazines from the 1930s to the 1950s. They were photographs of interiors and school buildings, sometimes with children in the photographs. The photographs breathe an atmosphere of past times, of abandonment, melancholy and impersonal feelings and reflect a situation in such a neutral way that everyone can add their own memories. In this respect, Bustamante’s work is similar to that of the artist Christian Boltanski. As the photographs are printed onto transparent perspex and hang a little way away from the wall, they have a ghostly atmosphere. The coarse grain and huge enlargement of the photograph, which is not completely in focus, further reinforce the blurred character of the image. This way of presenting the scene corresponds to the atmosphere of the photograph. 'Bustamante made objects using very different materials. Sometimes his work seems abstract, and sometimes there are direct links with the invisible world, but they always have a neutral character. Bustamante aimed to make works which “lack any type of classification and is so simple that it does not reveal any particular characteristics or qualities.” His objects demand attention because of their physical presence, while they give the viewer the space to add their own interpretation in terms of content. Frameworks, hooks, lists and edges are important elements in Bustamante’s work. They provide a boundary between the work and its environment so that the work is enclosed. Despite the relatively flat surface of Bustamante’s works, they are clearly objects. This also applies for the Lumières, which are more than photographic images because they hang on hooks a little way away from the wall.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Lumière no.1' van de Franse kunstenaar Bustamante is een op perspex gezeefdrukte zwartwitfoto. De foto, die niet helemaal scherp is en een grove korrel heeft, toont een blote arm en hand die aan het touwtje van een wandlampje trekt. Het lampje is aan. Diagonaal in beeld zie je een stuk van de leuning van een bank of van het hoofdeinde van een bed. 'Tussen 1987 en 1993 maakt Bustamante een aantal werken die hij 'Lumières' noemt. Het uitgangspunt hiervoor zijn foto's uit kunst- en architectuurboeken en -bladen uit de jaren '30 tot '50. Het betreft foto's van interieurs en schoolgebouwen, soms met kinderen erop. De foto's ademen een sfeer van tijden die voorbij zijn, van verlatenheid, melancholie en onpersoonlijkheid. Ze geven een situatie op een dusdanig neutrale manier weer dat iedereen er zijn eigen herinnering aan kan verbinden. In dit opzicht vertoont Bustamantes werk overeenkomst met dat van de kunstenaar Christian Boltanski. Doordat de foto's op transparant perspex zijn afgedrukt en ze een eindje van de wand af worden opgehangen, krijgen ze iets schimmigs. De grove korrel, sterke uitvergroting en niet helemaal scherpe opname versterken het wazige karakter van het beeld. Deze manier van presenteren sluit aan bij de sfeer van de foto. 'Bustamante maakt objecten van zeer uiteenlopende materialen. Soms lijkt zijn werk abstract, soms heeft het directe aanknopingspunten in de zichtbare wereld, maar altijd heeft het iets neutraals. Bustamante streeft ernaar werk te maken dat "... elke typering mist en zo simpel is dat het geen bepaalde kenmerken of eigenschappen vertoont." Zijn objecten vragen aandacht door hun fysieke aanwezigheid, terwijl ze de beschouwer de ruimte bieden er zijn eigen inhoudelijke invulling aan te geven. Kaders, haken, lijsten en randen zijn belangrijke elementen in Bustamantes werk. Ze grenzen het beeld af van zijn omgeving en maken het in zichzelf besloten. Ondanks de relatieve vlakheid van Bustamantes werken, zijn het duidelijk objecten. Dat geldt ook voor de 'Lumières' die, omdat ze met haken een eindje van de wand af worden opgehangen, meer zijn dan fotografische beelden.</dc:description><dc:identifier>2086</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">zeefdruk op perspex</dc:type><dcterms:extent>174 x 144 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:date>1988</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dc:title>Lumière no.1</dc:title><dcterms:created>1988</dcterms:created><dc:type xml:lang="en">screen print on plexiglass</dc:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>