<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/108"><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:description xml:lang="en">The painting 'La main dans le sac' by the French painter Jean Dubuffet is a colourful mixture of pieces that fit together in cheerful but rather muted colours. All the elements of a street scene are depicted in levels, one above the other, as though it is a brick wall. At the bottom of the painting, a road with cars has been represented in a primitive, almost cartoon-like way, and the number plates and makes of the cars are legible and the chauffeurs can be clearly seen behind their wheels. Above this there is a pavement populated by armless little men. Further up there are shop windows with signs showing what sort of shops they are. 'Dubuffet despised art which is created in accordance with the western norms of beauty. He was not concerned with “combining colours and forms to create a pleasurable unit”, or with creating images intended for a small elite, initiated into the rules of art. He said: “The important thing is to be moved”. He collected “art brut” (raw art), including the pictorial work of children, the mentally ill and people from “primitive” societies. According to Dubuffet, these people work directly from the heart. What he valued in them are concepts such as “instinct, passion, caprice, violence, exuberance”, values which are suppressed in our western society in favour of rationality and logical thinking. He wanted to work directly from life just as naturally as they do. They are much more at one with nature than “civilized” western man who has placed himself above nature. 'In this painting Dubuffet shows, particularly in the title and the texts, that he is suspicious of the civilized world. “La main dans le sac” means “caught in the act”. “'Société la fripouille” can be translated as “society, the scoundrel”, “empoche” means “put it in your pocket”, “gredin” is “scoundrel”, “Banque l’interlope”, “the black market bank”. With a sense of humour, Dubuffet revealed the weak sides of humanity and the other side of our civilization. He opted for a childish, primitive style. The subject actually embraces the civilized world, the big city, cars, shopwindows, the business world. But it has been stripped of its lustre: the beautiful exterior has been unmasked. 'La main dans le sac' is part of a series of work on this theme under the heading “Paris-circus”.</dc:description><dc:identifier>108</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="nl">olieverf op doek</dc:type><dcterms:created>1961</dcterms:created><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:extent>165,5 x 133,5 x 5 cm (incl. lijst / frame)</dcterms:extent><dc:creator>Jean Dubuffet</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="en">oil on canvas</dc:type><dc:date>1961</dc:date><dc:title>La main dans le sac</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Het schilderij 'La main dans le sac' van de Franse schilder Jean Dubuffet is een bonte mengeling van in elkaar passende stukjes in vrolijke, maar enigszins gedempte kleuren. Alle onderdelen van een straatbeeld zijn in lagen boven elkaar afgebeeld alsof het een gemetselde muur is. Onderaan het schilderij is een rijbaan met autootjes weergegeven op een primitieve, bijna stripfiguurachtige manier. De nummerplaten en merken zijn leesbaar. De chauffeurs zijn goed zichtbaar achter hun stuurtjes. Daarboven is het trottoir, bevolkt door armloze mannetjes. Verder naar boven zijn gevels van winkels te zien met opschriften die aangeven wat voor zaken het zijn. 'Dubuffet heeft een afkeer van kunst die gemaakt is volgens de westerse schoonheidsnormen. Het gaat er niet om "kleuren en vormen samen te voegen tot een plezierig geheel", of beelden te maken die bestemd zijn voor een kleine elite, ingewijd in de regels van de kunst. "Waar het om gaat is de vervoering", zegt hij. Hij verzamelt 'art brut' (rauwe kunst), waaronder beeldend werk van kinderen, geesteszieken en mensen uit 'primitieve' samenlevingen. Volgens Dubuffet werken deze mensen direct vanuit het hart. Wat hij in hen waardeert zijn begrippen als "instinct, hartstocht, grilligheid, geweld, uitzinnigheid", waarden die in onze westerse maatschappij onderdrukt worden ten gunste van rationaliteit en logisch denken. Hij wil zelf net zo onbevangen, direct vanuit het leven werken als deze mensen. Zij zijn veel meer één met de natuur dan de 'beschaafde' westerse mens, die zichzelf daarboven heeft geplaatst. 'In dit schilderij laat Dubuffet vooral door de titel en de opschriften zien dat hij wantrouwend staat tegenover de beschaafde wereld. 'La main dans le sac' betekent 'op heterdaad'. 'Société la fripouille' kan vertaald worden met 'Maatschappij de schoft', 'empoche' betekent 'steek in je zak', 'gredin' is 'schurk', 'Banque l'interlope', 'Bank de Zwarte Handel'. Dubuffet laat met gevoel voor humor de mensheid van zijn zwakke kant en de keerzijde van onze beschaving zien. Hij kiest een kinderlijke, primitieve stijl. Het onderwerp omvat juist de geciviliseerde wereld: de grote stad, auto's, etalages, de zakenwereld. Maar ontdaan van zijn luister: de schone schijn ontmaskerd. 'La main dans le sac' maakt deel uit van een serie werken rond dit thema onder de noemer 'Paris-circus'.</dc:description></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/108"><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/108"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C449"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0108-01.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/0108-01.jpg"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>