<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2210"><dc:creator>Thomas Schütte</dc:creator><dc:type xml:lang="nl">synthetische verf op papier, latex op gips, hout</dc:type><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type><dcterms:created>1984</dcterms:created><dc:identifier>2210</dc:identifier><dc:type xml:lang="en">synthetic paint on paper, latex on plaster, wood</dc:type><dc:description xml:lang="en">'Blauer Bunker' by the German artist Thomas Schütte is a scale model of a spherical bunker with a monumental staircase and a circular gateway as the front entrance. The whole work stands on a plate based on a wooden scaffold-like construction. The bunker has been painted an even bright blue. The plate is partly covered by blue lines of paint. There are three sheets of paper painted orange with simple plant-like shapes on the walls next to and behind the bunker. ''Blauer Bunker' looks like a model for a building that could be constructed, though Schütte made it as a sculpture. The object is a work of art, as it is exhibited and does not really serve as a model. Schütte made several of these sorts of architectural models. They are intended to be conceptual models, buildings with which Schütte asks questions about the function and position of art and the artist in our contemporary culture. A bunker is a safe place in times of danger, for people, but also for works of art. However, it is also a place where you are isolated from your environment. Because of the monumental entrance, Schütte’s bunker becomes a large and impressive building, such as a museum. It is also reminiscent of 18th-century utopian architecture in which the perfect spherical shape symbolizes perfection and the sublime. With this model, Schütte raises questions with regard to the institution of the museum. It is a safe place to keep art, but how accessible is a museum, both literally and metaphorically? 'In Schütte’s model the threshold or entrance is very high and the sphere is literally inaccessible because there is no door. The entrance is an unreal entrance. The sheets of paper on the walls are in stark contrast to the bunker, orange versus blue, fragile nature versus powerful architecture. The presentation of both has a provisional character. The sheets of paper are only attached to the walls at the top, and the bottom is slightly curled over. The wooden construction on which the bunker is placed looks as though it has been very quickly put together and painted in a rather nonchalant way. Schütte provides us with a suggestion, a sketch, not a definitive answer.</dc:description><dc:date>1984</dc:date><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:title>Blauer Bunker</dc:title><dc:description xml:lang="nl">'Blauer Bunker' van de Duitse kunstenaar Thomas Schütte is een schaalmodel voor een bolvormige bunker met een monumentale trap en een cirkelvormige poort als voorportaal. Het geheel staat op een plaat die rust op een houten schraagachtige constructie. De bunker is egaal felblauw geschilderd. De plaat is gedeeltelijk met blauwe verfstreken bedekt. Aan de wanden naast en achter de bunker hangen drie oranje geschilderde vellen papier waarop eenvoudige plantaardige vormen te zien zijn. ''Blauer Bunker' lijkt een model voor een gebouw dat uitgevoerd zou kunnen worden. Schütte maakt het echter als sculptuur. Het object zoals het gepresenteerd wordt is het kunstwerk; het dient niet werkelijk als maquette. Schütte maakt meer van dit soort architectuurmodellen. Ze zijn bedoeld als 'denkmodellen': gebouwen waarmee Schütte vragen stelt over de functie en de positie van de kunst en de kunstenaar in onze huidige cultuur. Een bunker is een veilig oord in tijden van gevaar, voor mensen, maar ook voor kunstwerken. Het is echter ook een plek waarin je afgezonderd bent van je omgeving. Door de monumentale entree wordt Schüttes bunker een groot en indrukwekkend gebouw zoals een museum. Het doet ook denken aan achttiende eeuwse utopische architectuur. De perfecte bolvorm staat daar symbool voor het volmaakte en het sublieme. 'Met zijn model roept Schütte vragen op ten aanzien van het instituut museum. Het is een veilige plek om kunst te bewaren, maar hoe toegankelijk is het museum, letterlijk en figuurlijk? In Schüttes model is de drempel, de entree, zeer hoog en de bol letterlijk ontoegankelijk omdat er geen deur in zit. De entree is een schijnentree. De vellen papier aan de wanden contrasteren sterk met de bunker: oranje tegenover blauw, fragiele natuur tegenover krachtige architectuur. De presentatie van beide heeft iets provisorisch. De vellen papier zijn alleen aan de bovenkant vastgemaakt aan de muur, de onderkant krult iets op. De houtconstructie waarop de bunker staat, lijkt even gauw in elkaar gezet en nonchalant beschilderd. Schütte biedt ons een voorstel, een schets, geen definitief antwoord.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>(3x) ca. 200 x 157 cm, (1x) 161 x 108 x 126 cm</dcterms:extent></edm:ProvidedCHO><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2210"><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2210.JPG"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2210"/><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2210.JPG"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2374"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/></ore:Aggregation></rdf:RDF>