<rdf:RDF xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:nave="http://schemas.delving.eu/nave/terms/" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/aggregation/van-abbe-museum/2175"><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2175.JPG"/><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/portal/rights/rr-f.html"/><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2175"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://mediabank.vanabbemuseum.nl/website/Artworks/2175.JPG"/><edm:provider>Rijksdienst voor het Cultureel Erfgoed</edm:provider><edm:dataProvider>Van Abbemuseum</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://vanabbemuseum.nl/details/collectie/?lookup%5B41%5D%5Bfilter%5D%5B0%5D=id:C2339"/></ore:Aggregation><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.collectienederland.nl/resource/document/van-abbe-museum/2175"><dc:type xml:lang="en">etched glass, wood</dc:type><dc:title>Untitled</dc:title><dc:rights>Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven</dc:rights><dc:creator>Matt Mullican</dc:creator><dc:date>1992</dc:date><dc:description xml:lang="en">This work comprises seven rectangular plates of glass and seven tables made of ash. The glass plates can be set up separately against one or more walls of the exhibition space with one of the short sides standing on the ground, but they can also serve as a table top. Each time that the work is exhibited, Mullican determines the place and position of the glass plates again. Tables without a tabletop are not set up. There is a picture etched into the glass plates. One plate shows a piece of nature: a landscape with dunes and a plant, as well as a cross section of the soil. The other illustrations consist of pictograms or signs reminiscent of these. There is always a “central field”, a “frame” and connections between them with perpendicular, diagonal or curved lines. Some of the signs are recognizable pictograms, such as a lock, a telephone and a shaft of lightning, while others are completely abstract. 'From the 1970s Mullican worked on the development of his own cosmology. Everything that was part of the world, whether material or immaterial, was given a place in this. Mullican divided it into five levels. The first level is concerned with unformed material, the elements, a primal condition, while the fifth level comprises thinking, the mind, the personal. The levels between these are stages in which man has a greater or lesser grasp of the things around him, in which he experiences things that are present only as being present, or assigns a meaning to them, arranges them, forms them and codes them. In his work, Mullican gives a visual translation of his cosmology using all sorts of materials and techniques for this, from objects which he found to pictograms and diagrams or charts which he designed himself. 'Sometimes Mullican integrated his work in public spaces. For example, the etched glass plates in 'Untitled' are examples of diagrams or charts that he designed. The lines on these can be read as various connecting paths from the middle to the edge. At the same time, they form patterns which continue from one chart to the next when they are placed side by side. In this way there is interaction between the different parts. In his works, Mullican usually refers to the different levels within his cosmology. The plate with the landscape refers to the lowest levels, to existing situations. With his charts and pictograms he referred to the higher levels in which man uses signs and codes. By using a neutral iconography (the pictograms and diagrams) Mullican’s work looks objective. However, it is a representation of a very personal view, of the relationship between man and the world.</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="nl">Dit werk omvat zeven rechthoekige glasplaten en zeven tafels van esdoornhout. De glasplaten kunnen los tegen één of meer wanden van de tentoonstellingsruimte opgesteld worden, waarbij een van de korte zijden op de grond staat; ze kunnen ook als tafelblad dienen. Elke keer dat het werk tentoongesteld wordt bepaalt Mullican opnieuw de plaats en positie van de glasplaten. Tafels zonder blad worden niet opgesteld. In de glasplaten is een afbeelding geëtst. Op één plaat is een stukje natuur te herkennen: een duinachtig landschap met een plant en een dwarsdoorsnede van de bodem. De overige afbeeldingen bestaan uit pictogrammen of tekens die daaraan doen denken. Er is telkens een 'middenveld', een 'omlijsting' en verbindingen daartussen via loodrechte, diagonale of kromme lijnen. Sommige tekens zijn herkenbare pictogrammen zoals een hangslot, een telefoon en een bliksemschicht, andere zijn volkomen abstract. 'Sinds het midden van de jaren zeventig houdt Mullican zich bezig met de ontwikkeling van een eigen kosmologie. Alles wat deel uitmaakt van de wereld, materieel of immaterieel, krijgt hierin een plaats. Mullican maakt een indeling in vijf niveaus. Het eerste niveau heeft betrekking op de ongevormde materie, de elementen, een oertoestand. Het vijfde niveau omvat het denken, de geest, het persoonlijke. De niveaus ertussen zijn stadia waarin de mens meer of minder grip heeft op de dingen om zich heen. Waarin hij de aanwezige dingen slechts als aanwezig ervaart, of ze betekenis geeft, ordent, vorm geeft en codeert. Mullican geeft met zijn werk een beeldende vertaling van zijn kosmologie. Hij gebruikt hiervoor allerlei materialen en technieken, van gevonden voorwerpen tot zelf ontworpen pictogrammen en diagrammen oftewel charts. Soms integreert Mullican zijn werk in de openbare ruimte. 'De geëtste glasplaten uit 'Untitled' zijn voorbeelden van door Mullican ontworpen diagrammen of charts. De lijnen erop kunnen gelezen worden als diverse verbindingswegen van het midden naar de rand. Ze vormen tevens doorgaande patronen van de ene chart naar de andere wanneer deze naast elkaar geplaatst worden. Zo ontstaat er interactie tussen de verschillende onderdelen. Mullican verwijst in zijn werken meestal naar de verschillende niveaus binnen zijn kosmologie. De plaat met het landschap verwijst naar de laagste niveaus, naar bestaande situaties. Met zijn charts en pictogrammen verwijst hij naar de hogere niveaus, waarin de mens zich bedient van tekens en codes. Door gebruik te maken van een neutrale beeldtaal (de pictogrammen en diagrammen) ziet Mullicans werk er objectief uit. Het is echter de weergave van een zeer persoonlijke kijk op de relatie tussen mens en wereld.</dc:description><dcterms:extent>(7x) 203,5 x 102 cm, (7x) 79 x 105,5 x 207 cm</dcterms:extent><dc:type xml:lang="nl">geëtst glas, hout</dc:type><dcterms:created>1992</dcterms:created><dc:identifier>2175</dc:identifier><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></edm:ProvidedCHO></rdf:RDF>